<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2663 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2663.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2782 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3561 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3561.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3629 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3686 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3686.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3826 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3826.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3986 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4634 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4634.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5234 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5245 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5869 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5869.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5890 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5890.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5891 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5891.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6781 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6781.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6895 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6895.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6940 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6940.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6979 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6979.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7748 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7748.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8032 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8032.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9458 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9458.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9498 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9498.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-schanzen-r5n-07" ipr="trust200902" obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The R5N Distributed Hash Table">
      The R5N Distributed Hash Table
    </title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schanzen-r5n-07"/>
    <author fullname="Martin Schanzenbach" initials="M." surname="Schanzenbach">
      <organization>Fraunhofer AISEC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Lichtenbergstrasse 11</street>
          <city>Garching</city>
          <code>85748</code>
          <country>DE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>martin.schanzenbach@aisec.fraunhofer.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Christian Grothoff" initials="C." surname="Grothoff">
      <organization>Berner Fachhochschule</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Hoeheweg 80</street>
          <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
          <code>2501</code>
          <country>CH</country>
        </postal>
        <email>grothoff@gnunet.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Bernd Fix" initials="B." surname="Fix">
      <organization>GNUnet e.V.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Boltzmannstrasse 3</street>
          <city>Garching</city>
          <code>85748</code>
          <country>DE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>fix@gnunet.org</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Independent Stream</workgroup>
    <keyword>distributed hash tables</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document contains the R<sup>5</sup>N DHT technical specification.
        R<sup>5</sup>N is a secure distributed hash table (DHT) routing algorithm
        and data structure for decentralized applications.
        It features an open peer-to-peer overlay routing mechanism which supports ad-hoc
        permissionless participation and support for topologies in restricted-route
        environments. Optionally, the paths data takes through the overlay can be
	recorded, allowing decentralized applications to use the DHT to discover routes.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines the normative wire format of protocol messages,
        routing algorithms, cryptographic routines and security considerations for
        use by implementers.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification was developed outside the IETF and does not have IETF
        consensus. It is published here to guide implementation of R<sup>5</sup>N and to
        ensure interoperability among implementations including the pre-existing
        GNUnet implementation.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        This specification describes the protocol of R<sup>5</sup>N.
        R<sup>5</sup>N is a Distributed Hash Table (DHT). The name is an acronym for
        "randomized recursive routing for restricted-route
        networks" and its first academic description can be found in
        <xref target="R5N"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        DHTs are a key data structure for the construction of decentralized applications
        and generally provide a robust and efficient means to distribute the
        storage and retrieval of key-value pairs.
      </t>
      <t>
        The core idea behind R<sup>5</sup>N is to combine a randomized routing
        algorithm with an efficient, deterministic closest-peer algorithm.
        This allows us to construct an algorithm that is able to escape and circumvent
        restricted route environments while at the same time allow for a logarithmically bounded
        routing complexity.
      </t>
      <t>
        R<sup>5</sup>N also includes advanced features like recording the path a
	key-value pair took
        through the network, response filters and on-path application-specific data
        validation.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines the normative wire format of peer-to-peer
        messages, routing algorithms, cryptographic routines and security
        considerations for use by implementors.
      </t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Notation</name>
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
          when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>System Model</name>
        <t>
          DHTs usually operate as overlay networks consisting of peers
          communicating over the existing Internet. Hence canonical
          DHT designs often assume that the IP protocol provides the
          peers of the overlay with unrestricted end-to-end pairwise
          connectivity.  However, in practice, firewalls and network
          address translation (NAT) <xref target="RFC2663"/> make it
          difficult for peers operating on consumer end-devices to
          communicate directly, especially in the absence of core
          network infrastructure enabling NAT traversal via protocols
          such as interactive connectivity establishment (ICE) <xref target="RFC5245"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Furthermore, not all peer-to-peer networks consistently
          operate over the Internet, such as mobile ad-hoc networks
          (MANETs). While routing protocols have been designed for
          such networks (<xref target="RFC3561"/>), these generally
          have issues with security in the presence of malicious
          participants, as they vulnerable to impersonation attacks.
          The usual solution to these issues is to assert that the
          entire MANET is a closed network and to require
          authentication on all control messages. In contrast, the
          system model for R<sup>5</sup>N is that of an open network
          without any kind of authorities that could restrict access
          to trusted participants.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default" anchor="security_model">
        <name>Security Model</name>
        <t>
          We assume that the network is open and thus a fraction of
          the participating peers is malicious.  Malicious peers may
          create, alter, delay or drop messages.  We also assume that
          an adversary can control (or fake) many peers <xref target="Sybil"/>, thus any kind
          of voting or punishment of malicious peers would be rather
          pointless.
        </t>
        <t>
          Honest peers are expected to establish and maintain many
          connections. We assume that, as a result, the adversary is
          generally unable to prevent honest peers from maintaining a
          sufficient number of direct connections with other honest
          peers to achieve acceptable performance.  As the number of
          malicious peers and their connections increases, performance
          of the system should gracefully degrade and
          only collapse for peers that an adversary has fully isolated
          from the benign network.
        </t>
        <t>
          The main security objectives are to provide honest nodes with
          correct results and to limit the propagation of invalid
          data.  Invalid data includes both invalid key-value pairs as
          well as invalid routing path data.
          While malicious nodes may make up arbitrary
          key-value pairs and paths within the adversary's domain,
          invalid key-value pairs are ideally
          discarded at the first honest node and path data
          honestly states entry- and exit-points
          from the honest network and the subset of malicious nodes.
        </t>
        <t>
          Malicious nodes may attempt to exhaust the
          storage capacity of honest nodes by distributing well-formed
          but possibly otherwise useless application data. We assume
          that storage space is relatively cheap compared to bandwidth
          and that honest nodes also frequently republish the useful
          data that they publish. As a result, an adversary
          may reduce the effectiveness and longevity of
          data cached in the DHT but is assumed to not be able to
          effectively prevent publication and retrieval of application
          data by honest nodes.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="terminology">
    <name>Terminology</name>
    <dl>
      <dt>Address</dt>
      <dd>
        <t>
         An <em>address</em> is a UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629"/> string which can be
         used to address a <em>peer</em> through the Underlay (<xref target="underlay"/>).
         The format of an address is not enforced by this specification
         but it is expected that in most cases the address is a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
        </t>
      </dd>
      <dt>Applications</dt>
      <dd>
        <em>Applications</em> are higher-layer components which use the
        <em>Core Operations</em> directly.
        Possible <em>applications</em> include the GNU Name System
        <xref target="RFC9498"/> and the GNUnet
	Confidential Ad-hoc Decentralized End-to-End Transport (CADET)
        <xref target="cadet"/>.
      </dd>
      <dt>Core Operations</dt>
      <dd>
        The <em>Core Operations</em> provide an interface to the
        core operations of the DHT overlay to <em>applications</em>.
        This includes storing <em>blocks</em> in the DHT and retrieving
	<em>blocks</em> from the DHT.
      </dd>
      <dt>Block</dt>
      <dd>
        A unit of payload of variable-size stored in the DHT
        under a <em>key</em>.
        In the context of &quot;key-value stores&quot; this
        refers to &quot;value&quot; stored under a <em>key</em>.
      </dd>
      <dt>Block Storage</dt>
      <dd>
        The <em>block storage</em> component is used to persist and manage
        <em>blocks</em> stored by <em>peers</em>.
        It includes logic for enforcing storage quotas, caching strategies and
        block validation.
      </dd>
      <dt>Block Type</dt>
      <dd>
        A unique 32-bit value identifying the data format of a <em>block</em>.
        <em>Block types</em> are public and applications that require
        application-specific
        block payloads are expected to register one or more
        block types in the GANA Block-Type registry
        (<xref target="gana_block_type"/>) and provide a specification
        of the associated block operations (<xref
        target="block_functions"/>) to implementors of
        R<sup>5</sup>N.
      </dd>
      <dt>Bootstrapping</dt>
      <dd>
        <em>Bootstrapping</em> is the process of establishing a connection
	to the peer-to-peer network.
        It requires an initial, non-empty set of reachable <em>peers</em> and corresponding
        <em>addresses</em> to connect to that are supported by the implementation.
      </dd>
      <dt>Initiator</dt>
      <dd>
        The <em>peer</em> that initially creates and sends a DHT protocol message (<xref target="p2p_hello"/>,
        <xref target="p2p_put"/>, <xref target="p2p_get"/>, <xref target="p2p_result"/>).
      </dd>
      <dt>HELLO block</dt>
      <dd>
        A type of <em>block</em> that is used to store and retrieve <em>addresses</em> of a <em>peer</em>.
        It is used by the peer discovery mechanism in <xref target="find_peer"/>.
      </dd>
      <dt>HELLO URL</dt>
      <dd>
        <tt>HELLO</tt> blocks represented as URLs.
        They are used for out-of-band exchanges of <em>peer</em> <em>addresses</em>
        and for signalling address updates to <em>neighbours</em>.
        Implementation details and examples are in <xref target="hello_url"/>.
      </dd>
      <dt>Key</dt>
      <dd>
        The 512-bit identifier of a location in the DHT. Multiple <tt>blocks</tt> can be
        stored under the same <em>key</em>. A <em>peer identity</em> is also a <tt>key</tt>.
      </dd>
      <dt>Message Processing</dt>
      <dd>
        The <em>message processing</em> component of the DHT implementation processes
	requests from and generates responses to <em>applications</em>
	and the <em>underlay interface</em>.
      </dd>
      <dt>Neighbor</dt>
      <dd>
        A neighbor is a <em>peer</em> which is directly able to communicate
        with our <em>peer</em> via the <em>underlay interface</em>.
      </dd>
      <dt>Peer</dt>
      <dd>
        A host that is participating in the overlay by running an implementation
	of the DHT protocol.  Each participating host is
        responsible for holding some portion of the data that has been
        stored in the overlay, and they are responsible for routing
        messages on behalf of other <em>peers</em> by following the <em>routing
        algorithm</em>.
      </dd>
      <dt>Peer Identity</dt>
      <dd>
        The identifier used on the overlay
        to identify a <em>peer</em>.  It is a SHA-512 hash of the <em>peer public key</em>.
      </dd>
      <dt>Peer Public Key</dt>
      <dd>
        The the key used to authenticate
        a <em>peer</em> in the underlay.
      </dd>
      <dt>Routing</dt>
      <dd>
        The <em>routing</em> component includes the routing table as well as
        routing and <em>peer</em> selection logic. It facilitates R<sup>5</sup>N routing
        by provoding the required data structures and algorithms.
      </dd>
      <dt>Underlay Interface</dt>
      <dd>
        The <em>underlay interface</em> is an abstraction layer on top of the
        supported links of a <em>peer</em>. Peers may be linked by a variety of
        different transports including "classical" protocols such as
        TCP, UDP and TLS or higher-layer protocols such as GNUnet, I2P or Tor.
	<!-- FIXME: add references to GNUnet/I2P/Tor here! -->
      </dd>
    </dl>
    </section>
    <section numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Motivation</name>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Restricted-route topologies</name>
        <t>
          Restricted-route topologies emerge when a connected underlay
          topology prevents or restricts direct connections between
          some of the nodes.  This commonly occurs through the use of
          NAT (<xref target="RFC2663"/>).  Nodes operated behind a NAT
          cause common DHT routing algorithms such as Kademlia <xref
          target="Kademlia"/> to exhibit degraded performance or even
          to fail.  While excluding such nodes is an option, this
          limits load distribution and is ineffective for some
          networks such as MANETs.
        </t>
        <t>
          In general, nodes may not be able to reach each other (for example
          due to a firewall or NAT) despite being <em>neighbours</em>
          according to the routing table construction algorithm of a
          particular DHT.  For example, Kademlia uses the XOR metric
          and would generally connect nodes that have peer identities
          with a small XOR distance. However, the XOR distance between
          randomly assigned peer identities is completely
          divorced from the ability of the nodes to directly
          communicate.  DHTs usually use greedy routing to store data
          at the peer(s) closest to the key.  In cases where a DHT
          cannot connect peers according to the construction rules of
          its routing algorithm, the topology may end up with
          multiple local minima for a given key.  Using canonical
          greedy routing from a particular fixed location in the
          network, a node may only be able to publish and
          retrieve data in the proximity of its local minima.
        </t>
        <t>
          R<sup>5</sup>N addresses this problem by doing a random
          walk before a classical, deterministic XOR-based routing.
          The optimal number of random hops
          is equal to the mixing time of the graph, which is well known
          for various graphs. For small-world
          networks <xref target="Smallworld"/>, the mixing time has
          been shown to be around <tt>O(log n)</tt> where <tt>n</tt>
          is the number of nodes in the network
          <xref target="Smallworldmix"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Thus, if the network exhibits the properties of a small
          world topology <xref target="Smallworld"/>, a random walk of
          length <tt>O(log n)</tt> will cause the algorithm to land on
          a random node in the network.  Consequently, the
          deterministic part of the algorithm will encounter a random
          local minimum.  It is then possible to repeat this process
          in order to store or retrieve data in the context of all or
          at least multiple local minima.  The ideal length of the
          random walk and the number of repetitions expected to cover
          all local minima depends on the network topology.  Our
          design assumes that the benign subset of the network forms a
          small-world topology <xref target="Smallworld"/> and then
          obtains an estimate of the current number of nodes
          <tt>n</tt> in the network and then uses <tt>log n</tt> for
          the actual length of the random walk.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Key differences to RELOAD</name>
        <t>
	  <xref target="RFC6940"/> specifies the RELOAD DHT.  The R<sup>5</sup>N DHT
	  described in this document differs from RELOAD in its objectives
	  and thus in its design.
          The authors of RELOAD make the case that P2P networks are often established
          among a set of peers that do not trust each other.
          It addresses this issue by requiring that node identifiers
          are either assigned by a central authority, or self-issued in the case of closed networks.
          In other words, by enforcing the P2P network to be established among a set
          of <em>trusted</em> peers.
          This misses the point that this openness is a core requirement of efficient and
          useful DHTs as they serve a fundamental part in a decentralized network
          infrastructure.
          R<sup>5</sup>N, by contrast, is intended for open
	  overlay networks, and thus does not include a central enrollment server to
	  certify participants and does not limit participation in another way.
          As participants could be malicious, R<sup>5</sup>N
	  includes on-path customizable key-value validation to delete malformed
	  data and path randomiziation
	  to help evade malicious peers. R<sup>5</sup>N also expects to perform
	  over a network where not every peer can communicate with every other peer,
	  and where thus its route discovery feature provides utility to higher-level
	  applications.  As a result, both the features and the security properties
	  of RELOAD and R<sup>5</sup>N are different, except in that both allow
	  storing and retrieving key-value pairs.
	        <!--
          2023/08/20 CG: I believe the above text addresses the comments from MSC below ...

          2022/12/23 MSC: I moved references to rfc6940 to security considerations.
          I think we should talk about R5N in the positive here only, not about
          RELOAD in the negative.

          - Lean. Can be implemented. Not overengineered.
          - Path tracking (more difficult) -> Not built in
          - Certificates central server ?
          - "self-signed certificates can be used in closed networks."
          - "Security Framework:  A P2P network will often be established among a
      set of peers that do not trust each other.  RELOAD leverages a
      central enrollment server to provide credentials for each peer,
      which can then be used to authenticate each operation.  This
          greatly reduces the possible attack surface." bizarre statement.
          - For a PUT, reload requires that
          "Each element is signed by a credential which is authorized to
      write this Kind at this Resource-ID.  If this check fails, the
      request <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be rejected with an Error_Forbidden error."
        -->
        <!--FIXME: Here we should also cite and discuss RELOAD (https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc6940)
        and establish why we need this spec and are not a "Topology plugin"
        in RELOAD. The argumentation revolves around the trust model (openness) and
        security aspects (path signatures).-->

        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Overview</name>
      <t>
        In R<sup>5</sup>N peers provide to their applications
        the two fundamental core operations of any DHT:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <tt>PUT</tt>: This operation stores a block
	  under a key on one or more peers with
          the goal of making the block availiable for queries using the <tt>GET</tt> operation.
          In the classical definition of a dictionary interface, this operation would be
          called "insert".
        </li>
        <li>
          <tt>GET</tt>: This operation queries the network of peers for any number of blocks
          previously stored under or near a key.
          In the classical definition of a dictionary interface, this operation would be
          called "find".
        </li>
      </ul>
      <t>
	An example for possible semantics of the above operations
	provided as an API to applications by an implementation are
	outlined in <xref target="overlay"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        A peer does not necessarily need to expose the above
        operations to applications, but it commonly will.  A
        peer that does not expose the above operations could
        be a host purely used for bootstrapping,
	routing or supporting
        the overlay network with resources.
      </t>
      <t>
	Similarly, there could be hosts on the network that
	participate in the DHT but do not route traffic or store
	data. Examples for such hosts would be mobile devices with
	limited bandwidth, battery and storage capacity.  Such hosts
	may be used to run applications that use the DHT. However, we
	will not refer to such hosts as peers.
      </t>
      <t>
        In a trivial scenario where there is only one peer (on the local host),
        R<sup>5</sup>N operates similarly to a dictionary data structure.
        However, the default use case is one where nodes communicate directly and
        indirectly in order to realize a distributed storage mechanism.
        This communication requires a lower-level peer addressing and message transport
        mechanism such as TCP/IP.
        R<sup>5</sup>N is agnostic to the underlying transport protocol which is why
        this document defines a common addressing and messaging interface in
        <xref target="underlay"/>.
        The interface provided by this underlay is used across the specification of the
        R<sup>5</sup>N protocol.
        It also serves as a set of requirements of possible transport mechanisms that
        can be used to implement R<sup>5</sup>N with.
        That being said, common transport protocols such as TCP/IP or UDP/IP and their
        interfaces are suitable R<sup>5</sup>N underlays and are used as such by existing
        implementations.
      </t>
      <!-- consider moving some of this back into sec considerations -->
      <t>
        Specifics about the protocols of the underlays implementing
        the underlay interface or the applications
        using the DHT are out of the scope of this document.
      </t>
      <t>
        To establish an initial connection to a network of
        R<sup>5</sup>N peers, at least one initial, addressable
        peer is required as part of the
        bootstrapping process.  Further peers,
        including neighbors, are then learned via a peer
        discovery process as defined in <xref target="find_peer"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Across this document, the functional components of an
        R<sup>5</sup>N implementation are divided into
        routing (<xref target="routing"/>), message
        processing (<xref target="p2p_messages"/>) and
        block storage (<xref target="blockstorage"/>).
 <xref target="figure_r5n_arch"/> illustrates
        the architectural overview of R<sup>5</sup>N.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="figure_r5n_arch" title="The R5N architecture.">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
             |  +-----------------+  +-------+
Applications |  | GNU Name System |  | CADET |  ...
             |  +-----------------+  +-------+
-------------+------------------------------------ Core Operations
             |  ^
             |  |   +---------------+
             |  |   | Block Storage |
             |  |   +---------------+
             |  |    ^
R5N          |  v    v
             | +--------------------+    +---------+
             | | Message Processing |<-->| Routing |
             | +--------------------+    +---------+
             |  ^                          ^
             |  v                          v
-------------+------------------------------------ Underlay Interface
             | +--------+  +--------+  +----------+
             | |GNUnet  |  |IP      |  | QUIC     |
Connectivity | |Underlay|  |Underlay|  | Underlay | ...
             | |Link    |  |Link    |  | Link     |
             | +--------+  +--------+  +----------+
]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section anchor="underlay" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Underlay</name>
      <t>
        A peer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> support one or more underlay
        protocols.
        Peers supporting multiple underlays effectively
        create a bridge between different networks.  How peers are
        addressed in a specific underlay is out of scope of this
        document.  For example, a peer may have a TCP/IP address, or
        expose a QUIC endpoint, or both.  While the specific addressing options
        and mechanisms are out of scope for this document,
        it is necessary to define a
        universal addressing format in order to facilitate the
        distribution of address information to other
        peers in the DHT overlay.
        This standardized format
        is the HELLO block (described in <xref
        target="hello_block"/>), which contains sets of addresses.
        If the address is a URI, it may indicate which
        underlay understands the respective address.
      </t>
      <!--
        1) The current API is always fire+forget, it doesn't allow for flow
        control. I think we need to add that, possibly for sending and receiving.

        IDK.
	CG: I think we should not have flow control for the DHT; overkill,
	should instead simply define transmission as unreliable.

        2) I'm not sure what to do with the crypto: mandate EdDSA or allow the
        underlay to do whatever public keys it likes.

        We need keys in the overlay. (Path signatures). Do they need to
        be the same keys???

        CG: I'd mandate EdDSA. CONG will have mitigation to establish
	EdDSA keys over libp2p, even if libp2p does not use EdDSA. But,
	that said, I'm not sure if we should even mandate AE on the
	underlay.

        3) I think we may want to mandate that the lower layer at least
        authenticate the other peer (i.e. every UDP message could be in
        cleartext, but would need to come with an EdDSA signature, alas 92 byte
        overhead and a signature verification _required_).  Otherwise, I don't
        see how we can offer even the most minimal protections against peer
        impersonation attacks. WDYT?

        CG: Yes, I think authentication should be mandatory, but not
        any _specific_ type of encryption.

        Security considerations? Prerequisites?
      -->
      <t>
        It is expected that the underlay provides basic mechanisms to
        manage peer connectivity and addressing.
        The essence of the underlay interface is
        captured by the following set of API calls:
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <tt>TRY_CONNECT(P, A)</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This call allows the DHT implementation to signal to the
          underlay that the DHT wants to establish a connection to the
          target peer <tt>P</tt> using the given address <tt>A</tt>.
          If the connection attempt is successful, information on the
          new peer connection will be offered through the
          <tt>PEER_CONNECTED</tt> signal.
       <!--
          Underlay implementations
          can ignore calls with addresses they do not support.
        -->
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <tt>HOLD(P)</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This call tells the underlay to hold on to a connection
          to a peer <tt>P</tt>.  Underlays are usually limited in the number
	  of active connections.  With this function the DHT can indicate to the
	  underlay which connections should preferably be preserved.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <tt>DROP(P)</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This call tells the underlay to drop the connection to a
          peer <tt>P</tt>.  This call is only there for symmetry and
	  used during the peer's shutdown to release all of the remaining
	  <tt>HOLDs</tt>.
	  <!-- FIXME: are we supposed to call DROP if a peer disconnects?
               NOTE: That would seem to be an implementation detail beyond what needs
               to be in the RFC. An API may mandate DROP on disconnect, or
               it may simply state that when the underlay signals a
               disconnect, all holds are automatically dropped.
          -->
	  As R<sup>5</sup>N always prefers the longest-lived
	  connections, it would never drop an active connection that it
	  has called <tt>HOLD()</tt> on before. Nevertheless, underlay implementations
	  should not rely on this always being true.  A call to <tt>DROP()</tt> also
	  does not imply that the underlay must close the connection: it merely
	  removes the preference to preserve the connection that was established
	  by <tt>HOLD()</tt>.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <tt>SEND(P, M)</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This call allows the local peer to send a protocol message
          <tt>M</tt> to a peer <tt>P</tt>.  Sending messages is expected
          to be done on a best-effort basis, thus the underlay does not
          have to guarantee delivery or message ordering. If the underlay
          implements flow- or congestion-control, it may
          discard messages to limit its queue size.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <tt>ESTIMATE_NETWORK_SIZE() -> L2NSE</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This call must return an estimate of the network size.  The
          resulting <tt>L2NSE</tt> value must be the base-2 logarithm
          of the <em>estimated</em> number of peers in the network.
          This estimate is used by the routing algorithm.  If the underlay does
          not support a protocol for network size estimation (such as
          <xref target="NSE"/>) the value is assumed to be provided as
          a configuration parameter to the underlay implementation.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      <t>
        The above calls are meant to be actively executed by the
        implementation as part of the peer-to-peer protocol.  In
        addition, the underlay creates <em>signals</em> to drive
        updates of the routing table, local storage and message
        processing (<xref target="p2p_messages"/>). Specifically,
        the underlay is expected to emit the following
        signals (usually implemented as callbacks) based on network
        events observed by the underlay implementation:
      </t>
      <dl>
        <dt>
          <tt>PEER_CONNECTED -> P</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This signal allows the DHT to react to a newly connected
          peer <tt>P</tt>.  Such an event triggers, for example,
          updates in the routing table and gossiping of HELLOs to that
          peer.  Underlays may include meta-data about the connection,
          for example to indicate that the connection is from a
          resource-constrained host that does not intend to function
          as a full peer and thus should not be considered
          for routing.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <tt>PEER_DISCONNECTED -> P</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This signal allows the DHT to react to a recently
          disconnected peer.  Such an event primarily triggers updates
          in the routing table.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <tt>ADDRESS_ADDED -> A</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          The underlay signals indicates that an address <tt>A</tt>
          was added for our local peer and that henceforth the peer
          may be reachable under this address.  This information is
          used to advertise connectivity information about the local
          peer to other peers.  <tt>A</tt> is an
          address suitable for inclusion in a <tt>HELLO</tt> payload
          <xref target="hello_block"/>.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <tt>ADDRESS_DELETED -> A</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This underlay signal indicates that an address <tt>A</tt>
          was removed from the set of addresses the local peer is
          possibly reachable under. The signal is used
          to stop advertising this address to other peers.
        </dd>
        <dt>
          <tt>RECEIVE -> (P, M)</tt>
        </dt>
        <dd>
          This signal informs the local peer that a protocol
          message <tt>M</tt> was received from a peer <tt>P</tt>.
        </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section anchor="routing" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Routing</name>
      <t>
        To enable routing, any R<sup>5</sup>N implementation must keep
	information about its current set of neighbors.
        Upon receiving a connection notification from the
	underlay interface through a
        <tt>PEER_CONNECTED</tt> signal, information on the new neighbor
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be added to the routing table, except if the
	respective <tt>k</tt>-bucket in the routing table is full or if meta-data
	is present that indicates that the peer does not wish to participate
	in routing.
        Peers added to the routing table <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be signalled to the
        underlay as important connections using a <tt>HOLD()</tt> call.
        Similarly when a disconnect is indicated by the underlay through
        a <tt>PEER_DISCONNECTED</tt> signal, the peer
        <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be removed from the routing table.
	  <!-- FIXME: are we supposed to call DROP if we called HOLD if a peer disconnects!?? -->
      </t>
      <t>
        To achieve logarithmically bounded routing performance,
        the data structure for managing neighbors and their
        metadata <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be implemented using the k-buckets concept of
        <xref target="Kademlia"/>  as defined in <xref target="routing_table"/>.
        Maintenance of the routing table (after bootstrapping) is
        described in <xref target="find_peer"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Unlike <xref target="Kademlia"/>, routing decisions in
        R<sup>5</sup>N are also influenced by a Bloom filter in the message
        that prevents routing loops. This data structure is discussed in
	<xref target="routing_bloomfilter"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
        In order to select peers which are suitable destinations for
        routing messages, R<sup>5</sup>N uses a hybrid approach: Given
        an estimated network size <tt>L2NSE</tt> retrieved using
        <tt>ESTIMATE_NETWORK_SIZE()</tt>, the peer selection for the
        first <tt>L2NSE</tt> hops is random. After the initial
        <tt>L2NSE</tt> hops, peer selection follows an XOR-based peer
        distance calculation.
        <xref target="routing_functions"/>
        describes the corresponding routing functions.
      </t>
      <t>
        Finally, each <tt>ResultMessage</tt> is routed back along the
        path that the corresponding <tt>GetMessage</tt> took
        previously. This is enabled by tracking state per
        <tt>GetMessage</tt> in the pending table described in
        <xref target="pending_table"/>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="routing_table">
        <name>Routing Table</name>
        <t>
          Whenever a <tt>PEER_CONNECTED</tt> signal is received from
          the underlay, the respective peer is considered for
          insertion into the routing table.  The routing table
          consists of an array of <tt>k</tt>-buckets. Each
          <tt>k</tt>-bucket contains a list of neighbors.
          The i-th <tt>k</tt>-bucket stores neighbors whose peer
          public keys are between XOR-distance 2<sup>i</sup> and
          2<sup>i+1</sup> from the local peer; <tt>i</tt> can be
          directly computed from the two peer identities using the
          <tt>GetDistance()</tt> function.  System constraints will
          typically force an implementation to impose some upper limit
          on the number of neighbors kept per
          <tt>k</tt>-bucket.  Upon insertion, the implementation
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> call <tt>HOLD()</tt> on the respective
          neighor.
        </t>
        <t>
          Implementations <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> try to keep at least
          5 entries per <tt>k</tt>-bucket.  Embedded systems that cannot manage
          this number of connections <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use connection-level
          signalling to indicate that they are merely a client utilizing a
          DHT and not able to participate in routing.  DHT peers receiving
          such connections <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> include connections to
          such restricted systems in their <tt>k</tt>-buckets, thereby effectively
	  excluding them when making routing decisions.
        </t>
        <t>
          If a system hits constraints with respect to
          the number of active connections, an implementation
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> evict neighbours from those <tt>k</tt>-buckets with the
          largest number of neighbors. The eviction strategy <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
          to drop the shortest-lived connection per <tt>k</tt>-bucket first.
        </t>
        <t>
          Implementations <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> cache valid addresses of disconnected
          peers outside of the routing table and sporadically or periodically try to (re-)establish connection
          to the peer by making <tt>TRY_CONNECT()</tt> calls to the underlay interface
          if the respective <tt>k</tt>-bucket has empty slots.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="find_peer">
        <name>Peer Discovery</name>
        <t>
          Initially, implementations require at least one initial connection to a
          neighbor (signalled through
          <tt>PEER_CONNECTED</tt>).
          The first connection <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be established
          by an out-of-band exchange of the information from a
          <tt>HELLO</tt> block.
          This is commonly achieved through the
          configuration of hardcoded bootstrap peers or bootstrap
          servers either for the underlay or the R<sup>5</sup>N
          implementation.
        </t>
        <t>
          Implementations <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> have other means to achieve this
          initial connection.
          For example, implementations could allow the application or
          even end-user to provide a working <tt>HELLO</tt>
          which is then in turn used to call <tt>TRY_CONNECT()</tt> on
          the underlay in order to trigger a subsequent
          <tt>PEER_CONNECTED</tt> signal from the underlay
          interface.
          <xref target="hello_url"/> specifies
          a URL format for encoding HELLO blocks as text strings. The
          URL format thus provides a portable, human-readable,
          text-based serialization format that can, for example, be
          encoded into a QR code for dissemination.
          HELLO URLs <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be supported by implementations for
          both import and export of <tt>HELLOs</tt>.
        </t>
        <t>
          To discover additional peers for its routing table, a peer
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> initiate <tt>GetMessage</tt> requests
          (see <xref target="p2p_get"/>) asking for blocks of type
          <tt>HELLO</tt> using its own peer identity in the
          <tt>QUERY_HASH</tt> field of the message.  The
          <tt>PEER_BF</tt> field of the <tt>GetMessage</tt>
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
          initialized to filter the peer's own peer identity as well as the peer
          identities of all currently connected
          neighbors. These requests <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use
          the <tt>FindApproximate</tt> and
          <tt>DemultiplexEverywhere</tt>
          flags. <tt>FindApproximate</tt> will ensure that other peers
          will reply with results where the keys are merely considered
          close-enough, while <tt>DemultiplexEverywhere</tt> will
          cause each peer on the path to respond if it has relevant
          information. The combination of these flags is thus likely
          to yield <tt>HELLOs</tt> of peers that are useful somewhere
          in the initiator's routing table.  The <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>
          replication level to be set in the <tt>REPL_LVL</tt> field
          is 4.  The size and format of the result filter is specified
          in <xref target="hello_block"/>.  The <tt>XQUERY</tt>
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be empty.
        </t>
        <t>
          In order to facilitate peers answering requests for
          <tt>HELLOs</tt>, the underlay is expected to provide the
          implementation with addresses signalled through
          <tt>ADDRESS_ADDED</tt>. It is possible that no addresses are
          provided if a peer can only establish outgoing connections
          and is otherwise unreachable.  An implementation
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> advertise its addresses periodically to
          its neighbors through <tt>HelloMessages</tt>.  The
          advertisement interval and expiration <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
          be configurable.
          If the values are chosen at the discretion of the
          implementation, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to choose external
          factors such as expiration of DHCP leases to determine the values.
          The specific frequency of advertisements
          <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be smaller than the expiration
          period.
          It <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> additionally depend on available bandwidth,
          the set of already connected neighbors, the workload of the system and
          other factors which are at the discretion of the developer.
	  If <tt>HelloMessages</tt> are not updated before they expire,
	  peers might be unable to discover and connect to the respective
	  peer, and thus miss out on quality routing table entries. This
	  would degrade the performance of the DHT and <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
	  thus be avoided by advertising updated <tt>HELLOs</tt> before the
	  previous one expires. When using unreliable underlays, an implementation
	  <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use higher frequencies and transmit
	  more <tt>HelloMessages</tt> within an expiration interval
	  to ensure that neighbours almost always have non-expired
	  <tt>HelloMessages</tt> at their disposal even if some messages
	  are lost.
        </t>
        <t>
          Whenever a peer receives such a <tt>HelloMessage</tt>
          from another peer that is already in the routing
          table, it must cache it as long as that peer remains in its
          routing table (or until the <tt>HELLO</tt> expires) and
          serve it in response to <tt>GET</tt> requests for
          <tt>HELLO</tt> blocks (see <xref
          target="p2p_get_processing"/>).  This behaviour makes it
          unnecessary for peers to initiate dedicated
          <tt>PutMessages</tt> containing <tt>HELLO</tt> blocks.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="routing_bloomfilter">
        <name>Peer Bloom Filter</name>
        <t>
          As DHT <tt>GetMessages</tt> and <tt>PutMessages</tt>
          traverse a random path through the network for the first
          <tt>L2NSE</tt> hops, a key design objective of
          R<sup>5</sup>N is to avoid routing loops.  The peer Bloom
          filter is part of the routing metadata in messages to
          prevent circular routes. It is updated at each hop where the
          hop's peer identity derived from the peer's public key is
          added to it.
          The peer Bloom filter follows the definition in <xref target="bloom_filters"/>.
          It <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be <tt>L=1024</tt> bits
          (128 bytes) in size and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> set <tt>k=16</tt> bits per
          element.
          The set of elements <tt>E</tt> consists of of all possible 256-bit peer
          public keys and the mapping function <tt>M</tt> is defined as follows:
        </t>
        <t>
          <tt>M(e) -> SHA-512 (e) as uint32[]</tt>
        </t>
        <t>
          The element <tt>e</tt> is the peer public key which is hashed using SHA-512.
          The resulting 512-bit peer identity is interpreted as an array of k=16
          32-bit integers in network byte order which are used to set and check the bits
          in <tt>B</tt> using <tt>BF-SET()</tt> and <tt>BF-TEST()</tt>.
        </t>
        <t>
          At this size, the Bloom filter reaches a false-positive rate of
          approximately fifty percent at about 200 entries. For peer
          discovery where the Bloom filter is initially populated with
          peer identities from the local routing table, the 200
          entries would still be enough for 40 buckets assuming 5
          peers per bucket, which corresponds to an overlay network
          size of approximately 1 trillion peers. Thus,
          <tt>L=1024</tt> bits should suffice for all conceivable
          use-cases.
        </t>
        <t>
          For the next hop selection in both the random
          and the deterministic case, any peer which is in the peer
          Bloom filter for the respective message is excluded from the
          peer selection process.
          Any peer which is forwarding <tt>GetMessages</tt> or <tt>PutMessages</tt>
          (<xref target="p2p_messages"/>) thus adds its own peer public key to the
          peer Bloom filter.
          This allows other peers to (probabilistically) exclude already
          traversed peers when searching for the next hops in the routing table.
        </t>
        <t>
	  We note that the peer Bloom filter may exclude peers due to false-postive
	  matches.  This is acceptable as routing should nevertheless
	  terminate (with high probability) in close vicinity of the key. Furthermore,
	  due to the randomization of the first L2NSE hops, it is possible that
	  false-positives will be different when a request is repeated.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="routing_functions">
        <name>Routing Functions</name>
         <t>
           Using the data structures described so far,
	   the R<sup>5</sup>N routing component provides
	   the following functions for
	   message processing (<xref target="p2p_messages"/>):
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>
            <tt>GetDistance(A, B) -&gt; Distance</tt>
          </dt>
          <dd>
            This function calculates the binary XOR between A and B.
            The resulting distance is interpreted as an integer where
            the leftmost bit is the most significant bit.
          </dd>
          <dt>
            <tt>SelectClosestPeer(K, B) -&gt; N</tt>
          </dt>
          <dd>
            This function selects the neighbor <tt>N</tt> from our
            routing table with the shortest XOR-distance to the key <tt>K</tt>.
            This means that for all other peers <tt>N'</tt> in the routing table
            <tt>GetDistance(N, K) &lt; GetDistance(N',K)</tt>.
            Peers with a positive test against the peer Bloom
	    filter <tt>B</tt> are not considered.
          </dd>
          <dt>
            <tt>SelectRandomPeer(B) -&gt; N</tt>
          </dt>
          <dd>
            This function selects a random peer <tt>N</tt> from
	    all neighbors.
            Peers with a positive test in the peer Bloom
	    filter <tt>B</tt> are not considered.
          </dd>
          <dt>
            <tt>SelectPeer(K, H, B) -&gt; N</tt>
          </dt>
          <dd>
            This function selects a neighbor <tt>N</tt> depending on the
            number of hops <tt>H</tt> parameter.
            If <tt>H &lt; NETWORK_SIZE_ESTIMATE</tt>
            returns <tt>SelectRandomPeer(B)</tt>, and otherwise
            returns <tt>SelectClosestPeer(K, B)</tt>.
          </dd>
          <dt>
            <tt>IsClosestPeer(N, K, B) -&gt; true | false</tt>
          </dt>
          <dd>
            This function checks if <tt>N</tt> is the closest peer for <tt>K</tt>
            (cf. <tt>SelectClosestPeer(K, B)</tt>).
            Peers with a positive test in the Bloom filter <tt>B</tt> are not considered.
          </dd>
          <dt>
            <tt>ComputeOutDegree(REPL_LVL, HOPCOUNT, L2NSE) -&gt; Number</tt>
          </dt>
          <dd>
	    <t>
      This function computes the number of neighbors
	    that a message should be forwarded to.  The arguments
	    are the desired replication level (<tt>REPL_LVL</tt>),
	    the <tt>HOPCOUNT</tt> of the message so far and
	    and the current network size estimate (<tt>L2NSE</tt>)
	    as provided by the underlay.
            The result is the non-negative number of next hops to
	    select.  The following figure gives the
	    pseudocode for computing the number of neighbors
	    the peer should attempt to forward the message to.
	    </t>
            <figure anchor="compute_out_degree" title="Computing the number of next hops.">
              <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
ComputeOutDegree(REPL_LVL, HOPCOUNT, L2NSE):
  if (HOPCOUNT > L2NSE * 4)
    return 0;
  if (HOPCOUNT > L2NSE * 2)
    return 1;
  if (0 = REPL_LEVL)
    REPL_LEVL = 1
  if (REPL_LEVEL > 16)
    REPL_LEVEL = 16
    RM1 = REPL_LEVEL - 1
    FRAC = 1 + (RM1 / (L2NSE + RM1 * HOPCOUNT))
  return PROUND(FRAC)
]]></artwork>
            </figure>
  	    <t>
          The above calculation of <tt>FRAC</tt> may yield values that are
          not discrete.
          The result is <tt>FRAC</tt> rounded probabilistically
          (<tt>PROUND</tt>) to the nearest
	      discrete value, using the fraction
          as the probability for rounding up.
          For example, a value of <tt>3.14</tt> is rounded up to <tt>4</tt> with
          a probability of 14% and rounded down to <tt>3</tt> with a probability
          of 86%.
          This probabilistic rounding is necessary to achieve
          the statistically expected value of the replication
          level and average number of peers a message is forwarded to.
	    </t>
	  </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section anchor="pending_table">
        <name>Pending Table</name>
	<t>
	  R<sup>5</sup>N performs stateful routing where the messages
	  only carry the query hash and do not encode the ultimate
	  source or destination of the request.  Routing a request
	  towards the key is done hop-by-hop using the routing table and the
	  query hash.  The pending table is used to route responses
	  back to the originator.  In the pending table each peer
	  primarily maps a query hash to the associated
	  originator of the request.  The pending table <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
	  store entries for the last <tt>MAX_RECENT</tt> requests
    the peer has encountered.
    To ensure that the peer does
	  not run out of memory, information about older requests
    <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be discarded.
    The value of <tt>MAX_RECENT</tt> <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be configurable
    at the host level to use available memory resources without
    conflicting with other system requirements and limitations.
    <tt>MAX_RECENT</tt> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
    be at least 128 * 10<sup>3</sup>.
    If the pending table is smaller, the likelihood grows that a peer
    receives a response to a query but is unable to forward it to the
    initiator because it forgot the predecessor.  Eventually, the
    initiator would likely succeed by repeating the query.
    However, this would be much more expensive than peers having an adequately
    sized pending table.
  </t>
	<t>
	  For each entry in the pending table, the DHT
	  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> track the query key, the peer identity
	  of the previous hop, the extended query, requested block type,
	  flags, and the result filter.  If the query did not provide
	  a result filter, a fresh result filter <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
	  still be created to filter duplicate replies.  Details of
	  how a result filter works depend on the type, as described
	  in <xref target="block_functions"/>.
	</t>
	<t>
	  When a second query from the same origin for the
	  same query hash is received, the DHT <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
	  attempt to merge the new request with the state for
	  the old request.  If this is not possible (say because
	  the MUTATOR differs), the
	  existing result filter <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
	  discarded and replaced with the result
	  filter of the incoming message.
	</t>
	<t>
	  We note that for local applications, a fixed limit on
	  the number of concurrent requests may be problematic.
	  Hence, it is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that implementations
	  track requests from local applications separately and
	  preserve the information about requests from local
	  applications until the local application explicitly
	  stops the request.
	</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="p2p_messages" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Message Processing</name>
      <t>
        An implementation will process
        messages either because it needs to transmit messages as part of routing
	table maintenance, or due to requests from local applications, or
	because it received a message from a neighbor.
        If instructed through an application-facing API such as the one outlined
        in <xref target="overlay"/>, a peer acts as an initiator
	of <tt>GetMessages</tt>
        or <tt>PutMessages</tt>.
        The status of initiator is relevant for peers when processing <tt>ResultMessages</tt>
        due to the required handover of results to the application that requested
        the respective result.
      </t>
      <t>
        The implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> listen for <tt>RECEIVE(P, M)</tt> signals
        from the underlay and react to the respective messages sent by
        the peer <tt>P</tt>.
      </t>
      <t>
        Whether initiated locally or received from a neighbor, an implementation
        processes messages according to the wire formats and the required
        validations detailed in the following sections.
        Where required, the local peer public key is referred to as <tt>SELF</tt>.
      </t>
      <section anchor="message_components">
        <name>Message components</name>
	<t>
	  This section describes some data structures and fields shared
	  by various types of messages.
        </t>
        <section anchor="route_flags">
          <name>Flags</name>
          <t>
            Flags is an 8-bit vector representing binary options.
            Each flag is represented by a bit in the field starting from 0 as
            the rightmost bit to 7 as the leftmost bit.
          </t>
	  <dl>
          <dt>0: DemultiplexEverywhere</dt>
          <dd>
	    This bit indicates that each peer along the way should process the request.
            If the bit is not set, intermediate peers only route the message and only
            peers which consider themselves closest to the key (based on their
	    routing table) look for answers
            in their local storage for <tt>GetMessages</tt>, or respectively cache the
	    block in their local storage for <tt>PutMessages</tt> and <tt>ResultMessages</tt>.
          </dd>
          <dt>1: RecordRoute</dt>
          <dd>
            This bit indicates to keep track of the path that the message takes
            in the P2P network.
          </dd>
          <dt>2: FindApproximate</dt>
          <dd>
            This bit asks peers to return results even if the key
	    does not exactly match the query hash.
          </dd>
          <dt>3: Truncated</dt>
          <dd>
            This is a special flag which is set if a peer truncated the
            recorded path.
            This results in the first hop on the path to be given without a signature
            to enable checking of the next signature.
            This flag <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> be set in
            a <tt>GetMessage</tt>.
          </dd>
          <dt>4-7: Reserved</dt>
          <dd>
            The remaining bits are reserved for future use and
	    <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero when initiating an operation.
	    If non-zero bits are received, implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
	    preserve these bits when forwarding messages.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>

      <section anchor="p2p_path">
        <name>Path</name>
        <t>
          If the <tt>RecordRoute</tt> flag is set, the route of a <tt>PutMessage</tt>
          or a <tt>ResultMessage</tt> through the overlay network is recorded in the
          <tt>PATH</tt> field of the message. <tt>PATH</tt> is a list of path elements.
          A new path element (<xref target="p2p_pathelement"/>) is appended to the
          existing <tt>PATH</tt> before a peer sends the message to the next peer.
        </t>
        <t>
          A path element contains a signature and the public key of the peer that
          created the element. The signature is computed over the public keys of the
          previous peer (from which the message was received) and next peer (the
          peer the message is send to). A new message has no previous peer and
          uses all <tt>ZEROs</tt> (32 NULL-bytes) in the
          public key field when creating the signature.
        </t>
        <t>
          Assuming peer A sends a new <tt>PUT</tt> message to peer B, which forwards
          the message to peer C, which forwards to peer D which finally stores the data.
          The <tt>PATH</tt> field of the message received at peer D contains three
          path elements (build from top to bottom):
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figure_path" title="Example PATH">
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
+---------------------+-------+
| Sig A(ZEROs, Pub B) | Pub A |
+---------------------+-------+
+---------------------+-------+
| Sig B(Pub A, Pub C) | Pub B |
+---------------------+-------+
+---------------------+-------+
| Sig C(Pub B, Pub D) | Pub C |
+---------------------+-------+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          Note that the wire format of <tt>PATH</tt> (<xref target="p2p_pathelement"/>)
          will not include the last public key (Pub C in our example) as this will be
          redundant; the receiver of a message can use the public key of the sender as
          the public key to verify the last signature.
        </t>
        <t>
          The <tt>PATH</tt> is stored along with the payload data from the <tt>PUT</tt>
          message at the final peer. Note that the same payload stored at different
          peers will have a different <tt>PATH</tt> associated with it.
        </t>
        <t>
          When the storing peer delivers the data based on a <tt>GET</tt> request, it
          initializes the <tt>PATH</tt> field with the stored path value and appends
          a new path element. The first part of <tt>PATH</tt> in a <tt>GET</tt> response
          message is called the <tt>PutPath</tt>, followed
          by the <tt>GetPath</tt>. This way the combined <tt>PATH</tt> will record the
          whole route of the payload from the originating peer (initial
          <tt>PutMessage</tt>) to the requesting peer (initial <tt>GetMessage</tt>).
        </t>
        <t>
          When receiving a message with flag <tt>RecordRoute</tt> and <tt>PATH</tt>,
          a peer is encouraged to verify the integrity of <tt>PATH</tt> (if the
          available resources of the peer allow this) by checking the signatures of
          the path elements.
        </t>
        <t>
          If an invalid signature is detected, the path is truncated keeping only
          element fields following the faulty signature and setting the <tt>Truncated</tt>
          flag. Assume that peer C detects a faulty signature from peer B,
          the trunacted path has two entries:
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figure_path_truncated" title="Example truncated PATH">
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
+-------+  +----------------------+-------+
| Pub B |  | Sig C (Pub B, Pub D) | Pub C |
+-------+  +----------------------+-------+
          ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The <tt>Truncated</tt> flag indicates that the first path element does not contain
          a signature but only the public key of the peer where the signature fails.
        </t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="p2p_pathelement">
        <!-- TODO-GROTHOFF: Discuss this change again. The text is currently not correct
             it is very difficult to understand. Is it worth 32 byte;
	     CG: I've fixed the figures, tried to clarify the text. Is it OK now? -->
        <name>Path Element</name>
        <t>
          A path element represents a hop in the path a message has taken
          through the overlay network.
          The wire format of a path element is illustrated in
          <xref target="figure_pathelement"/>.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figure_pathelement" title="The Wire Format of a path element.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   SIGNATURE                   |
|                   (64 bytes)                  |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|             PRED PEER PUBLIC KEY              |
|                  (32 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
         ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>where:</t>
        <dl>
          <dt>SIGNATURE</dt>
          <dd>
            is a 64 byte EdDSA signature <xref target="ed25519"/> created
            using the current hop's private
            key which affirms the public keys of the peers from the
            previous and next hops.
          </dd>
          <dt>PRED PEER PUBLIC KEY</dt>
          <dd>
            is the EdDSA public key <xref target="ed25519"/> of the previous peer on the path.
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          An ordered list of path elements may be appended to any routed
          <tt>PutMessages</tt> or <tt>ResultMessages</tt>.
          The last signature (after which the peer public key is omitted)
	  is created by the current hop only after the peer made its routing
	  decision identifiying the successor peer. The peer public key is not
	  included after the last signature as it must be that of the sender of
	  the message and including it would thus be redundant.
	  Similarly, the predecessor of the first element of
            an untruncated path is not stated explicitly, as it must be <tt>ZERO</tt>
            (32 NULL-bytes).
        </t>
        <t>
          <xref target="figure_path_ex"/> shows the wire format of an example
          path from peer A over peers B and C and D as it would be received by peer E in the
          <tt>PUTPATH</tt> of a <tt>PutMessage</tt>, or as the combined
          <tt>PUTPATH</tt> and <tt>GETPATH</tt> of a <tt>ResultMessage</tt>.
          The wire format of the path elements allows a natural
          extension of the <tt>PUTPATH</tt> along the route of the <tt>ResultMessage</tt>
          to the destination forming the <tt>GETPATH</tt>.
          The <tt>PutMessage</tt> would indicate in the <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> field
          a length of 3.
          The <tt>ResultMessage</tt> would indicate a path length of 3 as the
          sum of the field values in <tt>PUTPATH_L</tt> and <tt>GETPATH_L</tt>.
	  Basically, the last signature does not count for the path length.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figure_path_ex" title="Example of a path as found in PutMessages or ResultMessages from Peer A to Peer D as transmitted by Peer D.">
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                  SIGNATURE A                  |
|                  (64 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|    (Over ZERO and PEER B signed by PEER A)    |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    PEER A                     |
|                  (32 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                  SIGNATURE B                  |
|                  (64 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|   (Over PEER A and PEER C signed by PEER B)   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    PEER B                     |
|                  (32 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                  SIGNATURE C                  |
|                  (64 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|   (Over PEER B and PEER D signed by PEER C)   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    PEER C                     |
|                  (32 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|             SIGNATURE D (last sig)            |
|                  (64 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|  (Over PEER C and receiver signed by PEER D)  |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
         ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

        <t>
          A path may be truncated in which case the signature of the truncated
          path element is omitted leaving only the public key of the peer preceeding
	  the truncation which is required for the
          verification of the subsequent path element signature.
          Such a truncated path is indicated with the respective
	  truncated flag (<xref target="route_flags"/>).
          For truncated paths, the peer public key of the signer of the last path element is
	  again omitted as it must be that of
          the sender of the <tt>PutMesssage</tt> or <tt>ResultMessage</tt>.  Similarly,
	  the public key of the receiving peer used in the last path element is omitted as
	  it must be SELF.
          The wire format of a truncated example path from peers B over C and D to E
          (possibly still originating at A, but the origin is unknowable to E due to truncation)
	  is illustrated in <xref target="figure_path_ex_trunc"/>.
          Here, a <tt>ResultMessage</tt> would indicate in the <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> field
          a length of 1 while
          a <tt>PutMessage</tt> would indicate a length of 1 as the sum of
          <tt>PUTPATH_L</tt> and <tt>GETPATH_L</tt> fields.
	  Basically, the truncated peer and the last signature do not count
	  for the path length.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figure_path_ex_trunc" title="Example of a truncated path from Peer B to Peer D as transmitted by Peer D.">
          <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|             PEER B (truncated)                |
|                  (32 byte)                    |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                  SIGNATURE C                  |
|                  (64 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|   (Over PEER B and PEER D signed by PEER C)   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    PEER C                     |
|                  (32 bytes)                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|            SIGNATURE D (last sig)             |
|                  (64 byte)                    |
|                                               |
|  (Over PEER C and receiver signed by PEER D)  |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
         ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
          The SIGNATURE field in a path element covers a 64-bit contextualization header, the
          the block expiration, a hash of the block
          payload, as well as the predecessor peer public key and the peer public key of the
          successor that the peer making the signature is routing the
	  message to.  Thus, the signature made by SELF basically says that
          SELF received the block payload from PEER PREDECESSOR and has forwarded
	  it to PEER SUCCESSOR.  The wire format is illustrated
          in <xref target="figure_pathelewithpseudo"/>.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figure_pathelewithpseudo" title="The Wire Format of the path element for Signing.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |       PURPOSE         |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   EXPIRATION                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                  BLOCK HASH                   |
|                  (64 byte)                    |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                PEER PREDECESSOR               |
|                    (32 byte)                  |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 PEER SUCCESSOR                |
|                    (32 byte)                  |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
         ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <dl>
          <dt>SIZE</dt>
          <dd>
            A 32-bit value containing the length of the signed data in bytes
            in network byte order.
            The length of the signed data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 144 bytes.
          </dd>
          <dt>PURPOSE</dt>
          <dd>
            A 32-bit signature purpose flag. This field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 6 (in network
            byte order).
          </dd>
          <dt>EXPIRATION</dt>
          <dd>
            denotes the absolute 64-bit expiration date of the block
            in microseconds since midnight (0 hour), January 1, 1970
            UTC in network byte order.
          </dd>
          <dt>BLOCK HASH</dt>
          <dd>
            a SHA-512 hash over the block payload.
          </dd>
          <dt>PEER PREDECESSOR</dt>
          <dd>
            the peer public key of the previous hop. If the signing peer initiated
            the PUT, this field is set to all zeroes.
          </dd>
          <dt>PEER SUCCESSOR</dt>
          <dd>
            the peer public key of the next hop (not of the signer).
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="p2p_hello" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>HelloMessage</name>
 	<t>
          When the underlay signals the implementation of added or
          removed addresses through <tt>ADDRESS_ADDED</tt> and
          <tt>ADDRESS_DELETED</tt> an implementation
          <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> disseminate those changes to neighbors
          using <tt>HelloMessages</tt> (as already discussed in
          section <xref target="find_peer"/>).  <tt>HelloMessages</tt>
          are used to inform neighbors of a peer about the sender's
          available addresses. The recipients use these messages to
          inform their respective underlays about ways to sustain the
          connections and to generate <tt>HELLO</tt> blocks (see <xref
          target="hello_block"/>) to answer peer discovery queries
          from other peers.
        </t>
        <section anchor="p2p_hello_wire">
          <name>Wire Format</name>
          <figure anchor="figure_hellomsg" title="The HelloMessage Wire Format.">
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|   MSIZE   |   MTYPE   |  VERSION  | NUM_ADDRS |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    SIGNATURE                  /
/                   (64 bytes)                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    EXPIRATION                 |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/          ADDRESSES (variable length)          /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>where:</t>
          <dl>
            <dt>MSIZE</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the size of this message in network byte order.
            </dd>
            <dt>MTYPE</dt>
            <dd>
              is the 16-bit message type.
              It must be set to
              the value 157 in network byte order as defined in the GANA "GNUnet Message Type" registry
              (see <xref target="gana_message_type"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>VERSION</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit field that indicates the version of the <tt>HelloMessage</tt>. Must be zero.
              In the future, this may be used to extend or update the <tt>HelloMessage</tt> format.
            </dd>
            <dt>NUM_ADDRS</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order that gives the
              total number of addresses encoded in the
              <tt>ADDRESSES</tt> field.
            </dd>
            <dt>SIGNATURE</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 64 byte EdDSA signature <xref target="ed25519"/> using the sender's private
              key affirming the information contained in the message.
              The signature is signing exactly the same data that is being
              signed in a <tt>HELLO</tt> block as described in <xref target="hello_block"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>EXPIRATION</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the absolute 64-bit expiration date of the content.
              The value specified is microseconds since midnight (0 hour),
              January 1, 1970, but must be a multiple of one million
              (so that it can be represented in seconds in a <tt>HELLO</tt> URL).
              Stored in network byte order.
            </dd>
            <dt>ADDRESSES</dt>
            <dd>
              A sequence of exactly <tt>NUM_ADDRS</tt>
              addresses which can be used to contact the peer.
              Each address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 0-terminated.
              If <tt>NUM_ADDRS = 0</tt> then this field is omitted (0 bytes).
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="p2p_hello_processing">
          <name>Processing</name>
          <t>
            If the initiator of a <tt>HelloMessage</tt> is <tt>SELF</tt>, the message
            is simply sent to all neighbors <tt>P</tt> currently in the routing table
            using the <tt>SEND()</tt> function of the underlay as defined in
            <xref target="underlay"/>.
          </t>
          <t>
            Upon receiving a <tt>HelloMessage</tt> from a peer <tt>P</tt>
            an implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> process it step by step as follows:
          </t>
          <ol>
            <li>
              If <tt>P</tt> is not in its routing table, the message is discarded.
            </li>
            <li>
              The signature is verified, including a check that the expiration time
              is in the future. If the signature is invalid, the message is discarded.
            </li>
            <li>
              The information contained in the <tt>HelloMessage</tt>
              is used to synthesize a block of type <tt>HELLO</tt>
              (<xref target="hello_block"/>).  The block is cached in
              the routing table until it expires, or the peer is
              removed from the routing table, or the information is
              replaced by another message from the peer.  The
              implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> instruct the
              underlay to connect to all now available addresses using
              <tt>TRY_CONNECT()</tt> in order to make the underlay
              aware of alternative addresses for this connection and
              to maintain optimal connectivity.
            </li>
            <li>
              Received <tt>HelloMessages</tt> <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
              be forwarded.
            </li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="p2p_put" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>PutMessage</name>
	<t>
	  <tt>PutMessages</tt> are used to store information at other
	  peers in the DHT.  Any application-facing API which allows
	  applications to initiate <tt>PutMessages</tt> to store data
	  in the DHT needs to receive sufficient, possibly
	  implementation-specific information to construct the initial
	  <tt>PutMessage</tt>.  In general, application-facing APIs
	  supporting multiple applications and block types need to be
	  given the block type (<tt>BTYPE</tt>) and message
	  <tt>FLAGS</tt> in addition to the actual <tt>BLOCK</tt>
	  payload. The <tt>BLOCK_KEY</tt> could be provided
	  explicitly, or in some cases might be derived using the
	  <tt>DeriveBlockKey()</tt> function from the block type
	  specific operations defined in <xref
	  target="block_functions"/>.
	</t>
        <section anchor="p2p_put_wire">
          <name>Wire Format</name>
          <figure anchor="figure_putmsg" title="The PutMessage Wire Format.">
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|   MSIZE   |   MTYPE   |         BTYPE         |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
| VER |FLAGS| HOPCOUNT  | REPL_LVL  | PATH_LEN  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   EXPIRATION                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                     PEER_BF                   /
/                   (128 byte)                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    BLOCK_KEY                  /
/                    (64 byte)                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/       TRUNCATED ORIGIN (0 or 32 bytes)        /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/           PUTPATH (variable length)           /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/      LAST HOP SIGNATURE (0 or 64 bytes)       /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/            BLOCK (variable length)            /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>where:</t>
          <dl>
            <dt>MSIZE</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the size of this message in network byte order.
            </dd>
            <dt>MTYPE</dt>
            <dd>
              is the 16-bit message type. Read-only.  It must be set
              to the value 146 in network byte order as defined in the
              GANA "GNUnet Message Type" registry <xref
              target="gana_message_type"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>BTYPE</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 32-bit block type in network byte order.  The block
              type indicates the content type of the payload.  Set by
              the initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>VER</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 8-bit protocol version.
              Set to zero. May be used in future protocol versions.
            </dd>
            <dt>FLAGS</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 8-bit vector with binary options (see <xref target="route_flags"/>).
              Set by the initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>HOPCOUNT</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order indicating how
              many hops this message has traversed to far.  Set by the
              initiator to zero.  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be incremented by one
              by each peer before forwarding the request.
            </dd>
            <dt>REPL_LVL</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order indicating the
              desired replication level of the data.  Set by the
              initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>PATH_LEN</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order indicating the
              number of path elements recorded in <tt>PUTPATH</tt>.  As <tt>PUTPATH</tt>
              is optional, this value may be zero.  If the <tt>PUTPATH</tt> is
              enabled, set initially to zero by the initiator.  Updated
              by processing peers to match the path length in the
              message.
            </dd>
            <dt>EXPIRATION</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the absolute 64-bit expiration date of the
              content in microseconds since midnight (0 hour), January
              1, 1970 in network byte order.  Set by the
              initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>PEER_BF</dt>
            <dd>
              A peer Bloom filter to stop circular routes (see <xref
              target="routing_bloomfilter"/>).  Set by the initiator
              to contain the local peer and all neighbors it is
              forwarded to.  Modified by processing peers to include
              their own peer public key using <tt>BF-SET()</tt>.
            </dd>
            <dt>BLOCK_KEY</dt>
            <dd>
              The key under which the <tt>PutMessage</tt> wants to store content
              under.
              Set by the initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>TRUNCATED ORIGIN</dt>
            <dd>
              is only provided if the <tt>Truncated</tt> flag is set
              in <tt>FLAGS</tt>. If present, this is the public key of
              the peer just before the first entry on the
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt> and the first peer on the
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt> is not the actual origin of the
              message.  Thus, to verify the first signature on the
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt>, this public key must be used.  Note
              that due to the truncation, this last hop cannot be
              verified to exist.  Value is modified by processing
              peers.
            </dd>
            <dt>PUTPATH</dt>
            <dd>
              the variable-length <tt>PUT</tt> path.
              The path consists of a list of <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> path elements.
              Set by the initiator to zero.
              Incremented by processing peers.
            </dd>
            <dt>LAST HOP SIGNATURE</dt>
            <dd>
              is only provided if the <tt>RecordRoute</tt> flag
              is set in <tt>FLAGS</tt>. If present, this is
              an EdDSA signature <xref target="ed25519"/> by the sender of this message
              (using the same format as the signatures in PUTPATH)
              affirming that the sender forwarded the message from
              the predecessor (all zeros if <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> is zero,
              otherwise the last peer in <tt>PUTPATH</tt>) to
              the target peer.
              Modified by processing peers (if flag is set).
            </dd>
            <dt>BLOCK</dt>
            <dd>
              the variable-length block payload. The contents are
              determined by the <tt>BTYPE</tt> field.  The length is
              determined by <tt>MSIZE</tt> minus the size of all of
              the other fields.  Set by the initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="p2p_put_processing">
          <name>Processing</name>
          <t>
            Upon receiving a <tt>PutMessage</tt> from a peer <tt>P</tt>,
            or created through initiation by an overlay API,
            an implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> process it step by step as follows:
          </t>
          <ol>
            <li>
              The <tt>EXPIRATION</tt> field is evaluated.
              If the message is expired, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be discarded.
            </li>
            <li>
              If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is <tt>ANY</tt>, then the message
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be discarded.  If the <tt>BTYPE</tt>
              is not supported by the implementation, no validation of
              the block payload is performed and processing continues
              at (5).  Else, the block <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              validated as defined in (3) and (4).
            </li>
            <li>
              The message is evaluated using the block validation
              functions matching the <tt>BTYPE</tt>. First, the client
              attempts to derive the key using the respective
              <tt>DeriveBlockKey</tt> procedure as described in <xref
              target="block_functions"/>.  If a key can be derived and
              does not match, the message <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              discarded.
	    </li>
	    <li>
	      Next, the <tt>ValidateBlockStoreRequest</tt> procedure
	      for the <tt>BTYPE</tt> as described in <xref
	      target="block_functions"/> is used to validate the block
	      payload. If the block payload is invalid, the message
	      <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be discarded.
            </li>
            <li>
              The peer identity of the sender peer <tt>P</tt>
              <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be in <tt>PEER_BF</tt>.  If not,
              the implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> log an error, but
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> continue.
            </li>
            <li>
              If the <tt>RecordRoute</tt> flag is not set, the
              <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero.
              If the flag is set and <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> is non-zero,
              the local peer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> verify the
              signatures from the <tt>PUTPATH</tt>.  Verification
              <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> involve checking all signatures or
              any random subset of the signatures.  It is
              <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that peers adapt their
              behavior to available computational resources so as to
              not make signature verification a bottleneck.  If an
              invalid signature is found, the <tt>PUTPATH</tt>
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be truncated to only include the
              elements following the invalid signature.
            </li>
            <li>
              If the local peer is the closest peer
              (cf. <tt>IsClosestPeer(SELF, BLOCK_KEY,
              PeerFilter)</tt>) or the <tt>DemultiplexEverywhere</tt>
              flag ist set, the message <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
              stored locally in the block storage if possible.  The
              implementation <tt>MAY</tt> choose not store the block
              if external factors or configurations prevent this, such
              as limited (allotted) disk space.
            </li>
            <li>
              If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> of the message indicates a
              <tt>HELLO</tt> block, the peer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              considered for the local routing table by using the peer
              identity in <tt>BLOCK_KEY</tt>.  If neither the peer is
              already connected nor the respective k-bucket is already
              full, then the peer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> try to establish
              a connection to the peer indicated in the <tt>HELLO</tt>
              block using the address information from the
              <tt>HELLO</tt> block and the underlay's
              <tt>TRY_CONNECT()</tt> function.  The implementation
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> instruct the underlay to try to
              connect to all provided addresses using
              <tt>TRY_CONNECT()</tt> in order to make the underlay
              aware of multiple addresses for this connection.  When a
              connection can be established, the underlay's
              <tt>PEER_CONNECTED</tt> signal will cause the peer to be
              added to the respective k-bucket of the routing table
              (<xref target="routing"/>).
            </li>
            <li>
              Given the value in <tt>REPL_LVL</tt>, <tt>HOPCOUNT</tt>
              and <tt>FALSE = IsClosestPeer(SELF, BLOCK_KEY,
              PeerFilter)</tt> the number of peers to forward to
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be calculated using
              <tt>ComputeOutDegree()</tt>.  The implementation
              <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> select this number of peers
              to forward the message to using the function
              <tt>SelectPeer()</tt> (<xref
              target="routing_functions"/>) using the
              <tt>BLOCK_KEY</tt>, <tt>HOPCOUNT</tt>, and utilizing
              <tt>PEER_BF</tt> as peer Bloom filter.  For each
              selected peer <tt>PEER_BF</tt> is updated with that peer
              in between calls to <tt>SelectPeer()</tt>.  The
              implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> forward to fewer or no
              peers in order to handle resource constraints such as
              limited bandwidth or simply because there are not enough
              suitable connected peers.  For each selected peer with
              peer identity <tt>P</tt> a dedicated
              <tt>PutMessage_P</tt> is created containing the original
              (and where applicable already updated) fields of the
              received <tt>PutMessage</tt>.  In each message
              <em>all</em> selected peer identities and the local peer
              identity <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be added to the
              <tt>PEER_BF</tt> and the <tt>HOPCOUNT</tt>
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be incremented by one.  If the
              <tt>RecordRoute</tt> flag is set, a new path element is
              created using the predecessor peer public key and the
              signature of the current peer.  The path element is
              added to the <tt>PUTPATH</tt> fields and the
              <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> field is incremented by one.  When
              creating the path element signature, the successor must
              be set to the recipient peer <tt>P</tt> of the
              <tt>PutMessage_P</tt>.  The successor in the new path
              element is the recipient peer <tt>P</tt>.  If the path
              becomes too long for the resulting message to be
              transmitted by the underlay, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              truncated.  Finally, the messages are sent using
              <tt>SEND(P, PutMessage_P)</tt> to each recipient.
            </li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="p2p_get" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>GetMessage</name>
	<t>
	  <tt>GetMessages</tt> are used to request information from
	  other peers in the DHT.  An application-level API which
	  allows applications to initiate <tt>GetMessages</tt> needs
	  to provide sufficient, implementation-specific information
	  needed to construct the initial <tt>GetMessage</tt>.  For
	  example, implementations supporting multiple applications
	  and blocks will need to be given the block type, message
	  <tt>FLAG</tt> parameters and possibly an <tt>XQUERY</tt> in
	  addition to just the <tt>QUERY_HASH</tt>. In some cases, it
	  might also be useful to enable the application to assist in
	  the construction of the <tt>RESULT_FILTER</tt> such that it
	  can filter already known results.  Note that the
	  <tt>RESULT_FILTER</tt> may need to be re-constructed every
	  time the query is retransmitted by the initiator (details
	  depending on the <tt>BTYPE</tt>) and thus a
	  <tt>RESULT_FILTER</tt> can often not be passed directly as
	  an argument by the application to an application API.
	  Instead, applications would typically provide the set of
	  results to be filtered, allowing the DHT to construct the
	  <tt>RESULT_FILTER</tt> whenever it retransmits a
	  <tt>GetMessage</tt> request as initiator.
        </t>
        <section anchor="p2p_get_wire">
          <name>Wire Format</name>
          <figure anchor="figure_getmsg" title="The GetMessage Wire Format.">
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|   MSIZE   |   MTYPE   |         BTYPE         |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
| VER |FLAGS|  HOPCOUNT | REPL_LVL  |  RF_SIZE  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    PEER_BF                    /
/                   (128 byte)                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   QUERY_HASH                  /
/                   (64 byte)                   |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 RESULT_FILTER                 /
/               (variable length)               /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/            XQUERY (variable length)           /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>where:</t>
          <dl>
            <dt>MSIZE</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the size of this message in network byte order.
            </dd>
            <dt>MTYPE</dt>
            <dd>
              is the 16-bit message type. Read-only.  It must be set
              to the value 147 in network byte order as defined in the
              GANA "GNUnet Message Type" registry <xref
              target="gana_message_type"/>.
            </dd>
            <dt>BTYPE</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 32-bit block type field in network byte order. The
              block type indicates the content type of the
              payload. Set by the initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>VER</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 8-bit protocol version.
              Set to zero. May be used in future protocol versions.
            </dd>
            <dt>FLAGS</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 8-bit vector with binary options (see <xref target="route_flags"/>).
              Set by the initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>HOPCOUNT</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order indicating how
              many hops this message has traversed to far.  Set by the
              initiator to zero.  Incremented by each peer by one
              per hop.
            </dd>
            <dt>REPL_LVL</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order indicating the
              desired replication level of the data.  Set by the
              initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>RF_SIZE</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order indicating the
              length of the <tt>RESULT_FILTER</tt>.  Set by the
              initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>PEER_BF</dt>
            <dd>
              A peer Bloom filter to stop circular routes (see <xref target="routing_bloomfilter"/>).
              Set by the initiator to include itself and all connected neighbors in the routing table.
              Modified by processing peers to include their own peer identity.
            </dd>
            <dt>QUERY_HASH</dt>
            <dd>
              The query used to indicate what the key is under which
              the initiator is looking for blocks with this request.
              The block type may use a different evaluation logic to
              determine applicable result blocks.  Set by the
              initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>RESULT_FILTER</dt>
            <dd>
              the variable-length result filter with <tt>RF_SIZE</tt>
              bytes as described in <xref target="result_filter"/>.
              Set by the initiator.  Modified by processing peers
              based on results returned.
            </dd>
            <dt>XQUERY</dt>
            <dd>
              the variable-length extended query. Optional.
              Set by the initiator. Read-only. The length is
              determined by subtracting the length of all
              other fields from <tt>MSIZE</tt>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
	<section anchor="result_filter">
          <name>Result Filter</name>
	  <t>
            A result filter is used to indicate to other peers which
            results are not of interest when processing a
            <tt>GetMessage</tt> (<xref target="p2p_get"/>).  Any peer
            which is processing <tt>GetMessages</tt> and has a result
            which matches the query key <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> check the
            result filter and only send a reply message if the result
            does not test positive under the result filter. Before
            forwarding the <tt>GetMessage</tt>, the result filter
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be updated using the result of the
            <tt>BTYPE</tt>-specific <tt>FilterResult</tt> (see <xref
            target="block_functions"/>) function to filter out all
            results already returned by the local peer.
          </t>
	  <t>
            How a result filter is implemented depends on the block type
	    as described in <xref target="block_functions"/>.
	    Result filters may be probabilistic data structures. Thus,
	    it is possible that a desireable result is filtered by a result
	    filter because of a false-positive test.
          </t>
          <t>
	    How exactly a block result is added to a result filter is
	    specified as part of the definition of a block type
	    (cf. <xref target="hello_block"/>).
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="p2p_get_processing">
          <name>Processing</name>
          <t>
            Upon receiving a <tt>GetMessage</tt> from a peer <tt>P</tt>, or
            created through initiation by the overlay API, an
            implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> process it step by step as follows:
          </t>
          <ol>
            <li>
              If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is supported, the
              <tt>QUERY_HASH</tt> and <tt>XQUERY</tt> fields are
              validated as defined by the respective
              <tt>ValidateBlockQuery()</tt> procedure for this type.  If
              the result yields <tt>REQUEST_INVALID</tt>, the message
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be discarded and processing ends.
              If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is not supported, the message
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be forwarded (Skip to step 4).  If
              the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is <tt>ANY</tt>, the message is
              processed further without validation.
            </li>
            <li>
              The peer identity of the sender peer <tt>P</tt>
              <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be in the <tt>PEER_BF</tt> peer
              Bloom filter. If not, the implementation
              <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> log an error, but <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
              continue.
            </li>
            <li>
              <t>
                The local peer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> try to produce a
                reply in any of the following cases: (1) If the local
                peer is the closest peer (cf. <tt>IsClosestPeer(SELF,
                QueryHash, PeerFilter)</tt>, or (2) if the
                <tt>DemultiplexEverywhere</tt> flag is set, or (3) if
                the local peer is not the closest and a previously
                cached <tt>ResultMessage</tt> also matches this
                request (<xref target="p2p_result_processing"/>).
              </t>
              <t>
                The reply is produced (if one is available) using the following
                steps:
              </t>
              <ol type="%c)">
                <li>
                  If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is <tt>HELLO</tt>, the
                  implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only consider
                  synthesizing its own addresses and the addresses it
                  has cached for the peers in its routing table as
                  <tt>HELLO</tt> block replies.  Otherwise, if the
                  <tt>BTYPE</tt> does not indicate a request for a
                  <tt>HELLO</tt> block or <tt>ANY</tt>, the
                  implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> only consider
                  blocks in the local block storage and previously
                  cached <tt>ResultMessages</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>
                  If the <tt>FLAGS</tt> field includes the flag
                  <tt>FindApproximate</tt>, the peer
                  <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> respond with the closest block
                  (smallest value of <tt>GetDistance(QUERY_HASH,
                  BLOCK_KEY)</tt>) it can find that is not filtered by
                  the <tt>RESULT_BF</tt>.  Otherwise, the peer
                  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> respond with the block with a
                  <tt>BLOCK_KEY</tt> that matches the
                  <tt>QUERY_HASH</tt> exactly and that is not filtered
                  by the <tt>RESULT_BF</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>
                  Any resulting (synthesized) block is encapsulated in
                  a <tt>ResultMessage</tt>.  The
                  <tt>ResultMessage</tt> <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
                  transmitted to the neighbor from which the request
                  was received.
                </li>
              </ol>
	      <t>
                Implementations <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> not reply if they
                are resource-constrained.  However,
                <tt>ResultMessages</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be given
                the highest priority among competing transmissions.
              </t>
              <t>
	       If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is supported and
	       <tt>ValidateBlockReply</tt> for the given query has
	       yielded a status of <tt>FILTER_LAST</tt>, processing
	       <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> end and not continue with
	       forwarding of the request to other peers.
              </t>
            </li>
            <li>
              The implementation <tt>MUST</tt> create (or merge) an
              entry in the pending table (see <xref
              target="pending_table"/>) for the query represented by
              this <tt>GetMessage</tt>.  The pending table
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> store the last <tt>MAX_RECENT</tt>
              requests, and peers thus <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> discard the
              oldest existing request if memory constraints on the
              pending table are encountered. Note that peers
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> clean up state for queries that had
              response with a status of <tt>FILTER_LAST</tt> even if
              they are not the oldest query in the pending table.
            </li>
            <li>
              Using the value in <tt>REPL_LVL</tt>, the number of
              peers to forward to <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be calculated
              using <tt>ComputeOutDegree()</tt>.  If there is at least
              one peer to forward to, the implementation
              <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> select up to this number of peers
              to forward the message to. Furthermore, the
              implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> select up to this
              number of peers to using the function
              <tt>SelectPeer()</tt> (from <xref
              target="routing_functions"/>) using the
              <tt>QUERY_HASH</tt>, <tt>HOPCOUNT</tt>, and the
              <tt>PEER_BF</tt>.  The implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
              forward to fewer or no peers in order to handle resource
              constraints such as bandwidth.  Before forwarding, the
              peer Bloom filter <tt>PEER_BF</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
              be updated to filter all selected peers and the local
              peer identity <tt>SELF</tt>.  For all peers with peer
              identity <tt>P</tt> chosen to forward the message to,
              <tt>SEND(P, GetMessage_P)</tt> is called.  Here,
              <tt>GetMessage_P</tt> is the original message with the
              updated fields for <tt>HOPCOUNT</tt> (incremented by
              one), updated <tt>PEER_BF</tt> and updated
              <tt>RESULT_FILTER</tt> (based on results already
              returned).
            </li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="p2p_result" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>ResultMessage</name>
	<t>
	  <tt>ResultMessages</tt> are used to return information to
	  other peers in the DHT or to applications using the overlay
	  API that previously initiated a <tt>GetMessage</tt>.  The
	  initiator of a <tt>ResultMessage</tt> is a peer triggered
	  through the processing of a <tt>GetMessage</tt>.
	</t>
        <section anchor="p2p_result_wire">
          <name>Wire Format</name>
          <figure anchor="figure_resmsg" title="The ResultMessage Wire Format">
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|   MSIZE   |   MTYPE   |        BTYPE          |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|  RESERVED | VER |FLAGS| PUTPATH_L | GETPATH_L |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   EXPIRATION                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   QUERY_HASH                  /
/                   (64 byte)                   |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/       TRUNCATED ORIGIN (0 or 32 bytes)        /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/                    PUTPATH                    /
/                (variable length)              /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/                    GETPATH                    /
/                (variable length)              /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/      LAST HOP SIGNATURE (0 or 64 bytes)       /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/                     BLOCK                     /
/               (variable length)               /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>where:</t>
          <dl>
            <dt>MSIZE</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the size of this message in network byte order.
            </dd>
            <dt>MTYPE</dt>
            <dd>
              is the 16-bit message type. Set by the
              initiator. Read-only.  It must be set to the value 148
              in network byte order as defined in the GANA "GNUnet
              Message Type" registry (see <xref
              target="gana_message_type"/>).
            </dd>
            <dt>BTYPE</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 32-bit block type field in network byte order. The
              block type indicates the content type of the payload.
              Set by the initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>RESERVED</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit value. Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
              set this value to zero when originating a result message.
              Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> forward
              this value unchanged even if it is non-zero.
            </dd>
            <dt>VER</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 8-bit protocol version in network byte order.
              Set to zero. May be used in future protocol versions.
            </dd>
            <dt>FLAGS</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 8-bit vector with binary options (see <xref
              target="route_flags"/>).  Set by the initiator of the
              response based on the flags retained from the original
              <tt>PutMessage</tt>, possibly setting the
              <tt>Truncated</tt> bit if the initiator is forced to
              truncate the path.  For <tt>HELLO</tt> blocks, the
              <tt>FLAGS</tt> should simply be cleared.
            </dd>
            <dt>PUTPATH_L</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order indicating the
              number of path elements recorded in <tt>PUTPATH</tt>. As
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt> is optional, this value may be zero
              even if the message has traversed several peers.  Set by
              the initiator to the <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> of the
              <tt>PutMessage</tt> from which the block originated.
              Modified by processing peers in case of path truncation.
            </dd>
            <dt>GETPATH_L</dt>
            <dd>
              is a 16-bit number in network byte order indicating the
              number of path elements recorded in <tt>GETPATH</tt>. As
              <tt>GETPATH</tt> is optional, this value may be zero
              even if the message has traversed several peers.
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to zero by the initiator.
              Modified by processing peers to match the path length in
              the message.
            </dd>
            <dt>EXPIRATION</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the absolute 64-bit expiration date of the
              content in microseconds since midnight (0 hour), January
              1, 1970 in network byte order.  Set by the initiator to
              the expiration value as recorded from the
              <tt>PutMessage</tt> from which the block originated.
              Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>QUERY_HASH</dt>
            <dd>
              the query hash corresponding to the <tt>GetMessage</tt>
              which caused this reply message to be sent.  Set by the
              initiator using the value of the <tt>GetMessage</tt>.
              Read-only.
            </dd>
            <dt>TRUNCATED ORIGIN</dt>
            <dd>
              is only provided if the <tt>Truncated</tt> flag is set
              in <tt>FLAGS</tt>. If present, this is the public key of
              the peer just before the first entry on the
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt> and the first peer on the
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt> is not the actual origin of the
              message.  Thus, to verify the first signature on the
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt>, this public key must be used.  Note
              that due to the truncation, this last hop cannot be
              verified to exist.  Set by processing peers.
            </dd>
            <dt>PUTPATH</dt>
            <dd>
              the variable-length PUT path.  The path consists of a
              list of <tt>PUTPATH_L</tt> path elements.  Set by the
              initiator to the the <tt>PUTPATH</tt> of the
              <tt>PutMessage</tt> from which the block originated.
              Modified by processing peers in case of path truncation.
            </dd>
            <dt>GETPATH</dt>
            <dd>
              the variable-length PUT path.  The path consists of a
              list of <tt>GETPATH_L</tt> path elements.  Set by
              processing peers.
            </dd>
            <dt>LAST HOP SIGNATURE</dt>
            <dd>
              is only provided if the <tt>RecordRoute</tt> flag is set
              in <tt>FLAGS</tt>. If present, this is an EdDSA
              signature <xref target="ed25519"/> by the sender of this
              message (using the same format as the signatures in
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt>) affirming that the sender forwarded
              the message from the predecessor (all zeros if
              <tt>PATH_LEN</tt> is zero, otherwise the last peer in
              <tt>PUTPATH</tt>) to the target peer.
            </dd>
            <dt>BLOCK</dt>
            <dd>
              the variable-length resource record data payload.  The
              contents are defined by the respective type of the
              resource record.  Set by the initiator. Read-only.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="p2p_result_processing">
          <name>Processing</name>
          <t>
            Upon receiving a <tt>ResultMessage</tt> from a connected
            peer or triggered by the processing of a
            <tt>GetMessage</tt>, an implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
            process it step by step as follows:
          </t>
          <ol>
            <li>
              First, the <tt>EXPIRATION</tt> field is evaluated.  If
              the message is expired, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
              discarded.
            </li>
            <li>
              If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is supported, then the
              <tt>BLOCK</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be validated against
              the requested <tt>BTYPE</tt>.  To do this, the peer
              checks that the block is valid using
              <tt>ValidateBlockStoreRequest</tt>.  If the result is
              <tt>BLOCK_INVALID</tt>, the message <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
              be discarded.
            </li>
            <li>
              If the <tt>PUTPATH_L</tt> or the <tt>GETPATH_L</tt> are
              non-zero, the local peer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> verify
              the signatures from the <tt>PUTPATH</tt> and the
              <tt>GETPATH</tt>.  Verification <bcp14>MAY</bcp14>
              involve checking all signatures or any random subset of
              the signatures.  It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> that
              peers adapt their behavior to available computational
              resources so as to not make signature verification a
              bottleneck.  If an invalid signature is found, the path
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be truncated to only include the
              elements following the invalid signature.  In
              particular, any invalid signature on the
              <tt>GETPATH</tt> will cause <tt>PUTPATH_L</tt> to be set
              to zero.
            </li>
	    <li>
	      The peer also attempts to compute the key using
	      <tt>DeriveBlockKey</tt>.  This may result in
	      <tt>NONE</tt>.  The result is used later.  Note that
	      even if a key was computed, it does not have to match
	      the <tt>QUERY_HASH</tt>.
	    </li>
            <li>
              If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> of the message indicates a
              <tt>HELLO</tt> block, the peer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be
              considered for the local routing table by using the peer
              identity computed from the block using
              <tt>DeriveBlockKey</tt>.  An implementation
              <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose to ignore the <tt>HELLO</tt>,
              for example because the routing table or the respective
              k-bucket is already full.  If the peer is a suitable
              candidate for insertion, the local peer
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> try to establish a connection to the
              peer indicated in the <tt>HELLO</tt> block using the
              address information from the <tt>HELLO</tt> block and
              the underlay's <tt>TRY_CONNECT()</tt> function.  The
              implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> instruct the underlay
              to connect to all provided addresses using
              <tt>TRY_CONNECT()</tt> in order to make the underlay
              aware of multiple addresses for this connection.  When a
              connection is established, the signal
              <tt>PEER_CONNECTED</tt> will cause the peer to be added
              to the respective k-bucket of the routing table (see
              <xref target="routing"/>).
            </li>
            <li>
              If the <tt>QUERY_HASH</tt> of this
              <tt>ResultMessage</tt> does not match an entry in the
              pending table (<xref target="pending_table"/>), then the
              message is discarded and processing ends.  Otherwise,
              processing continues for each entry in the table as
              follows.
            </li>
            <li>
	      <ol type="%c)">
		<li>
		  If the <tt>FindApproximate</tt> flag was not set in
		  the query and the <tt>BTYPE</tt> enabled the
		  implementation to compute the key from the block,
		  the computed key must exactly match the
		  <tt>QUERY_HASH</tt>, otherwise the result does not
		  match the pending query and processing continues
		  with the next pending table entry.
                </li>
		<li>
                  If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is supported, result block
                  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be validated against the
                  specific query using the respective
                  <tt>FilterBlockResult</tt> function. This function
                  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> update the result filter if a
                  result is returned to the originator of the query.
                </li>
	        <li>
		  If the <tt>BTYPE</tt> is not supported, filtering of
		  exact duplicate replies <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> still be
		  performed before forwarding the reply.  Such
		  duplicate filtering <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be
		  implemented probabilistically, for example using a
		  Bloom filter.  The result of this duplicate
		  filtering is always either <tt>FILTER_MORE</tt> or
		  <tt>FILTER_DUPLICATE</tt>.
                </li>
		<li>
		  If the <tt>RecordRoute</tt> flag is set in
		  <tt>FLAGS</tt>, the local peer identity
		  <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be appended to the
		  <tt>GETPATH</tt> of the message and the respective
		  signature <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set using the query
		  origin as the <tt>PEER SUCCESSOR</tt> and the
		  response origin as the <tt>PEER PREDECESSOR</tt>.
		  If the flag is not set, the <tt>GETPATH_L</tt> and
		  <tt>PUTPATH_L</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be set to
		  zero when forwarding the result.
                </li>
                <li>
		  If the result filter result is either
		  <tt>FILTER_MORE</tt> or <tt>FILTER_LAST</tt>, the
		  message is forwarded to the origin of the query as
		  defined in the entry which may either be the local
		  peer or a remote peer.  In case this is a query of
		  the local peer the result may have to be provided to
		  applications through the overlay API.  Otherwise,
		  the result is forwarded using <tt>SEND(P,
		  ResultMessage')</tt> where <tt>ResultMessage'</tt>
		  is the now modified message.  If the result was
		  <tt>FILTER_LAST</tt>, the query <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
		  be removed from the pending table.
	        </li>
              </ol>
            </li>
	    <li>
	      Finally, the implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> cache
	      <tt>ResultMessages</tt> in order to provide already seen
	      replies to future <tt>GetMessages</tt>.  The
	      implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose not no cache
	      any or a limited number of <tt>ResultMessages</tt> for
	      reasons such as resource limitations.
            </li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="blockstorage" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Blocks</name>
      <t>
	This section describes various considerations R<sup>5</sup>N
	implementations must consider with respect to blocks.
	Specifically, implementations <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be validate and persist
  blocks.
  Implementations
	<bcp14>MAY</bcp14> not support validation for all types
    of blocks.
    For example, on some devices, storing blocks is impossible due to lack of
  storage capacity.
  Block storage improves lookup performance for local applications and also
  other peers. Not storing blocks results in degraded performance.
      </t>
      <t>
        The block type determines the format and handling of the block
        payload by peers in <tt>PutMessages</tt> and
        <tt>ResultMessages</tt>.  Applications can and should define
        their own block types.  Block types <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        registered with GANA (see <xref target="gana_block_type"/>).
        Especially when new block types are introduced, some peers
        <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> lack support for the respective block
        operations.
      </t>
      <t>
      </t>
      <section anchor="block_functions">
        <name>Block Operations</name>
          <t>
            Block validation operations are used as part of message
            processing (see <xref target="p2p_messages"/>) for all
            types of DHT messages.  To enable these validation
            operations, any block type specification
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> define the following functions:
          </t>
          <dl>
            <dt>ValidateBlockQuery(Key, XQuery)
	        -&gt; RequestEvaluationResult</dt>
            <dd>
	      <t>
              is used to evaluate the request for a block as part of
              <tt>GetMessage</tt> processing. Here, the block payload is unkown,
              but if possible the <tt>XQuery</tt> and <tt>Key</tt>
              <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be verified.  Possible values for
	      the <tt>RequestEvaluationResult</tt> are:
              </t>
              <dl>
               <dt>REQUEST_VALID</dt>
               <dd>
                 The query is valid.
               </dd>
               <dt>REQUEST_INVALID</dt>
               <dd>
		 The query format does not match the block type. For example,
		 a mandatory <tt>XQuery</tt> was not provided, or of
		 the size of the <tt>XQuery</tt> is not appropriate
		 for the block type.
               </dd>
              </dl>
            </dd>
            <dt>DeriveBlockKey(Block) -&gt; Key | NONE</dt>
            <dd>
              is used to synthesize the block key from the block
              payload as part of <tt>PutMessage</tt> and
              <tt>ResultMessage</tt> processing.  The special return
              value of <tt>NONE</tt> implies that this block type does
              not permit deriving the key from the block.  A
              <tt>Key</tt> may be returned for a block that is
              ill-formed.
            </dd>
            <dt>ValidateBlockStoreRequest(Block)
	        -&gt; BlockEvaluationResult</dt>
            <dd>
	      <t>
                is used to evaluate a block payload as part of
                <tt>PutMessage</tt> and <tt>ResultMessage</tt>
                processing.  Possible values for the
                <tt>BlockEvaluationResult</tt> are:
              </t>
              <dl>
               <dt>BLOCK_VALID</dt>
               <dd>
                 The block is valid.
               </dd>
               <dt>BLOCK_INVALID</dt>
               <dd>
                 The block payload does not match the block type.
               </dd>
              </dl>
            </dd>
            <dt>SetupResultFilter(FilterSize, Mutator) -&gt; RF</dt>
            <dd>
	      is used to setup an empty result filter.  The arguments
	      are typically the size of the set of results that must
	      be filtered at the initiator, and a <tt>Mutator</tt>
	      value which <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used to
	      deterministically re-randomize probabilistic data
	      structures.  <tt>RF</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a byte
	      sequence suitable for transmission over the network.
            </dd>
            <dt>FilterResult(Block, Key, RF, XQuery) -&gt; (FilterEvaluationResult, RF')</dt>
            <dd>
	      <t>
	      is used to filter results against specific queries.
	      This function does not check the validity of
	      <tt>Block</tt> itself or that it matches the given key,
	      as this must have been checked earlier.  Locally
	      stored blocks from previously observed
	      <tt>ResultMessages</tt> and <tt>PutMessages</tt> use
	      this function to perform filtering based on the request
	      parameters of a particular GET operation.  Possible
	      values for the <tt>FilterEvaluationResult</tt> are:
  	      </t>
              <dl>
              <dt>FILTER_MORE</dt>
              <dd>
                <tt>Block</tt> is a valid result, and there may be more.
              </dd>
              <dt>FILTER_LAST</dt>
              <dd>
                The given <tt>Block</tt> is the last possible valid result.
              </dd>
              <dt>FILTER_DUPLICATE</dt>
              <dd>
                <tt>Block</tt> is a valid result, but considered to be
                a duplicate (was filtered by the <tt>RF</tt>) and
                <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be returned to the previous
                hop.  Peers that do not understand the block type
                <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> return such duplicate results
                anyway and implementations must take this into account.
              </dd>
              <dt>FILTER_IRRELEVANT</dt>
              <dd>
                <tt>Block</tt> does not satisfy the constraints
                imposed by the <tt>XQuery</tt>. The result
                <bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14> be returned to the previous
                hop.  Peers that do not understand the block type
                <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> return such irrelevant results
                anyway and implementations must take this into account.
              </dd>
              </dl>
	      <t>
	        If the main evaluation result is <tt>FILTER_MORE</tt>,
	        the function also returns an updated result filter
	        where the <tt>Block</tt> is added to the set of
	        filtered replies.  An implementation is not expected
	        to actually differenciate between the
	        <tt>FILTER_DUPLICATE</tt> and
	        <tt>FILTER_IRRELEVANT</tt> return values: in both
	        cases the <tt>Block</tt> is ignored for this query.
	      </t>
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section anchor="hello_block">
          <name>HELLO Blocks</name>
          <t>
            For bootstrapping and peer discovery, the DHT
            implementation uses its own block type called "HELLO".
            <tt>HELLO</tt> blocks are the only type of block that
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be supported by every R<sup>5</sup>N
            implementation. A block with this block type contains the
            peer public key of the peer that published the
            <tt>HELLO</tt> together with a set of addresses of this
            peer. The key of a <tt>HELLO</tt> block is the SHA-512
            hash <xref target="RFC4634"/> of the peer public key and
            thus the peer's identity in the DHT.
          </t>
          <t>
            The <tt>HELLO</tt> block type wire format is illustrated
            in <xref target="figure_hello"/>. A query for block of
            type <tt>HELLO</tt> <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> include
            extended query data (XQuery). Any implementation
            encountering a request for a <tt>HELLO</tt> with non-empty
            XQuery data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> consider the request
            invalid and ignore it.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="figure_hello" title="The HELLO Block Format.">
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                PEER PUBLIC KEY                |
|                    (32 byte)                  |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   SIGNATURE                   |
|                   (64 byte)                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   EXPIRATION                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/                   ADDRESSES                   /
/               (variable length)               /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
                ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <dl>
            <dt>PEER PUBLIC KEY</dt>
            <dd>
              is the public key of the peer to which the
              <tt>ADDRESSES</tt> belong. This is also the public key
              needed to verify the <tt>SIGNATURE</tt>.
            </dd>
            <dt>EXPIRATION</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the absolute 64-bit expiration date of the
              content.  The value specified is microseconds since
              midnight (0 hour), January 1, 1970 in network byte
              order, but must be a multiple of one million (so that it
              can be represented in seconds in a <tt>HELLO</tt> URL).
            </dd>
            <dt>ADDRESSES</dt>
            <dd>
              is a list of UTF-8 addresses (<xref target="terminology"/>)
              which can be used to contact the peer.
              Each address <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 0-terminated.
              The set of addresses <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be empty, for example
              if the peer knows that it cannot be reached from the outside (i.e. NAT).
            </dd>
            <dt>SIGNATURE</dt>
            <dd>
	    <t>
              is the EdDSA signature <xref target="ed25519"/> of the
              <tt>HELLO</tt> block.  The signature covers various
              information derived from the actual data in the
              <tt>HELLO</tt> block.  The data signed over includes the
              block expiration time, a constant that uniquely
              identifies the purpose of the signature, and a hash of
              the addresses with 0-terminators in the same order as
              they are present in the <tt>HELLO</tt> block.  The
              format is illustrated in <xref
              target="figure_hellowithpseudo"/>.
          </t>
          <figure anchor="figure_hellowithpseudo" title="The Wire Format of the HELLO for Signing.">
           <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |        PURPOSE        |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                   EXPIRATION                  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    H_ADDRS                    |
|                   (64 byte)                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <dl>
            <dt>SIZE</dt>
            <dd>
              A 32-bit value containing the length of the signed data
              in bytes in network byte order.  The length of the
              signed data <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 80 bytes.
            </dd>
            <dt>PURPOSE</dt>
            <dd>
              A 32-bit signature purpose flag. This field
              <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 7 in network byte order.
            </dd>
            <dt>EXPIRATION</dt>
            <dd>
              denotes the absolute 64-bit expiration date of the
              <tt>HELLO</tt> in microseconds since midnight (0 hour),
              January 1, 1970 in network byte order.
            </dd>
            <dt>H_ADDRS</dt>
            <dd>
              a SHA-512 hash over the addresses in the <tt>HELLO</tt>.
              <tt>H_ADDRS</tt> is generated over the
              <tt>ADDRESSES</tt> field as provided in the
              <tt>HELLO</tt> block using SHA-512 <xref
              target="RFC4634"/>.
            </dd>
          </dl>
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
            The <tt>HELLO</tt> block operations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
            implemented as follows:
          </t>
          <dl>
          <dt>ValidateBlockQuery(Key, XQuery)
	        -&gt; RequestEvaluationResult</dt>
          <dd>
            To validate a block query for a <tt>HELLO</tt> is to
            simply check that the <tt>XQuery</tt> is empty. If it is empty,
            <tt>REQUEST_VALID</tt> ist returned. Otherwise,
            <tt>REQUEST_INVALID</tt> is returned.
          </dd>
          <dt>DeriveBlockKey(Block) -&gt; Key | NONE</dt>
          <dd>
            To derive a block key for a <tt>HELLO</tt> is to simply
            hash the <tt>PEER PUBLIC KEY</tt> from the <tt>HELLO</tt>. The
            result of this function is thus always the SHA-512 hash over
            the <tt>PEER PUBLIC KEY</tt>.
          </dd>
          <dt>ValidateBlockStoreRequest(Block)
	        -&gt; BlockEvaluationResult</dt>
          <dd>
	    To validate a block store request is to verify the EdDSA
	    <tt>SIGNATURE</tt> over the hashed <tt>ADDRESSES</tt>
	    against the public key from the <tt>PEER PUBLIC KEY</tt>
	    field.  If the signature is valid <tt>BLOCK_VALID</tt> is
	    returned.  Otherwise <tt>BLOCK_INVALID</tt> is returned.
          </dd>
          <dt>SetupResultFilter(FilterSize, Mutator) -&gt; RF</dt>
          <dd>
	  <t>
	    The <tt>RF</tt> for <tt>HELLO</tt> blocks is implemented
	    using a Bloom filter following the definition from <xref
	    target="bloom_filters"/> and consists of a variable number
	    of bits <tt>L</tt>.  <tt>L</tt> depends on the
            <tt>FilterSize</tt> which will be the number of
	    connected peers <tt>|E|</tt> known to the peer creating a
	    <tt>HELLO</tt> block from its own addresses: <tt>L</tt> is
	    set to the minimum of 2<sup>18</sup> bits (2<sup>15</sup>
	    bytes) and the lowest power of 2 that is strictly larger
	    than <tt>2*K*|E|</tt> bits (<tt>K*|E|/4</tt> bytes).
          </t>
          <t>
            The <tt>k</tt>-value for the Bloom filter
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 16.  The elements used in the Bloom
            filter consist of an XOR between the <tt>H_ADDRS</tt>
            field (as computed using SHA-512 over the
            <tt>ADDRESSES</tt>) and the SHA-512 hash of the
            <tt>MUTATOR</tt> field from a given <tt>HELLO</tt> block.
            The mapping function M(<tt>H_ADDRS XOR MUTATOR</tt>) is
            defined as follows:
          </t>
          <t>
            <tt>M(e = H_ADDR XOR MUTATOR) -> e as uint32[]</tt>
          </t>
          <t>
            <tt>M</tt> is an identity function and returns the 512-bit
            XOR result unmodified.  This resulting byte string is
            interpreted as k=16 32-bit integers in network byte order
            which are used to set and check the bits in <tt>B</tt>
            using <tt>BF-SET()</tt> and <tt>BF-TEST()</tt>.  The
            32-bit <tt>MUTATOR</tt> is prepended to the L-bit Bloom filter
            field <tt>HELLO_BF</tt> containing <tt>B</tt> to create
            the result filter for a <tt>HELLO</tt> block:
          </t>
          <figure anchor="hello_rf" title="The HELLO Block Result Filter.">
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|        MUTATOR        |      HELLO_BF         /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+  (variable length)    /
/                                               /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
]]></artwork>
          </figure>
          <t>where:</t>
          <dl>
            <dt>MUTATOR</dt>
            <dd>
              The 32-bit mutator for the result filter.
            </dd>
            <dt>HELLO_BF</dt>
            <dd>
              The L-bit Bloom filter array.
            </dd>
          </dl>
          <t>
	    The <tt>MUTATOR</tt> value is used to additionally
	    "randomize" the computation of the Bloom filter while
	    remaining deterministic across peers.  It is only ever set
	    by the peer initiating the GET request, and changed every
	    time the GET request is repeated.  Peers forwarding GET
	    requests <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> not change the mutator value
	    included in the <tt>RESULT_FILTER</tt> as they might not
	    be able to recalculate the result filter with a different
	    <tt>MUTATOR</tt> value.
          </t>
	  <t>
	    Consequently, repeated requests have statistically
	    independent probabilities of creating false-positives in a
	    result filter. Thus, even if for one request a result
	    filter may exclude a result as a false-positive match,
	    subsequent requests are likely to not have the same
	    false-positives.
          </t>
	  <t>
	    <tt>HELLO</tt> result filters can be merged if the Bloom
	    filters have the same size and <tt>MUTATOR</tt> by setting
	    all bits to 1 that are set in either Bloom filter.  This
	    is done whenever a peer receives a query with the same
	    <tt>MUTATOR</tt>, predecessor and Bloom filter size.
	  </t>
          </dd>
            <dt>FilterResult(Block, Key, RF, XQuery) -&gt; (FilterEvaluationResult, RF')</dt>
            <dd>
             The <tt>H_ADDRS</tt> field is XORed with the SHA-512 hash
             of the <tt>MUTATOR</tt> field from the <tt>HELLO</tt>
             block and the resulting value is checked against the
             Bloom filter in <tt>RF</tt>.  Consequently,
             <tt>HELLOs</tt> with completely identical sets of
             addresses will be filtered and <tt>FILTER_DUPLICATE</tt>
             is returned.  Any small variation in the set of addresses
             will cause the block to no longer be filtered (with high
             probability) and <tt>FILTER_MORE</tt> is returned.
            </dd>
          </dl>
        </section>
        <section>
        <name>Persistence</name>
        <t>
          An implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> provide a local
          persistence mechanism for blocks.  Embedded systems that
          lack storage capability <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> use
          connection-level signalling to indicate that they are merely
          a client utilizing a DHT and are not able to participate
          with storage.  The local storage <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> provide
          the following functionality:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Store(Key, Block)</dt>
          <dd>
            Stores a block under the specified key. If an block with identical
	    payload exists already under the same key, the meta data should
	    be set to the maximum expiration time of both blocks and use the
	    corresponding <tt>PUTPATH</tt> (and if applicable
            <tt>TRUNCATED ORIGIN</tt>) of that version of the block.
          </dd>
          <dt>Lookup(Key) -&gt; Set of Blocks</dt>
          <dd>
            Retrieves blocks stored under the specified key.
          </dd>
          <dt>LookupApproximate(Key) -&gt; List of Blocks</dt>
          <dd>
            Retrieves the blocks stored under the specified key and
            any blocks under keys close to the specified key, in order
            of decreasing proximity.
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <section anchor="approx_search">
          <name>Approximate Search Considerations</name>
        <t>
          Over time a peer may accumulate a significant number of blocks
          which are stored locally in the persistence layer.
          Due to the expected high number of blocks, the method to
          retrieve blocks close to the specified lookup key in the
          <tt>LookupApproximate</tt> API must be implemented with care
          with respect to efficiency.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to limit the number of
          results from the <tt>LookupApproximate</tt> procedure to a
          result size which is easily manageable by the local system.
          The <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14> default is to return blocks
          with the four closest keys.  Note that filtering by the
          <tt>RF</tt> will be done by the DHT afterwards and it is
          <bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14> to fetch additional records
          even if all four closest keys are filtered by the
          <tt>RF</tt>.  The main reason for this is to ensure peers do
          not spend extensive resources to process approximate
          lookups.  In particular, implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
          limit the worst-case effort they spent on approximate
          lookups.
        </t>
        <t>
          In order to efficiently find a suitable result set, the
          implementation <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> follow the following
          procedure:
        </t>
        <ol>
          <li>
            Sort all blocks by the block key in ascending (decending) order.
            The block keys are interpreted as integers.
          </li>
          <li>
            Alternatingly select a block with a key larger and smaller
            from the sortings.  The resulting set is then sorted by
            the XOR distance to the query.  The selection process
            continues until the upper bound for the result set is
            reached and both sortings do not yield any closer blocks.
          </li>
        </ol>
        <t>
          An implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> decide to use a custom
          algorithm in order to find the closest blocks in the local
          storage.  But, especially for more primitive approaches
          (such as only comparing XOR distances for all blocks in the
          storage), more simplistic procedures may become ineffective
          for large data sets and care <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be taken
          to strictly bound the maximum effort expended per query.
        </t>
        </section>
        <section>
          <name>Caching Strategy Considerations</name>
          <t>
            An implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> implement an
            eviction strategy for blocks stored in the block storage
            layer.
          </t>
          <t>
            In order to ensure the freshness of blocks, an implementation
            <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> evict expired blocks in favor of
            new blocks.
          </t>
          <t>
            An implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> preserve blocks which
            are often requested.  This approach can be expensive as it
            requires the implementation to keep track of how often a
            block is requested.
          </t>
          <t>
            An implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> preserve blocks which
            are close to the local peer public key.
          </t>
          <t>
            An implementation <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> provide configurable
            storage quotas and adapt its eviction strategy based on
            the current storage size or other constrained resources.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <!-- FIXME: Here we should (again) discuss how the system is open and
        does not have/require a trust anchor a priori. This is (again) in contrast
      to RELOAD -->
      <t>
        If an upper bound to the maximum number of neighbors in a
        k-bucket is reached, the implementation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
        prefer to preserve the oldest working connections instead of
        new connections.  This makes Sybil attacks <xref
        target="Sybil"/> less effective as an adversary would have to
        invest more resources over time to mount an effective attack.
      </t>
      <t>
	The <tt>ComputeOutDegree</tt> function limits the
	<tt>REPL_LVL</tt> to a maximum of 16. This imposes
	an upper limit on bandwidth amplification an attacker
	may achieve for a given network size and topology.
      </t>
      <section>
        <name>Disjoint Underlay or Application Protocol Support</name>
      <t>
        We note that peers
	implementing disjoint sets of underlay protocols may
	experience difficulties communicating (unless other peers
	bridge the respective underlays). Similarly, peers that
	do not support a particular application will not be able
	to validate application-specific payloads and may thus be
	tricked into storing or forwarding corrupt blocks.
      </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Approximate Result Filtering</name>
        <t>
          When a <tt>FindApproximate</tt> flag is encountered in a
          query, a peer will try to respond with the closest block it
          has that is not filtered by the result Bloom filter
          (<tt>RF</tt>).  Implementations <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> ensure
          that the cost of evaluating any such query is reasonably
          small.  For example, implementations <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>
          consider ways to avoid an exhaustive search of their
          database.  Not doing so can lead to denial of service
          attacks as there could be cases where too many local results
          are filtered by the result filter.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Access Control</name>
        <t>
          By design R<sup>5</sup>N does not rely on strict admission
          control through the use of either centralized enrollment
          servers or pre-shared keys.  This is a key distintion over
          protocols that do rely on this kind of access control such
          as <xref target="RFC6940"/> which, like R<sup>5</sup>N,
          provides a peer-to-peer (P2P) signaling protocol with
          extensible routing and topology mechanisms.  Some
          decentralized applications, such as the GNU Name System
          (<xref target="RFC9498"/>), require an open system that
          enables ad-hoc participation.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Block-level confidentiality and privacy</name>
        <t>
          Applications using the DHT APIs to store application-specific
          block types may have varying security and privacy requirements.
          R<sup>5</sup>N does NOT provide any kind confidentiality or
          privacy for blocks, for example through the use of cryptography.
          This must be provided by the application as part of the block
          type design.
          One example where confidentiality and privacy are required are
          GNS records and their record blocks as defined in
          <xref target="RFC9498"/>.
          Other possibilities to protect the block objects may be implemented
          using ideas from other efforts such as Oblivious HTTP and its
          encapsulation of HTTP requests and responses <xref target="RFC9458"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Protocol extensions and cryptographic agility</name>
        <t>
          R<sup>5</sup>N makes heavy use of the Ed25519 cryptosystem.
          It cannot be ruled out that the relevant primitives
          are broken at any point in the future.
          In this case, the R<sup>5</sup>N design can be reused by modifying
          the messages and related artifacts defined in
          <xref target="message_components"/>.
          In order to extend and modify the R<sup>5</sup>N protocol
          in general and to replace cryptographic primitives in particular,
          new message types (<tt>MTYPE</tt> fields) can be registered in
          <xref target="GANA"/> and the message formats updated accordingly.
          Peers processing messages <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>
          modify the <tt>MTYPE</tt> field in order to prevent
          possible security downgrades.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>Availability versus security tradeoffs in routing table evictions</name>
        <t>
          R<sup>5</sup>N does not implement locality-sensitive as it does not
          preferentially evict distant nodes (where distance is a metric based
          on closeness in the physical network).
          Locality-sensitive routing table eviction may offer performance improvements
          especially if the local network and its resources can be leveraged
          more efficiently.
          Similarly, if requests (and responses) can be contained to the local
          network, this can offer better privacy.
          But, this an important security trade-off when choosing network locality over
          R<sup>5</sup>N's eviction strategy (<xref target="routing_table"/>):
          "Flash mob"-style attackers that quickly spin up a large number of nodes
          a target node's proximity are displacing legitimate, benign neighbours.
          In case of the R<sup>5</sup>N eviction strategy these will likely not
          degrade the routing table to the same degree because long-lived connections
          are preferred.
          This in turn forces an attacker to run their nodes for a long time to run a
          successful attack.
        </t>
        <t>
          It is important to highlight that in order to address the R<sup>5</sup>N threat
          and security model (<xref target="security_model"/>), the routing starts with a
          random walk.
          Should all nodes implement a locality sensitive eviction strategy, the theoretical
          effectiveness of this measure would drastically decrease.
          R<sup>5</sup>N puts security and availability under its threat model, over performance
          and privacy.
        </t>
        <t>
          It should be noted that any reasonable locality metric will choose nodes
          that implicitly provide more stable network connections than distant nodes as
          the probability for network failures grows with physical distance.
          As a consequence it can be assumed that a locality-sensitive metric and
          R<sup>5</sup>N's eviction strategy eventually converge into a similar
          situation where a node primarily maintains a routing table consisting of
          long-lived and somewhat local connections.
        </t>
      </section>


    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
	IANA maintains a registry called the "Uniform Resource Identifier
	(URI) Schemes" registry.
	The registry should be updated to include
	an entry for the 'gnunet' URI scheme.  IANA is requested to
	update that entry to reference this document when published
	as an RFC.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="gana" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>GANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="gana_block_type" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Block Type Registry</name>
      <t>
        GANA <xref target="GANA"/>
        is requested to create a "DHT Block Types" registry.
        The registry shall record for each entry:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>Name: The name of the block type (case-insensitive ASCII
          string, restricted to alphanumeric characters</li>
        <li>Number: 32-bit</li>
        <li>Comment: Optionally, a brief English text describing the purpose of
          the block type (in UTF-8)</li>
        <li>Contact: Optionally, the contact information of a person to contact for
          further information</li>
        <li>References: Required, references (such as an RFC) specifying the block type and its block functions</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        The registration policy for this sub-registry is "First Come First
        Served", as described in <xref target="RFC8126"/>.
        GANA created the registry as follows:
      </t>
      <!-- NOTE: changed GNS Reference to This.I-D because we either need to define it here
           or in the GNS RFC. And I think here is better or in a separate document
           => not in here. Use separate document for NAMERECORD draft.
           -MSC -->
      <figure anchor="figure_btypenums" title="The Block Type Registry.">
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Number| Name           | References | Description
------+----------------+------------+-------------------------
0       ANY              [This.I-D]   Reserved
13      DHT_HELLO        [This.I-D]   Address data for a peer

Contact: r5n-registry@gnunet.org
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="gana_gnunet_url" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>GNUnet URI Schema Subregistry</name>
      <t>
        GANA <xref target="GANA"/>
        is requested to create a "gnunet://" sub-registry.
        The registry shall record for each entry:
      </t>
      <ul>
        <li>Name: The name of the subsystem (case-insensitive ASCII
          string, restricted to alphanumeric characters)</li>
        <li>Comment: Optionally, a brief English text describing the purpose of
          the subsystem (in UTF-8)</li>
        <li>Contact: Optionally, the contact information of a person to contact for
          further information</li>
        <li>References: Optionally, references describing the syntax of the URL
          (such as an RFC or LSD)</li>
      </ul>
      <t>
        <!-- FIXME: See GNS wording for this which is already improved / ISE compliant -->
        The registration policy for this sub-registry is "First Come First
        Served", as described in <xref target="RFC8126"/>.
        GANA created this registry as follows:
      </t>
      <figure anchor="figure_gnunetscheme" title="GNUnet scheme Subregistry.">
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Name           | References | Description
---------------+------------+-------------------------
HELLO            [This.I-D]   How to contact a peer.
ADDRESS          N/A          Network address.
Contact: gnunet-registry@gnunet.org
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="gana_signature_purpose" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>GNUnet Signature Purpose Registry</name>
      <t>
        GANA amended the "GNUnet Signature Purpose" registry
        as follows:
      </t>
      <figure anchor="figure_purposenums" title="The Signature Purpose Registry Entries.">
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Purpose | Name            | References | Description
--------+-----------------+------------+---------------
6         DHT PATH ELEMENT  [This.I-D]   DHT message routing data
7         HELLO PAYLOAD     [This.I-D]   Peer contact information
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </section>

      <section anchor="gana_message_type" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>GNUnet Message Type Registry</name>
      <t>
        GANA is requested to amend the "GNUnet Message Type" registry
        as follows:
      </t>
      <figure anchor="figure_messagetypeenums" title="The Message Type Registry Entries.">
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Type    | Name            | References | Description
--------+-----------------+------------+---------------
146       DHT PUT          [This.I-D]    Store information in DHT
147       DHT GET          [This.I-D]    Request information from DHT
148       DHT RESULT       [This.I-D]    Return information from DHT
157       HELLO Message    [This.I-D]    Peer contact information

]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
      <section anchor="implementation_deployment" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Implementation and deployment status</name>
       <t>
         There are two implementations conforming to this specification written
         in C and Go, respectively. The C implementation as part of GNUnet
         <xref target="GNUnetGNS"/> represents the original
         and reference implementation. The Go implementation
         <xref target="GoGNS"/> demonstrates how two implementations of GNS are
         interoperable if they are built on top of the same underlying
         DHT storage.
       </t>
       <t>
         Currently, the GNUnet peer-to-peer network <xref target="GNUnet"/>
         is an active deployment of R<sup>5</sup>N.
         It's primary but not only purpose is to provide the storage underlay
         for the GNU Name System <xref target="RFC9498"/>.
         The <xref target="GoGNS"/> implementation shows how R<sup>5</sup>N implementations
         can interoperate.
       </t>
    </section>
    <!-- gana -->
    <!--<section anchor="testvectors">
      <name>Test Vectors</name>
    </section>-->
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>

        &RFC2119;
        &RFC2663;
        &RFC3561;
        &RFC3629;
        &RFC3986;
        &RFC4634;
        &RFC5234;
        &RFC5245;
        &RFC6940;
        &RFC8126;
        &RFC8174;
        &RFC9458;
        &RFC9498;

      <reference anchor="ed25519" target="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-642-23951-9_9"><front><title>High-Speed High-Security Signatures</title><author initials="D." surname="Bernstein" fullname="Daniel Bernstein"><organization>University of Illinois at Chicago</organization></author><author initials="N." surname="Duif" fullname="Niels Duif"><organization>Technische Universiteit Eindhoven</organization></author><author initials="T." surname="Lange" fullname="Tanja Lange"><organization>Technische Universiteit Eindhoven</organization></author><author initials="P." surname="Schwabe" fullname="Peter Schwabe"><organization>National Taiwan University</organization></author><author initials="B." surname="Yang" fullname="Bo-Yin Yang"><organization>Academia Sinica</organization></author><date year="2011"/></front></reference>

      <reference anchor="GANA" target="https://gana.gnunet.org/"><front><title>GNUnet Assigned Numbers Authority (GANA)</title><author><organization>GNUnet e.V.</organization></author><date month="April" year="2020"/></front></reference>



    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <reference anchor="R5N" target="https://doi.org/10.1109/ICNSS.2011.6060022">
        <front>
          <title>R5N: Randomized recursive routing for restricted-route networks</title>
          <author initials="N. S." surname="Evans" fullname="Nathan S. Evans">
            <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Grothoff" fullname="Christian Grothoff">
            <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2011"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="NSE" target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-30045-5_23">
        <front>
          <title>Efficient and Secure Decentralized Network Size Estimation</title>
          <author initials="N. S." surname="Evans" fullname="Nathan S. Evans">
            <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="B." surname="Polot" fullname="Bartlomiej Polot">
            <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Grothoff" fullname="Christian Grothoff">
            <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2012"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Kademlia" target="http://css.csail.mit.edu/6.824/2014/papers/kademlia.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Kademlia: A peer-to-peer information system based on the xor metric.</title>
          <author initials="P." surname="Maymounkov" fullname="Petar Maymounkov">
          </author>
          <author initials="D." surname="Mazieres" fullname="David Mazieres">
          </author>
          <date year="2002"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Sybil" target="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/3-540-45748-8_24">
        <front>
          <title>The Sybil Attack</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Douceur" fullname="John R. Douceur">
          </author>
          <date year="2002"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Smallworldmix" target="https://api.semanticscholar.org/CorpusID:44240877">
        <front>
          <title>A Measurement of Mixing Time in Social Networks</title>
          <author initials="M." surname="Dell'Amico" fullname="Matteo Dell'Amico">
          </author>
          <date year="2009"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="Smallworld" target="https://www.nature.com/articles/35022643">
        <front>
          <title>Navigation in a small world</title>
          <author initials="J." surname="Kleinberg" fullname="Jon M. Kleinberg">
          </author>
          <date year="2000"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      <reference anchor="cadet" target="https://doi.org/10.1109/MedHocNet.2014.6849107">
        <front>
          <title>CADET: Confidential ad-hoc decentralized end-to-end transport</title>
          <author initials="B." surname="Polot" fullname="Bartlomiej Polot">
            <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Grothoff" fullname="Christian Grothoff">
            <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
       <reference anchor="GNUnet" target="https://gnunet.org">
         <front>
           <title>The GNUnet Project</title>
          <author>
            <organization>GNUnet e.V.</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
       </reference>
       <reference anchor="GNUnetGNS" target="https://git.gnunet.org/gnunet.git/tree/src/gns">
         <front>
           <title>The GNUnet GNS Implementation</title>
          <author>
            <organization>GNUnet e.V.</organization>
          </author>
        </front>
       </reference>

       <reference anchor="GoGNS" target="https://github.com/bfix/gnunet-go/tree/master/src/gnunet/service/gns">
         <front>
           <title>The Go GNS Implementation</title>
          <author initials="B." surname="Fix" fullname="Bernd Fix">
          </author>
        </front>
       </reference>

    </references>
    <section anchor="bloom_filters" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Bloom filters in R<sup>5</sup>N</name>
      <t>
	R<sup>5</sup>N uses Bloom filters in several places.  This section
	gives some general background on Bloom filters and defines functions
	on this data structure shared by the various use-cases in R<sup>5</sup>N.
      </t>
      <t>
        A Bloom filter (BF) is a space-efficient probabilistic datastructure
        to test if an element is part of a set of elements.
        Elements are identified by an element ID.
        Since a BF is a probabilistic datastructure, it is possible to have
        false-positives: when asked if an element is in the set, the answer from
        a BF is either "no" or "maybe".
      </t>
      <t>
        Bloom filters are defined as a string of <tt>L</tt> bits.
        The bits are initially always empty, meaning that the bits are set to
        zero.
        There are two functions which can be invoked on the Bloom filter "bf":
        BF-SET(bf, e) and BF-TEST(bf, e) where "e" is an element that is to
        be added to the Bloom filter or queried against the set.
      </t>
      <t>
        A mapping function M is used to map each ID of each element from the set to a
        subset of k bits.
        In the original proposal by Bloom, M is non-injective and can thus map the same
        element multiple times to the same bit.
        The type of the mapping function can thus be described by the following
        mathematical notation:
      </t>
      <figure anchor="figure_bf_func" title="Bloom filter mapping function.">
        <artwork><![CDATA[
        ------------------------------------
        # M: E->B^k
        ------------------------------------
        # L = Number of bits
        # B = 0,1,2,3,4,...L-1 (the bits)
        # k = Number of bits per element
        # E = Set of elements
        ------------------------------------
        Example: L=256, k=3
        M('element-data') = {4,6,255}
]]>
        </artwork>
      </figure>
      <t>
        When adding an element to the Bloom filter <tt>bf</tt> using
        <tt>BF-SET(bf, e)</tt>, each integer <tt>n</tt> of the mapping
        <tt>M(e)</tt> is interpreted as a bit offset <tt>n mod L</tt> within
        <tt>bf</tt> and set to 1.
      </t>
      <t>
        When testing if an element may be in the Bloom filter <tt>bf</tt> using
        <tt>BF-TEST(bf,e)</tt>, each bit offset <tt>n mod L</tt> within
        <tt>bf</tt> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> have been set to 1.
        Otherwise, the element is not considered to be in the Bloom filter.
      </t>
    </section>
  <section anchor="overlay" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Overlay Operations</name>
      <t>
        An implementation of this specification commonly exposes the two overlay
        operations "GET" and "PUT".
        The following are non-normative examples of APIs for those operations.
        Their behaviour is described prosaically in order to give implementers a fuller
        picture of the protocol.
      </t>
      <section>
        <name>GET operation</name>
        <t>
          A basic GET operation interface may be exposed as:
        </t>
        <t>
          <tt>GET(Query-Key, Block-Type) -> Results as List</tt>
        </t>
        <t>
          The procedure typically takes at least two arguments to initiate a lookup:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt><tt>QueryKey</tt>:</dt>
          <dd>
            is the 512-bit key to look for in the DHT.
          </dd>
          <dt>Block-Type:</dt>
          <dd>
            is the type of block to look for, possibly "any".
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The GET procedure may allow additional optional parameters in order to
          control or modify the query:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Replication-Level:</dt>
          <dd>
            is an integer which controls how many nearest peers the request
            should reach.
          </dd>
          <dt>Flags:</dt>
          <dd>
            is an 8-bit vector which indicates certain
            processing requirements for messages.
            Any combination of flags as defined in <xref target="route_flags"/>
            may be specified.
          </dd>
          <dt>eXtended-Query (XQuery):</dt>
          <dd>
            is medatadata which may be
            required depending on the respective <tt>Block-Type</tt>.
            A <tt>Block-Type</tt> must define if the <tt>XQuery</tt> can or must
            be used and what the specific format of its contents should be.
            Extended queries are in general used to implement domain-specific filters.
            These might be particularly useful in combination with FindApproximate
            to add a well-defined filter by an application-specific distance.
            Regardless, the DHT does not define any particular semantics for an XQuery.
            See also <xref target="blockstorage"/>.
          </dd>
          <dt>Result-Filter:</dt>
          <dd>
            is data for a <tt>Block-type</tt>-specific filter
	    which allows applications to
	    indicate results which are
	    not relevant anymore to the
            caller (see <xref target="result_filter"/>).
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The GET procedure should be implemented as an asynchronous
	  operation that returns individual results as they are found
	  in the DHT.  It should terminate only once the application
	  explicitly cancels the operation.  A single result commonly
	  consists of:</t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Block-Type:</dt>
          <dd>
            is the desired type of block in the result.
          </dd>
          <dt>Block-Data:</dt>
          <dd>
            is the application-specific block payload. Contents are
            specific to the <tt>Block-Type</tt>.
          </dd>
          <dt>Block-Expiration:</dt>
          <dd>
            is the expiration time of the block. After this time, the result should no
	    longer be used.
          </dd>
          <dt>Key:</dt>
          <dd>
            is the key under which the block was stored. This may be different from the
            key that was queried if the flag <tt>FindApproximate</tt> was set.
          </dd>
          <dt>GET-Path:</dt>
          <dd>
            is a signed path of the public keys of peers which the
            query traversed through the network. The DHT will try to
            make the path available if the <tt>RecordRoute</tt> flag
            was set by the application calling the PUT procedure. The
            reported path may have been truncated from the beginning.
            The API <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> signal truncation by exposing
            the <tt>Truncated</tt> flag.
          </dd>
          <dt>PUT-Path:</dt>
          <dd>
            is a signed path of the public keys of peers which the
            result message traversed.  The DHT will try to make the
            path available if the <tt>RecordRoute</tt> flag was set
            for the GET procedure.  The reported path may have been
            truncated from the beginning. The API
            <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> signal truncation by exposing the
            <tt>Truncated</tt> flag.  As the block was cached by the
            node at the end of this path, this path is more likely to
            be stale compared to the <tt>GET-Path</tt>.
          </dd>
          <dt>Truncated:</dt>
          <dd>
            is true if the <tt>GET-Path</tt> or <tt>PUT-Path</tt>
            was truncated, otherwise false.
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>PUT operation</name>
        <t>
          A PUT operation interface may be exposed as:
        </t>
        <t>
          <tt>PUT(Key, Block-Type, Block-Expiration, Block-Data)</tt>
        </t>
        <t>
          The procedure typically takes at least four parameters:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Key:</dt>
          <dd>is the key under which to store the block.</dd>
          <dt>Block-Type:</dt>
          <dd>is the type of the block to store.</dd>
          <dt>Block-Expiration:</dt>
          <dd>specifies when the block should expire.</dd>
          <dt>Block-Data:</dt>
          <dd>is the application-specific payload of the block to store.</dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The PUT procedure may accept additional optional parameters that
          control or modify the operation:
        </t>
        <dl>
          <dt>Replication-Level:</dt>
          <dd>
            is an integer which controls how many nearest peers the request
            should reach.
          </dd>
          <dt>Flags:</dt>
          <dd>
            is a bit-vector which indicates certain processing
            requirements for messages.  Any combination of flags as
            defined in <xref target="route_flags"/> may be specified.
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <t>
          The PUT procedure does not necessarily yield any information.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  <section anchor="hello_url">
        <name>HELLO URLs</name>
        <t>
	  The general format of a <tt>HELLO</tt> URL uses "gnunet://"
          as the scheme, followed by "hello/" for the name
          of the GNUnet subsystem, followed by "/"-separated values
          with the GNS Base32 encoding <xref target="RFC9498"/> of
          the peer public key, a Base32-encoded EdDSA signature
          <xref target="ed25519"/>, and an expiration
          time in seconds since the UNIX Epoch in decimal format.
	  After this a "?" begins a list of key-value pairs where the key
          is the URI scheme of one of the peer's addresses and the value
          is the URL-escaped payload of the address URI without the "://".
        </t>
        <t>
          The general syntax of <tt>HELLO</tt> URLs specified using
          Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) of <xref target="RFC5234"/> is:
        </t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
hello-URL = "gnunet://hello[:version]/" meta [ "?" addrs ]
version = *(DIGIT)
meta = pid "/" sig "/" exp
pid = *bchar
sig = *bchar
exp = *DIGIT
addrs = addr *( "&" addr )
addr = addr-name "=" addr-value
addr-name = scheme
addr-value = *pchar
bchar = *(ALPHA / DIGIT)
]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure>
	<t>
         'scheme' is defined in <xref target="RFC3986" /> in Section 3.1.
         'pchar' is defined in <xref target="RFC3986" />, Appendix A.
        </t>
        <t>
          For example, consider the following URL:
        </t>
	<figure>
	  <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
          gnunet://hello/1MVZC83SFHXMADVJ5F4
          S7BSM7CCGFNVJ1SMQPGW9Z7ZQBZ689ECG/
          CFJD9SY1NY5VM9X8RC5G2X2TAA7BCVCE16
          726H4JEGTAEB26JNCZKDHBPSN5JD3D60J5
          GJMHFJ5YGRGY4EYBP0E2FJJ3KFEYN6HYM0G/
          1708333757?foo=example.com&bar+baz=1.2.3.4%3A5678%2Ffoo
]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure>
	<t>
    It specifies that the peer with the <tt>pid</tt> "1MVZ..."
          is reachable via "foo" at "example.com" and "bar+baz" at
          "1.2.3.4" on port 5678 until
          1708333757 seconds after the Epoch.  Note that "foo"
	  and "bar+baz" here are underspecified and just used as a simple example.
	  In practice, the <tt>addr-name</tt> refers to a scheme supported by a
	  DHT underlay.
        </t>
      </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
