<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
<!ENTITY RFC1034 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1035 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1928 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1928.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!--<!ENTITY RFC2693 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2693.xml">-->
<!ENTITY RFC2782 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3629 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3686 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3686.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3826 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3826.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4033 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5237 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5237.xml">
<!--<!ENTITY RFC3912 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3912.xml">-->
<!ENTITY RFC5890 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5890.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5895 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5895.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6066 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6066.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6761 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6761.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6895 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6895.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6979 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6979.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7363 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7363.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8806 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8806.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7748 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7748.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8244 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8244.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8324 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8324.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8499 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9106 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9106.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9180 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9180.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dnsop-alt-tld PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-alt-tld.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-schanzen-hpke-elligator-kem-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="" updates=""
     submissionType="independent" 
     xml:lang="en"
     version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.26.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The HPKE Elligator KEM">
      The HPKE Elligator KEM
    </title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-schanzen-hpke-elligator-kem-00"/>
    <author fullname="Martin Schanzenbach" initials="M." surname="Schanzenbach">
      <organization>Fraunhofer AISEC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Lichtenbergstrasse 11</street>
          <city>Garching</city>
          <code>85748</code>
          <country>DE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>martin.schanzenbach@aisec.fraunhofer.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Pedram Fardzadeh" initials="P." surname="Fardzadeh">
      <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Boltzmannstrasse 3</street>
          <city>Garching</city>
          <code>85748</code>
          <country>DE</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pedram.fardzadeh@tum.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Independent Stream</workgroup>
    <keyword>transport protocols</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        This document contains the GNUnet communicator
        specification.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines the normative wire format of communicator protocols,
        cryptographic routines and security
        considerations for use by implementers.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification was developed outside the IETF and does not have
        IETF consensus.  It is published here to inform readers about the
        function of GNUnet communicators, guide future communicator implementations, and ensure
        interoperability among implementations including with the pre-existing
        GNUnet implementation.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        Diffie-Hellman-based KEMs (DHKEMs) allow us to securely establish a secret between two parties.
        However, an observer can quickly identify the exchanged encapsulation in DHKEMs as public keys.
        In the presence of a passive eavesdropping attacker, packets could drop based on this information,
        preventing communication between peers as outlined in <xref target="BHKL13"/>.
        The presented solution in  <xref target="BHKL13"/> is called "Elligator" and allows us to produce random-looking
        representations of curve points.
        This leaves an attacker with fewer options: either do nothing or intercept most random-looking packets,
        thereby potentially disrupting a large part of today's internet communication.
      </t>
      <t>
        In the case of Montgomery curves, such as Curve25519, a point [X, Y] on that curve (e.g., the ephemeral public key) follows the equation 
        <tt>Y^2 = X^3 + A * X^2 + X mod P</tt>, where A and P are parameters for Curve25519 specified in Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC7748"/>. For any 
        valid x-coordinate, the left side of the equation is always a quadratic number. An attacker could read the x-coordinate
        and verify if this property holds. While this property holds for any valid Curve25519 point, it only holds for a 
        random number in about 50% of the cases. By observing multiple communication attempts, an attacker can be sure that curve points are being sent if the property consistently holds. 
        To circumvent this attack, curve points should be encoded into property-less numbers, making valid and invalid curve points indistinguishable 
        to an outside observer.
        The Elligator encoding function (also known as the "inverse map") and decoding function (also known as the "direct map") implement this feature. 
      </t>
      <t>
        In this document, we define and use an Elligator transformation for X25519 curve points based on the Curve25519 transformations
        in <xref target="BHKL13"/> to be used in a Key Encapsulation Mechanim (KEM) for use
        in HPKE <xref target="RFC9180"/>
        and its security considerations for use by implementers.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification was developed outside the IETF and does not have
        IETF consensus.  It is published here to guide implementers
        and ensure interoperability among implementations.
      </t>
      <section numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Requirements Notation</name>
        <t>
          The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
          "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
          "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
          when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="notation" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Notation</name>
      <t>
        We use the notation and terminology of <xref target="RFC9180"/> throughout
        this document.
        In addition, we define:
      </t>
     <dl>
       <dt>coinFlip()</dt>
       <dd>
         A helper function that returns "heads" or "tails". Each result is
         returned with a likelihood of 50%.
       </dd>
     </dl>    </section>
    <section anchor="elligator_dhkem" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Elligator DHKEM</name>
      <t>
        The Elligator HPKE DHKEM utilizes Elligator to encode and decode the ephemeral public keys
        as described in Section 5 of <xref target="BHKL13"/>.
        We define our KEM analogous to <xref target="RFC9180"/> Section 4.
        The <tt>kem_id</tt> in the <tt>suite_id</tt> for the Elligator KEM is <tt>TBD</tt>
      </t>
      <t>
        The <tt>ExtractAndExpand()</tt>, <tt>Encap()</tt>
        and <tt>Decap()</tt> functions (and their authenticated variants) can remain unchanged and <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
        implemented as defined in Section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC9180"/>.
        The serialization functions <tt>SerializePublicKey</tt> and <tt>DeserializePublicKey</tt> are defined in the following for Curve25519.
      </t>
      <section anchor="elligator_dhkem_keygen" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>GenerateKeyPair()</name>
        <t>
          First, not all X25519 key pairs are suitable candidates for Elligator.
          In particular, not all Curve25519 points have the property that the Elligator encoding and subsequent
          decoding result in the original point (See <xref target="security_elligator"/> for details).
          To create a Curve25519 point that can be used with Elligator, one needs to find a curve point
          for which this property holds.
          When generating a key pair suitable for Elligator, the general idea is to create both a random high-order point and a low-order point.
          Adding them together results in a curve point that is evenly distributed on the whole curve.
          One heuristic is to generate random key pairs until one such point is found:
        </t>
        <t>
          Let <tt>G</tt> be the generator of the prime order group of Ed25519 and <tt>H</tt> the generator of the low order subgroup of
          Ed25519.
          <tt>EdToCurve()</tt> is a function that converts Ed25519 points to their corresponding Curve25519 points.
          We define "GenerateElligatorKeyPair()" as follows:
        </t>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
      GenerateElligatorKeyPair():
        VALID := 0
        while(!VALID):
          skX := random(Nsk)
          skX[0] &= 24
          skX[31] &= 127
          skX[31] |= 64
          E_high := skX * G
          E_low := (skX mod 8) * H
          E := E_high + E_low
          pkX := EdToCurve(E)
          if ElligatorDec(ElligatorEnc(pkX)) == pkX:
            return (skX,pkX)
          ]]></artwork>
        <t>
          We operate on the Edwards representation for the key generation because the necessary
          low-order point additions are more efficient in most implementations than they would be in their Montgomery form.
          A conversion from Edwards to their birationally equivalent Montgomery form is always possible and found in
          most cryptographic library implementations.
        </t>
        <t>
          The <tt>GenerateKeyPair</tt> algorithm <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be implemented to produce a key pair suitable for
          Elligator.
          The <tt>GenerateElligatorKeyPair()</tt> algorithm defined here is <bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>.
          Other, more efficient key generation algorithms <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> be used.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="elligator_dhkem_serialize" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SerializePublicKey()</name>
        <t>
          The serialization functions incorporate the Elligator inverse and direct map functions to obfuscate a curve
          point.
          The Elligator literature calls the obfuscated curve point a "representative". In the following, the "representative"
          is named pkXm, where X stands for any of the roles defined in <xref target="RFC9180"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          Let <tt>A</tt> and <tt>P</tt> be the parameters for Curve25519 as specified in section 4.1 of <xref target="RFC7748"/>.
          Further, let <tt>X</tt> be any valid x-coordinate of a Curve25519 point, <tt>L()</tt> a function that computes the
          Legendre symbol of a field element with regard to the odd prime <tt>P</tt>.
          Let <tt>sqrt()</tt> denote the square root operation within the field. As each square number has two roots, we need to 
          define the notion of positive and negative numbers. There are multiple valid ways to partition the field 
          elements. For this Elligator, we follow the recommendations of the paper in section 5.1 of <xref target="BHKL13"/> and 
          choose <tt>{0,..., (P-1)/2}</tt> as the set of positive numbers, and consequently <tt>{(P-1)/2 + 1,...,P-1}</tt> as the 
          set of the  negative numbers. Both Elligator's inverse and direct map require us to define a constant non-square number 
          of the finite field. Let <tt>U := sqrt(-1)</tt> be this number.
          The resulting serialization algorithm for the HPKE KEM can then be described as:
        </t>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
      SerializeElligatorPublicKey(pkX):
        if coinFlip() == 1:
          pkXm :=  sqrt(-pkX / ((pkX + A) * U))
        else:
          pkXm :=  sqrt(-(pkX + A) / (U * X))
        if coinFlip() == 1:
          pkXm[31] |= 128
        if coinFlip() == 1:
          pkXm[31] |= 64
        return pkXm
        ]]></artwork>
        <t>
          Note that SerializeElligatorPublicKey(pkX) represents Elligator's inverse map
          with a slight modification: The resulting representative of the inverse map is strictly smaller than 2^254 - 9. Therefore, 
          the most and second most significant bits are always zero, an obvious property an attacker could observe. We avoid this 
          problem by randomly flipping both bits. The target peer will ignore these bits after reception by setting those bits back to zero.
          Similarly, as there are always two roots for each square number, we randomly select one or the other upon each serialization.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="elligator_dhkem_deserialize" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>DeserializePublicKey()</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
      DeserializeElligatorPublicKey(pkXm):
        pkXm[31] &= 63
        V := -A / (1 + U * pkXm^2)
        E := L(V^3 + A * V^2 + V)
        pkX := E * V - (1 - E)(A / 2)
        return pkX
        ]]></artwork>
        <t>
          Note that DeserializeElligatorPublicKey(pkX) represents Elligator's direct map.
          We must, and can safely, clear the most and second most significant bits that were set randomly as
          elaborated above before reconstructing the square root.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security and Privacy Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="security_elligator" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Elligator</name>
      <t>
        Most modern implementations of Curve25519 only generate points from its prime 
        subgroup to circumvent known attacks for which points not within the prime subgroup are susceptible. Those attacks are not an 
        issue in our case as we use the ephemeral secret key only once for computing key material. The exclusive use of the prime subgroup is a recognizable 
        property that an outside observer can easily detect, even when using the encoding function. An attacker could decode the suspected 
        parts of packets to the corresponding Curve25519 points and check if the resulting points are always in the prime subgroup. To circumvent 
        this attack, we must randomly choose the ephemeral key pair from the whole curve as defined in "GenerateElligatorKeyPair()".
      </t>
        <t>
          The intuition behind elligator is based on the following idea: The direct map (here DeserializeElligatorPublicKey(r))
          expects a random field element r. The value r is mapped to two values, for which only one coordinate is a valid Curve25519 x-coordinate.
          One can show the pair of values V_1 := -A / (1 + U * r^2) and V_2 := -A * U * r^2 (1 + U * r^2) always fulfill this property,
          based on the fact that U is a non-square number in the field. The direct map first computes V_1 and checks if V_1 fulfills the curve
          equation. If it does, it returns V_1; otherwise, V_2 is computed and returned instead. The inverse map, 
          (here SerializeElligatorPublicKey(V)) reverses this process and computes the corresponding field element of a valid x-coordinate. 
          Note that for encode and decode public keys, we reverse the call order of the direct and inverse map: First,
          the inverse map is called on the ephemeral public key to retrieve the representative r. This representative is then send to the 
          receiving peer, who calls the direct map to retrieve the corresponding public key. 
        </t>
        <t>
          Note that both for a value r and its negative counterpart -r (in the finite field), the inverse map function will result in the same 
          x-coordinate. Moreover, for two different valid x-coordinates, the resulting representatives of the corresponding encoding calls are 
          different. Conversely, we can't decode both representatives back to their original x-coordinate. This is why the sender 
          eventually tries several random key pairs in GenerateElligatorKeyPair() to create a valid public key that can be used 
          for a key exchange. Also note that this effectively reduces the entropy of our public keys by 1 bit, which is tolerable.
        </t>
        <t>
          In <xref target="BHKL13"/>, Elligator's inverse map takes the sign of y-coordinate as an additional input parameter. Its value determines 
          which of the two terms is used instead of our random selection. Due to 
          known attacks, we also skip the calculation of the corresponding y-coordinate in the decoding function. 
          We omitted the y-coordinate part of both functions because Curve25519 points are solely represented by their x-coordinate in modern cryptosystems. 
          Nevertheless, the desired feature of Elligator is still ensured.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="security_aead" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Combination with AEAD Encryption</name>
        <t>
          When using the Elligator KEM in combination with AEAD encryption schemes, care must be taken to ensure that the
          ciphertext produced by the AEAD cipher is also indistinguishable from random.
          The AEAD schemes listed in <xref target="RFC9180"/> use GCM and Poly1305 authentication tags, which
          should result in ciphertexts that are indistinguishable from random.
          However, future AEAD schemes and, in particular, their authenticators may not exhibit the same
          cryptographic properties.
          This should be considered when assembling HPKE suites with the Elligator KEM.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <!-- gana -->
    <section>
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>
        The "HPKE KEM Identifiers" registry was amended with
        the values from <xref target="kemid-values"/>.
      </t>
      <table anchor="kemid-values" align="center">
        <name slugifiedName="name-kem-ids">KEM IDs</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Value</th>
            <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">KEM</th>
            <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nsecret</th>
            <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nenc</th>
            <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Npk</th>
            <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Nsk</th>
            <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Auth</th>
            <th align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">0x0022</td>
            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">DHKEM(X25519+Elligator, HKDF-SHA256)</td>
            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">32</td>
            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">yes</td>
            <td align="left" colspan="1" rowspan="1">
            This.I-D</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table> 
    </section>
    <section>
         <name>Implementation and Deployment Status</name>
         <t>
         There is one implementation conforming to this specification, written in C. 
         The implementation is part of <xref target="GNUnet"/> and represents the original and reference implementation.
         </t>
         <t>
         The basic Elligator primitives GenerateKeyPair(), SerializePublicKey() and DeserializePublicKey() 
         are present in <xref target="GNUnetElligator"/>. The corresponding KEM primitives are part of <xref target="GNUnetHPKE"/>.
         </t>
         </section>
    <!-- <section>
    <name>Acknowledgements</name>
    <t>
    FIXME
    </t>
    </section> -->
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>Normative References</name>
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC7748;
      &RFC8174;
      &RFC9180;

    </references>
    <references>
      <name>Informative References</name>
      <reference anchor="BHKL13" target="https://eprint.iacr.org/2013/325.pdf">
        <front>
          <title>Elligator: Elliptic-curve points indistinguishable from uniform random strings</title>
          <author initials="D.J" surname="Bernstein"
                  fullname="Daniel J.  Bernstein">
          </author>
          <author initials="M." surname="Hamburg"
                  fullname="Mike Hamburg">
          </author>
          <author initials="A." surname="Krasnova"
                  fullname="Anna Krasnova">
          </author>
          <author initials="T." surname="Lange"
                  fullname="Tanja Lange">
          </author>
          <date month="August" year="2013" />
        </front>
      </reference>
      <!--<reference anchor="LSD0007" target="https://lsd.gnunet.org/lsd0007">
        <front>
          <title>The GNUnet communicators</title>
          <author initials="M" surname="Schanzenbach"
                  fullname="Martin Schanzenbach">
          </author>
          <author initials="C." surname="Grothoff"
                  fullname="Christian Grothoff">
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Fardzadeh"
                  fullname="Pedram Fardzadeh">
          </author>
          <date month="July" year="2024" />
        </front>
      </reference>-->
    <reference anchor="GNUnet" target="https://git.gnunet.org/gnunet.git">
        <front>
          <title>gnunet.git - GNUnet core repository</title>
          <author initials="GNUnet e.V." surname=""
                  fullname="">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2023" />
        </front>
    </reference>
    <reference anchor="GNUnetElligator" target="https://git.gnunet.org/gnunet.git/tree/src/lib/util/crypto_elligator.c">
        <front>
          <title>gnunet.git - Elligator primitives implementation in GNUnet core repository</title>
          <author initials="M" surname="Schanzenbach"
                  fullname="Martin Schanzenbach">
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Fardzadeh"
                  fullname="Pedram Fardzadeh">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2023" />
        </front>
    </reference>
    <reference anchor="GNUnetHPKE" target="https://git.gnunet.org/gnunet.git/tree/src/lib/util/crypto_hpke.c">
        <front>
          <title>gnunet.git - HPKE Primitive implementation in GNUnet core repository</title>
          <author initials="M" surname="Schanzenbach"
                  fullname="Martin Schanzenbach">
          </author>
          <author initials="P." surname="Fardzadeh"
                  fullname="Pedram Fardzadeh">
          </author>
          <date month="" year="2023" />
        </front>
    </reference>
    </references>
    
    
    <section>
      <name>Elligator implementation</name>
      <t>
        This section provides a test vector for the Elligator KEM and should aid in verifying implementations. 
        Note that Elligator has two parameters: the set of positive and negative numbers, and a non-square number U
        within the finite field, as described in section 5.1 of <xref target="BHKL13"/>. The displayed test vectors assume that the set of positive 
        numbers is defined as {0,...,(P-1)/2}, the set of negative numbers as {(P-1)/2 + 1,...,P−1} and U is the non-square number 
        sqrt(-1). The depicted coin flips are used in the order of the coinFlip() calls in SerializeElligatorPublicKey(pkX), namely 
        coin flip 1 for choosing the pkXm term, coin flip 2 for the MSB and coin flip 3 for the second MSB.
        Unless indicated otherwise, the test vectors are provided as little-endian hexadecimal byte arrays.
      </t>
      <section>
        <name>Elligator KEM</name>
        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
coin flip 1: 0
coin flip 2: 1
coin flip 3: 1
pkEm:
3f73ee0dd1970ff957f7ec15e0b5151166be3046e6a8b0ee53beca395b74e42c

skEm:
09395966d6d1c493b9917dd12c8dd24e2c05c081c98a67eb2d6dff622ec9c069

skRm:
f33887a8562dad5151e9289a0afa1301ccc698917850d56ea409a9949497baa4

pkRm:
3febadac122d397725ff580f6ce9a3e1c1c4a7de19807f13d383f2f9b6467136

enc:
da0f7edaefed18a99f0b73a789e51c4c6e80664190ae3c8ae4e95b9d926a34f7

key:
46eff65b5313f41fbaffc7adf98f5df03ab4e4f46ae62a2c7ecbe1f0ae83280b
        ]]></artwork>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
