<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
<!ENTITY RFC1034 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1035 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1928 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1928.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!--<!ENTITY RFC2693 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2693.xml">-->
<!ENTITY RFC2782 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3629 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3686 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3686.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3826 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3826.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4033 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5237 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5237.xml">
<!--<!ENTITY RFC3912 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3912.xml">-->
<!ENTITY RFC5869 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5869.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5890 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5890.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5895 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5895.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6066 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6066.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6234 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6761 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6761.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6895 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6895.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6979 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6979.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7363 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7363.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8806 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8806.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7748 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7748.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8032 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8032.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8244 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8244.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8324 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8324.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8499 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9114 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9114.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9106 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9106.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC9180 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9180.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dnsop-alt-tld PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-alt-tld.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
     category="info"
     docName="draft-gnunet-communicators-00"
     ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="" updates=""
     submissionType="independent" 
     xml:lang="en"
     version="3">
 <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.26.0 -->
 <front>
  <title abbrev="The GNUnet communicators">
   The GNUnet communicators
  </title>
  <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-gnunet-communicators-00"/>
  <author fullname="Martin Schanzenbach" initials="M." surname="Schanzenbach">
   <organization>Fraunhofer AISEC</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Lichtenbergstrasse 11</street>
     <city>Garching</city>
     <code>85748</code>
     <country>DE</country>
    </postal>
    <email>martin.schanzenbach@aisec.fraunhofer.de</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Christian Grothoff" initials="C." surname="Grothoff">
   <organization>Berner Fachhochschule</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Hoeheweg 80</street>
     <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
     <code>2501</code>
     <country>CH</country>
    </postal>
    <email>christian.grothoff@bfh.ch</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="Pedram Fardzadeh" initials="P." surname="Fardzadeh">
    <organization>Technischen Universität München</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Boltzmannstrasse 3</street>
     <city>Garching</city>
     <code>85748</code>
     <country>DE</country>
    </postal>
    <email>pedram.fardzadeh@tum.de</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  <author fullname="ch3" initials="" surname="ch3">
    <organization>GNUnet e.V.</organization>
    <address>
      <postal>
        <street></street>
        <city>Lenggries</city>
        <code></code>
        <country>DE</country>
      </postal>
      <email>ch3@mailbox.org</email>
    </address>
  </author>


  <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
  <area>General</area>
  <workgroup>Independent Stream</workgroup>
  <keyword>transport protocols</keyword>
  <abstract>
    <t>
      This document contains the GNUnet communicator
      specification.
    </t>
    <t>
      This document defines the normative wire format of communicator protocols,
      cryptographic routines and security
      considerations for use by implementers.
    </t>
    <t>
      This specification was developed outside the IETF and does not have
      IETF consensus.  It is published here to inform readers about the
      function of GNUnet communicators, guide future communicator implementations, and ensure
      interoperability among implementations including with the pre-existing
      GNUnet implementation.
    </t>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <middle>
   <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>Introduction</name>
     <t>
       This document defines the normative wire format of resource
       records, resolution processes, cryptographic routines and
       security considerations for use by implementers.
     </t>
     <t>
       This specification was developed outside the IETF and does not have
       IETF consensus.  It is published here to guide GNS implementers
       and to ensure interoperability among implementations.
     </t>
     <section numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Requirements Notation</name>
       <t>
         The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
         "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
         "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
         BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
         when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
       </t>
     </section>
   </section>
   <section>
     <name>Terminology</name>
     <dl>
       <dt>Communicator</dt>
       <dd>
         What is a communicator?
       </dd>
       <dt>Peer Identity</dt>
       <dd>
         Peer IDs in GNUnet are Ed25519 public keys as defined <xref target="RFC8032"/>
         and serialized accordingly.
       </dd>
     </dl>
   </section>
   <section>
     <name>Notation</name>
     <t>
       We use the notation from <xref target="RFC9180"/> and <xref target="LSD0011"/>.
       In addition, we define:
     </t>
     <dl>
       <dt>(skXed, pkXed)</dt>
       <dd>
         A key pair is used in role X, where X is one of S as sender or R as recipient, respectively;
         skXed is the Ed25519 private key and pkXed is the Ed25519 public key as defined in
         <xref target="RFC8032"/>.
       </dd>
     </dl>
   </section>   <section anchor="overview" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>Overview</name>
     <t>
       Each communicator must specify its (global) communication characteristics,
       which for now only say whether the communication is reliable (e.g., TCP, HTTPS)
       or unreliable (e.g., UDP, WLAN).
       Each communicator must specify a unique address prex, or NULL if the
       communicator cannot establish outgoing connections (for example, because
       it is only acting as a TCP server).
       A communicator must tell TRANSPORT which addresses it is reachable under.
       Addresses may be added or removed at any time.
       A communicator may have zero addresses (transmission only).
       Addresses do not have to match the address prefix.
     </t>
     <t>
       TRANSPORT may ask a communicator to try to connect to another address.
       TRANSPORT will only ask for connections where the address matches the
       communicator’s address prefix that was provided when the connection was
       established.
       Communicators should then attempt to establish a connection.
       No response is provided to TRANSPORT service on failure.
       The TRANSPORT service has to ask the communicator explicitly to retry.
     </t>
     <t>
       If a communicator succeeds in establishing an outgoing connection for
       transmission, or if a communicator receives an incoming bi-directional
       connection, the communicator must inform the TRANSPORT service that a
       message queue (MQ) for transmission is now available.
       For that MQ, the communicator must provide the peer identity claimed by
       the other end.
       It must also provide a human-readable address (for debugging) and a
       maximum transfer unit (MTU).
       A MTU of zero means sending is not supported, SIZE_MAX should be used for
       no MTU. The communicator should also tell TRANSPORT what network type is
       used for the queue.
       The communicator may tell TRANSPORT anytime that the queue was deleted
       and is no longer available.
     </t>
     <t>
       The communicator API also provides for flow control.
       First, communicators exhibit backpressure on TRANSPORT:
       the number of messages TRANSPORT may add to a queue for transmission will
       be limited.
       So, by not draining the transmission queue, backpressure is provided to
       TRANSPORT.
       In the other direction, communicators may allow TRANSPORT to give
       backpressure towards the communicator by providing a non-NULL
       GNUNET_TRANSPORT_MessageCompletedCallback argument to the
       GNUNET_TRANSPORT_communicator_receive function.
       In this case, TRANSPORT will only invoke this function once it has
       processed the message and is ready to receive more.
       Communicators should then limit how much traffic they receive based on
       this backpressure.
       Note that communicators do not have to provide a
       GNUNET_TRANSPORT_MessageCompletedCallback;
       for example, UDP cannot support backpressure due to the nature of the
       UDP protocol.
       In this case, TRANSPORT will implement its own TRANSPORT-to-TRANSPORT
       flow control to reduce the sender’s data rate to acceptable levels.
     </t>
     <t>
       TRANSPORT may notify a communicator about backchannel messages TRANSPORT
       received from other peers for this communicator.
       Similarly, communicators can ask TRANSPORT to try to send a backchannel
       message to other communicators of other peers.
       The semantics of the backchannel message are up to the communicators
       who use them.
       TRANSPORT may fail to transmit backchannel messages, and TRANSPORT will
       not attempt to retransmit them.
     </t>
   </section>
   <section anchor="primitives" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>Cryptographic dependencies</name>
   <section anchor="elligator_dhkem" numbered="true" toc="default">
   <name>Elligator DHKEM</name>
      <t>
        GNUnet communicators utilize en Elligator KEM for the encoding and decoding
        the ephemeral public keys.
        While standard Diffie-Hellman-based KEMs securely establish a secret between
        two parties, an observer can easily identify the encapsulation as a public key.
        In the presence of an active attacker, this could lead to packet dropping based on this information,
        preventing communication between peers.
        The UDP and TCP communicators use the Elligator KEM defined in
        <xref target="LSD0011"/>.
        This leaves the attacker with the option to either do nothing or intercept all random-looking packets,
        thereby potentially disrupting a large part of today's internet communication.
      </t>
      <t>
        We use the KEMs and their notations as defined in <xref target="RFC9180"/> and
        <xref target="LSD0011"/>.
      </t>
   </section>
   <section anchor="key_derivation" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>Key derivation</name>
      <t>
        We use a hash-based key derivation function (HKDF) as defined in
        <xref target="RFC5869" />, using SHA-256 <xref target="RFC6234"/> for the extraction
        phase and SHA-256 <xref target="RFC6234"/> for the expansion phase.
        We derive the master secret as a uniform symmetric key
        from the X25519 result "Z" and the ephemeral public key "A" in a
        "HKDF-Extract" step and then derive context-specific keys through "HKDF-Expand" as needed.
        </t>
        <t>
        Peer IDs in GNUnet are Ed25519 public keys as defined <xref target="RFC8032"/>.
        In order to use such keys in our X25519-based KEMs (including the Elligator KEM), those
        keys must be converted to Curve25519 public keys, which is generally possible.
        </t>
   </section>
   </section>
  <section anchor="udp_comm" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>UDP communicator</name>
     <t>
   The UDP communicator implements an encryption layer that protects both the payload and the communicator's
   specific metadata (not to be confused with the UDP header). In particular, any message sent by the communicator
   is indistinguishable from random payload to an outside observer, with the exception of broadcast messages.
    </t>
    <t>
   For any new connection to a target peer, the communicator attempts to establish a shared secret using the
   KEM defined in <xref target="elligator_dhkem"/>.
   The communicator initiating the connection sends the resulting Elligator representative, the authentication tag
   and the encrypted data to the receiving peer.
   Since the GCM authentication tag and the encrypted data in the key exchange message also appear random,
   the entire message is computationally indistinguishable from a random byte stream.
   Independent of the payload, each message includes the sender's peer identity, a monotonic timestamp, and a
   signature over the session metadata.
   Receivers <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> keep track of the monotonic timestamps of key exchanges with each peer
   to prevent replay attacks.
   For each subsequent message the same procedure is used with a new encapsulation.
   While the communicator may always fall back to this type of encryption, it is inefficient for
   high-volume data transfer because a new key exchange is required for every message.
   However, sometimes we may have no other choice, for example, if there is only bi-directional connectivity
   to the receiving peer.
    </t>
    <t>
    If the target peer is able to acknowledge the reception of a message, the employed key can be reused.
    Such acknowledgments can be sent either via a bi-directional UDP connection or a backchannel connection provided
    by TRANSPORT.
    This acknowledgment prompts the communicator to offer a new queue to TRANSPORT, which has a higher priority
    than the default queue but starts with limited capacity.
    The capacity increases whenever the communicator receives an acknowledgment for a transmission.
    This queue is suitable for high-volume data transfer, and TRANSPORT will prioritize it if available.
    </t>
    <t>
   There are three distinct message types that are sent and received by UDP communicators: KX, BOX and BROADCAST.
   For KX and BOX messages, their metadata is chosen such that they are indistinguishable from random. This property
   does not hold for BROADCAST messages and is not necessary, as they are only sent within a local area network.
    </t>

    <section anchor="Key_exchange" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Key exchange</name>
       <t>
       Independent of the type of message queue, a key exchange is initiated at least once by the sending peer.
       In cases where the receiving peer cannot acknowledge the reception of messages, a key exchange is performed for every message.
       Two key pairs are needed for the KEM: An ephemeral key pair generated as part of the encapsulation procedure
       <tt>Encap(pkR) -> (MSK,enc)</tt> and the peer identity of the receiving communciator.
       The algorithm in use for the KEM is <tt>DHKEM(X25519+Elligator, HKDF-SHA256)</tt> <xref target="LSD0011"/>.
       The peer identity of the receiving communicator is an Ed25519 public key <tt>pkRed</tt>.
       In order to use it compliantly with a X25519-based DHKEM as defined in <xref target="LSD0011"/> and <xref target="RFC9180"/>, the
       curve point must first be converted from Edwards into its birationally equivalent Montgomery form
       <tt>pkR</tt>.
       The encapsulation <tt>enc</tt> is transferred via a key exchange (KX) message, as defined in <xref target="figure_udp_initialkx"/>.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figure_udp_initialkx" title="The binary representation of the KX message.">
       <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0           8           16          24    
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    ENC                        |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    GCM TAG                    |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/                 ENCRYPTED DATA                /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
         ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>ENC</dt>
         <dd>
           The 256-bit serialized encapsulation result <tt>enc</tt> of the KEM.
         </dd>
         <dt>GCM TAG</dt>
         <dd>
           The 128-bit GCM tag is used to authenticate the ciphertext immediately following the header part of the KX message.
         </dd>
         <dt>ENCRYPTED DATA</dt>
         <dd>
           The remaining data (as indicated by SIZE) is AES-GCM encrypted using the current session key and authenticated
           through the GCM TAG.
         </dd>
       </dl>
        <t>
         In order to prevent replay attacks for KX messages, the plaintext resulting from decryption of the encrypted data
         <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> must start with a session-specific Confirmation header as defined in <xref target="figure_udp_confirmation"/>.
         It includes the sender's peer identity and a monotonic timestamp, which the receiving peer <bcp14>MUST</bcp14>
         keep track of each peer identity to reject possible replay attacks.
       </t>
<figure anchor="figure_udp_confirmation" title="The binary representation of the KX Confirmation header">
       <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                                               |
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                                               |
|                 SIGNATURE                     |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP            |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/                PAYLOAD                        /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
         ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key (<tt>pkSed</tt>).
         </dd>
         <dt>SIGNATURE</dt>
         <dd>
           The EdDSA signature is computed with the peer private key
           over the session metadata, as detailed in <xref target="figure_udp_handshake_sig"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP</dt>
         <dd>
          A 64-bit value for the absolute time used by GNUnet, in microseconds and in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>PAYLOAD</dt>
         <dd>
           The message payload data.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
       The confirmation header also includes a signature over the session's metadata, which is signed with the corresponding private key of
       the sender's peer identity. The data format over which the signature is computed is defined in <xref target="figure_udp_handshake_sig"/>
       </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_udp_handshake_sig" title="The wire format of the data structure over which the signature of the UDP Confirmation header is computed.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |       PURPOSE (0x0X)  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 RECEIVER PEER ID              |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 ENC                           |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP            |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 32-bit value containing the length of the signed data in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>PURPOSE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 32-bit signature purpose flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 33. It defines the context in which
           the signature is created so that it cannot be reused in other parts
           of the protocol, including possible future extensions.
           The value of this field corresponds to an entry in the
           GANA "GNUnet Signature Purpose" registry <xref target="GANA"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key (<tt>pkSed</tt>).
         </dd>
         <dt>RECEIVER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key (<tt>pkRed</tt>).
         </dd>
         <dt>ENC</dt>
         <dd>
           The 256-bit serialized encapsulation result <tt>enc</tt> of the KEM.
         </dd>
         <dt>MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP</dt>
         <dd>
           A 64-bit value for the absolute time used by GNUnet, in microseconds and in network byte order.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
         Upon receiving a KX message, the receiving peer decapsulates the secret key <tt>MSK</tt> using
         <tt>MSK &lt;- Decap(skR,enc)</tt>, where <tt>skR</tt> is the X25519 private key derived from
         its Ed25519 counterpart <tt>skRed</tt>.
         This <tt>Decap(skR, enc)</tt> procedure is defined in <xref target="LSD0011"/>.
       Note that the exchange of the receiver peer identity is not within the scope of the UDP communicator's key
       exchange and is already assumed to be known to the sending peer.
       One way to exchange peer identities is through the UDP BROADCAST messages as described in
       <xref target="udp_bc"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
        The MSK is then used together with a sequence number SEQ to derive symmetric encryption key K and initialization
        vector IV using the "SetupCipher" procedure outlined below.
        Both the sending and the receiving peer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> store the master shared secret MSK and attribute
        it to the corresponding peer.
        <!-- FIXME SEQ is increased by ACKs! -->
        In case of an acknowledgment from the receiving peer, the established MSK can be reused by iteratively increasing
        the sequence number SEQ for SetupCipher(MSK, SEQ).
        </t>
         <t>
         Additional data might be inserted after the confirmation header as part of the encrypted data of the KX message.
         <!-- Wat? -->
         Padding may be necessary due to the use of AES-GCM.
         Once a KX message is received and validated, the peer <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> try to acknowledge the established
         MSK to switch to a stable session.
         The details about the acknowledgment process and subsequent message exchange can be found in
         <xref target="udp_message_exchange"/>.
         </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="udp_key_schedule" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Key schedule</name>
       <t>
       Once a shared secret MSK is established through the Elligator KEM, a symmetric key and
       initialization vector are derived.
       According to a key schedule from a 32-bit sequence number SEQ (in network byte order) and the MSK.
       The initial value of the sequence number is 0.
       </t>
       <artwork anchor="setup_cipher" name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
SetupCipher(MSK,SEQ):
  K := HKDF-Expand (MSK, "gnunet-communicator-udp-key"||SEQ, 32)
  IV := HKDF-Expand (MSK, "gnunet-communicator-udp-iv"||SEQ, 12)
  return K,IV
       ]]></artwork>
     <t>
       SetupCipher returns a 256-bit AES key "K" as well as a 96-bit "IV" for use in AES-GCM.
     </t>
       <t>
         Each derived key is uniquely identified using a separately derived
         256-bit key ID (KID) derived in a similar fashion:
       </t>
       <artwork anchor="derive_kid" name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
DeriveKID(MSK,SEQ):
  KID := HKDF-Expand (MSK, "gnunet-communicator-udp-kid"||SEQ, 32)
  return KID
  ]]></artwork>
       <t>
       The sequence number SEQ for any shared secret is initially 0 and incremented on the sender side for each 
       successive encryption and on the receiver side for each decryption.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="udp_message_exchange" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Message exchange</name>
       <t>
       KX messages, as presented in <xref target="Key_exchange"/>, are sufficient for transferring arbitrary amounts of data. This way of 
       communicating is slow due to the establishment of a shared secret for each message using asymmetric cryptography. The UDP communicator 
       offers a faster way of communicating by reusing a shared secret. For this purpose, the receiver of a message <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> 
       acknowledge the reception to signal the sender that the same shared secret can be reused. The sender can then use the acknowledged shared 
       secret and increment the utilized sequence number for each subsequent message to derive new symmetric key material. These messages are 
       sent as BOX messages, which incorporate a KID as defined in <xref target="derive_kid"/> to identify both the master shared secret and 
       sequence number. The wire format of a BOX message is depicted in <xref target="figure_udp_box"/>. 
       </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_udp_box" title="The binary representation of the UDP Box message.">
       <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0           8           16          24    
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                     KEY ID                    |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    GCM TAG                    |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
/                 ENCRYPTED DATA                /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
         ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>KEY ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit value containing the KID of the symmetric key to
           use for decryption as derived using DeriveKID as described in <xref target="derive_kid"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>GCM TAG</dt>
         <dd>
           A 128-bit GCM tag used to authenticate the ciphertext immediately following this TCP Box header.
         </dd>
         <dt>ENCRYPTED DATA</dt>
         <dd>
           The remaining data (as indicated by SIZE) is AES-GCM encrypted using the
           derived key and IV identified by the KID.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
       An acknowledgment can be sent in various ways is ultimately decided by TRANSPORT. If the target peer can also reach the sending peer via 
       UDP messages, both KX messages or BOX messages could be utilized to send the acknowledgment as their payload. TRANSPORT could also choose 
       to utilize another communicator type to send the acknowledgment (backchannel). Either way, acknowledgments are always sent in form of an 
       ACK header. The wire format of the ACK header can be seen in <xref target="figure_udp_ack"/>.
       </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_udp_ack" title="The wire format of an ACK header.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0                       16
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |       TYPE (0x0X)     |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SEQ ACK                       |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MSK HASH (fromerly CMAC)       |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit value containing the length of the message in bytes in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>TYPE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit signature type flag in network byte order. The value of this field MUST be 1460.
         </dd>
         <dt>SEQ ACK</dt>
         <dd>
           Sequence acknowledgment limit. Specifies the current maximum sequence number supported by the receiver.
         </dd>
         <dt>MSK HASH</dt>
         <dd>
           CMAC of the base key being acknowledged.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
       To avoid having to acknowledge every single message individually, the sender of an acknowledgment can specify the allowed sequence number for
       the sender in the ACK header. 
       The receiver <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> precalculate all derived keys and corresponding KIDs for which it has already sent ACKs. Consequently, for 
       valid sequence numbers below the current ACK limit, KID should match one of the precalculated keys in the key cache, and the encrypted data 
       can be decrypted. Otherwise, the message <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be rejected.
       </t>
       <t>
       Multiple shared secrets can be used simultaneously between the sending peer and target peer. Should the 
       sending peer use up all acknowledgments for all its shared secrets, messages are sent through KX messages again.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="udp_rekeying" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Rekeying</name>
       <t>
       The amount of data that can be encrypted with a shared secret <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be limited. Before
       the capacity of a shared secret is used up, the sender initiates rekeying by sending a new ephemeral public key
       for a key exchange. As multiple shared secrets can be used simultaneously, rekeying doesn't necessarily delete the old shared secret if its 
       capacity is not yet reached. The ephemeral public key is sent encrypted in a Rekey header as part of the payload of BOX message. Because the 
       ephemeral public key is encrypted, there is no need to use Elligator's encoding function and we use the normal, unobfuscated
       <tt>DHKEM(X25519, HKDF-SHA256)</tt>. The wire format of the Rekey header can 
       be seen in <xref target="figure_udp_rekey"/>.
       </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_udp_rekey" title="The wire format of a Rekey header.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0                       16
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |       TYPE (0x0X)     |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                     ENC                       |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
       <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit value containing the length of the message in bytes in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>TYPE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit signature type flag in network byte order. The value of this field MUST be 1462.
         </dd>
         <dt>ENC</dt>
         <dd>
           The 256-bit serialized encapsulation result <tt>enc</tt> of the KEM.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
       Additional data might be inserted after the Rekey header as part of the encrypted data of the BOX message. Padding 
       may be necessary due to the use of AES-GCM.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="udp_bc" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Broadcast</name>
       <t>
       BROADCAST messages are sent by peers to announce their presence. Those messages are only distributed in the LAN and sent in cleartext.
       </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_udp_broadcast" title="The binary representation of the udp BROADCAST message">
       <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                                               |
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                                               |
|                 SIGNATURE                     |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
         ]]></artwork>
     </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key (<tt>pkSed</tt>).
         </dd>
         <dt>SIGNATURE</dt>
         <dd>
           The EdDSA signature is computed with the announced peer private key
           over the peer identity and address hash, as depicted in <xref target="figure_udp_broadcast_sig"/>.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <figure anchor="figure_udp_broadcast_sig" title="The wire format of the data structure over which the signature of the UDP BROADCAST message is computed.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |       PURPOSE (0x0X)  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 ADDRESS HASH                  |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
        <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 32-bit value containing the length of the signed data in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>PURPOSE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 32-bit signature purpose flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 34. It defines the context in which
           the signature is created so that it cannot be reused in other parts
           of the protocol, including possible future extensions.
           The value of this field corresponds to an entry in the
           GANA "GNUnet Signature Purpose" registry <xref target="GANA"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key (<tt>pkSed</tt>).
         </dd>
         <dt>ADDRESS HASH</dt>
         <dd>
           Hash of the sender's UDP address.
         </dd>
       </dl>
     </section>
  </section>
   <section anchor="tcp_comm" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>TCP communicator</name>
     <t>
       TCP communicators always establish an encrypted and bi-directional communication channel. For 
       each direction of communication, a dedicated shared secret is used to both encrypt and 
       authenticate messages. These shared secrets are exchanged during the initial handshake. After a 
       certain amount of data has been transmitted, rekeying occurs to renew the key material. 
       Note that the rekeying process is triggered individually for each communication direction.
     </t>
     <t>
       To achieve a zero-plaintext design, we <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the mac-then-encrypt approach to 
       hide the message size on the wire. Extra caution needs to be taken due to the vulnerability of 
       the mac-then-encrypt design to padding oracle attacks. To mitigate this issue, the TCP communicator 
       uses AES-CTR for encryption, which does not require padding. Additionally, the use of ephemeral keys 
       combined with monotonic timestamps limits an attacker's ability to exploit the oracle, as replay 
       attacks are prevented.
     </t>
     <section anchor="tcp_handshake" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Handshake</name>
      <t>
      The main purpose of the handshake is to establish shared key material for each direction of the communication
      channel.
      The initiating TCP Communicator starts the handshake by sending an encapsulation from the Elligator KEM
      defined in <xref target="elligator_dhkem"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
      The encapsulation <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be directly followed by an encrypted TCP handshake message, as shown in
      <xref target="figure_tcp_handshake"/>.
      In addition to the peer identity of the sender and a timestamp, it contains a nonce as a challenge for the
      receiving TCP communicator.
      All data is authenticated with a signature.
      </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_tcp_handshake" title="The binary representation of the TCP handshake message.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SIGNATURE                     |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP            |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                     NONCE                     |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key (<tt>pkSed</tt>).
         </dd>
         <dt>SIGNATURE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 512-bit EdDSA signature. The signature is calculated over
           the data as defined in <xref target="figure_tcp_handshake_sig"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP</dt>
         <dd>
           A 64-bit value for the absolute time used by GNUnet, in microseconds and in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>NONCE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit random value used as a challenge to be signed in a TCP handshake acknowledgment message.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
       The data scheme used for computing the signature is depicted in <xref target="figure_tcp_handshake_sig"/>.
       </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_tcp_handshake_sig" title="The wire format used for creating the signature of the tcp handshake message.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |       PURPOSE (0x0X)  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 RECEIVER PEER ID              |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                REPRESENTATIVE                 |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP            |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                     NONCE                     |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 32-bit value containing the length of the signed data in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>PURPOSE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 32-bit signature purpose flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 31.  It defines the context in which
           the signature is created so that it cannot be reused in other parts
           of the protocol, including possible future extensions.
           The value of this field corresponds to an entry in the
           GANA "GNUnet Signature Purpose" registry <xref target="GANA"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key.
         </dd>
         <dt>RECEIVER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key.
         </dd>
         <dt>REPRESENTATIVE</dt>
         <dd>
           The 256-bit serialized encapsulation result of the KEM.
         </dd>
         <dt>MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP</dt>
         <dd>
           A 64-bit value for the absolute time used by GNUnet, in microseconds and in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>NONCE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit random value.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
         Upon reception of the ephemeral public key, the receiving TCP communicator carries out the decapsulation step of the
         key exchange and retrieves the shared key material. The subsequently received TCP handshake message is then decrypted and verified.
         If the signature is invalid, the connection is dropped.
         In the case of a valid signature, the receiving TCP communicator sends its own TCP handshake message to establish 
         shared key material for outgoing messages and also replies with an encrypted TCP handshake acknowledgment message as defined 
         in <xref target="figure_tcp_handshake_ack"/>. 
       </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_tcp_handshake_ack" title="The binary representation of the tcp handshake acknowledgment message.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0           8           16          24
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |        TYPE (0x0X)    |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 RECEIVER PEER ID              |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SIGNATURE                     |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP            |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                     NONCE                     | 
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit value containing the length of the message in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>TYPE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit signature type flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 1453.
         </dd>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key.
         </dd>
         <dt>RECEIVER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key.
         </dd>
         <dt>Signature</dt>
         <dd>
           A 512-bit EdDSA signature. The signature is calculated over
           the data as defined in <xref target="figure_tcp_handshake_ack_sig"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP</dt>
         <dd>
           A 64-bit value for the absolute time used by GNUnet, in microseconds and in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>NONCE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit random value.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
       The data scheme used for computing the signature for the acknowledgment message is depicted 
       in <xref target="figure_tcp_handshake_ack_sig"/>.
       </t>
       <figure anchor="figure_tcp_handshake_ack_sig" title="The wire format used for creating the signature of the tcp handshake acknowledgment message.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0           8           16          24
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |        TYPE (0x0X)    |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 RECEIVER PEER ID              |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP            |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                     NONCE                     | 
|                                               |
/                                               /
/                                               /
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit value containing the length of the message in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>TYPE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit signature type flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 39.
         </dd>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key.
         </dd>
         <dt>RECEIVER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key.
         </dd>
         <dt>MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP</dt>
         <dd>
           A 64-bit value for the absolute time used by GNUnet, in microseconds and in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>NONCE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit random value.
         </dd>
       </dl>
      <t>
       The initiating TCP communicator also replies with a TCP handshake acknowledgment message after receiving
       a valid TCP handshake message. Lastly, each party verifies both the signature and the challenge within the received
       TCP handshake acknowledgment message, thus completing the handshake.
     </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="tcp_KEM" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Key exchange</name>
      <t>
      During the initial handshake, each communication channel performs the Elligator KEM defined in
      <xref target="elligator_dhkem"/>.
      The resulting shared secret us used in an AES-CTR encryption with HMAC-SHA512.
      Subsequent key exchanges are performed with each rekeying.
      More about the initial handshake and rekeying can be found in <xref target="tcp_handshake"/> and
      <xref target="tcp_rekeying"/>, respectively.
      </t>
      <t>
      Let (REC_SK, REC_ID) be the receiver peer's EdDSA key pair.
      The sender peer initiates the key exchange using the Elligator KEM from <xref target="elligator_dhkem"/>
      resulting in an encapsulation and initial master secret key MSK.
      MSK is used to derive a symmetric encryption and HMAC key as well as an initialization vector using
      the procedure "SetupCipher":
    </t>
       <artwork anchor="setup_cipher_tcp" name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
SetupCipher(REC_ID, MSK):
  K := HKDF-Expand (MSK, "gnunet-communicator-tcp-key", 32)
  IV := HKDF-Expand (MSK, "gnunet-communicator-tcp-ctr, 16)
  K_mac := HKDF-Expand (MSK, "gnunet-communicator-tcp-hmac, 64)
  return K,IV,K_mac
  ]]></artwork>
       <t>
       Note that the initiating TCP communicator can immediately encrypt the first TCP handshake message when
       sending it.
       As soon as the receiving TCP communicator receives and decapsulates the representative, it can decrypt the
       following TCP handshake message.
       The same applies to the TCP handshake message sent by the receiving TCP communicator.
       </t>
     </section>
     <section anchor="tcp_message_exchange" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>Message exchange</name>
     <t>
     Once the handshake is completed, actual payloads can be exchanged bi-directionally using TCP BOX messages. A TCP Box message
     consists of a TCP BOX message, as defined in <xref target="figure_tcp_box"/>, followed by the payload. Both parts are encrypted
     before being sent to the receiving peer.
     </t>
     <t>
     TCP Box messages follow the mac-then-encrypt approach to hide the size of the payload and achieve a zero-plaintext design.
     The HMAC utilizes SHA512 as the underlying hash function and is ratcheted after each operation. Given the mac-then-encrypt
     approach, additional safeguards are needed to protect against Oracle padding attacks. Therefore, we <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use 
     a padding-free encryption scheme such as AES-CTR for encryption. Additionally, we restrict the attacker's ability to replay 
     attacks by exchanging new key material after a randomly chosen amount of transferred data, as described in 
     <xref target="tcp_rekeying"/>. The necessary key exchanges to establish the new key material are protected using monotonic 
     timestamps. 
     </t>
     <figure anchor="figure_tcp_box" title="The binary representation of the TCP BOX message.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0           8           16          24
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |        TYPE (0x0X)    |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    HASHCODE                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+

           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit value containing the length of the message in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>TYPE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit signature type flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 1451.
         </dd>
         <dt>HASHCODE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit HMAC-SHA512 hashcode for the subsequently sent payload.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       </section>
   
   <section anchor="tcp_rekeying" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>Rekeying</name>
     <t>
     After each key exchange, up to 400 MB of data is transferred until rekeying is triggered by the sender of the communication direction. 
     The actual amount of transferred data <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> be chosen randomly. If the chosen byte quantity is not reached after 
     one day, rekeying is set off anyway. 
     </t>
     <t>
     The receiving communicator is signaled about a rekeying through the dispatch of a TCP Rekey message, as defined in 
     <xref target="figure_tcp_rekey"/>. The message <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be encrypted with the current key. Due to the encryption of the message, 
     the encoding of the new ephemeral public key with Elligator is not needed. Similarly to the initial handshake, the ephemeral public key
     is used to perform a key exchange from which new key material for the encryption and authentication code scheme is derived. For further 
     details, please refer to <xref target="tcp_KEM"/>. Note that the rekeying process doesn't involve an acknowledgment by the receiver of
     a TCP Rekey message. So the sender might send new payload encrypted by the new key right after sending the TCP Rekey message. 
     </t>
     <figure anchor="figure_tcp_rekey" title="The binary representation of the TCP Rekey message.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0           8           16          24
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |        TYPE (0x0X)    |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                    HASHCODE                   |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                       ENC                     |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SIGNATURE                     |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP            |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit value containing the length of the message in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>TYPE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit signature type flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 1450.
         </dd>
         <dt>HASHCODE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit HMAC-SHA512 hashcode of this TCP Rekey message. The hashcode is 
           computed with the hashcode field initially set to zero and is inserted afterward.
         </dd>
         <dt>ENC</dt>
         <dd>
           The 256-bit serialized encapsulation result <tt>enc</tt> of the KEM.
         </dd>
         <dt>Signature</dt>
         <dd>
           A 512-bit EdDSA signature. The signature is calculated over
           the data as defined in <xref target="figure_tcp_rekey_sig"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP</dt>
         <dd>
           A 64-bit value for the absolute time used by GNUnet, in microseconds and in network byte order.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <figure anchor="figure_tcp_rekey_sig" title="The wire format used for creating the signature of the TCP Rekey message.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |       PURPOSE (0x0X)  |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 SENDER PEER ID                |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 RECEIVER PEER ID              |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                      ENC                      |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP            |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 32-bit value containing the length of the signed data in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt>PURPOSE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 32-bit signature purpose flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be 32.  It defines the context in which
           the signature is created so that it cannot be reused in other parts
           of the protocol, including possible future extensions.
           The value of this field corresponds to an entry in the
           GANA "GNUnet Signature Purpose" registry <xref target="GANA"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>SENDER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key (<tt>pkSed</tt>).
         </dd>
         <dt>RECEIVER PEER ID</dt>
         <dd>
           A 256-bit EdDSA public key (<tt>pkRed</tt>).
         </dd>
         <dt>ENC</dt>
         <dd>
           The 256-bit serialized encapsulation result <tt>enc</tt> of the KEM.
         </dd>
         <dt>MONOTONIC TIMESTAMP</dt>
         <dd>
           A 64-bit value for the absolute time used by GNUnet, in microseconds and in network byte order.
         </dd>
       </dl>
      </section>
     </section>
  <section anchor="http3_comm" numbered="true" toc="default">
  <name>HTTP/3 communicator</name>
  <t>
  The HTTP/3 <xref target="RFC9114"/> communicator operates over a bidirectional communication channel,
    with the client initiating the connection and the server on the receiving end.
    Once the connection is successfully established, messages are transmitted via POST and GET requests,
    and all communication is secured using TLS.
  </t>
  <t>
    Upon successfully establishing an HTTP/3 connection, the client <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> immediately transmit
    its <tt>PeerIdentity</tt> in a POST.
    The server will store this PeerIdentity to identify the client.
    Following this exchange, data exchange between the client and server can proceed.
    </t>
    <t>
      When the client needs to send a message, it uses a POST request to transmit the data to the server.
      While the server cannot initiate messages independently, it can include data in its response to a
      client's POST request.
    </t>
    <t>
      To enable the server to proactively send data when the client has no data to transmit,
      long polling is used.
      The client sends GET requests to the server, which <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> not immediately respond
      but instead sets a timer for each request.
      The server responds either when the timer expires or when there is data to send.
      Upon receiving a response, the client immediately sends a new GET request to maintain an adequate
      number of long polling requests with the server.
      </t>
      <figure anchor="figure_http3_msg" title="The wire format of exchanged messages.">
         <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|         SIZE          |         TYPE (0x0X)   |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|                 MESSAGE                       |
|                                               |
|                                               |
|                                               |
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
           ]]></artwork>
       </figure>
       <dl>
         <dt>SIZE</dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit value containing the length of the signed data in bytes
           in network byte order.
         </dd>
         <dt></dt>
         <dd>
           A 16-bit type flag in network byte order. The value of this
           field <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be XY.
           The value of this field corresponds to an entry in the
           GANA "GNUnet Message Type" registry <xref target="GANA"/>.
         </dd>
         <dt>MESSAGE</dt>
         <dd>
           The message.
         </dd>
       </dl>
       <t>
         Example POST:
       </t>
       <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
:method: POST
:scheme: https
:authority: PEER'S IP ADDRESS
:path: /
content-type: application/octet-stream
content-length: LENGTH OF MESSAGE
]]></artwork>
       <t>
         If server no data to send it will respond with HTTP status OK (200).
         If server has data to send it will respond with HTTP status OK and
         a response body with a message (<xref target="figure_http3_msg"/>) and
         content type  <tt>application/octet-stream</tt>
       </t>
       <t>
         GET request example (long polling):
       </t>
       <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
:method: GET
:scheme: https
:authority: PEER'S IP ADDRESS
:path: /
       ]]></artwork>
       <t>
         If server no data to send and the long poll times out it will
         respond with status 204.
         If server has data to send it will respond with HTTP status OK (200)
         a response body with a message (<xref target="figure_http3_msg"/>) and
         content type <tt>application/octet-stream</tt>.
       </t>
     <section anchor="http3_handshake" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Handshake</name>
       <t>
         The public keys in the certificates in use as part of the TLS handshake
         are not verified or evaluated against a trust store.
         The initial message by the initiating peer (the HTTP/3 client) will
         contain the peer identity.
         In the future, the peer identity should be part of the TLS handshake instead.
       </t>
     </section>
     </section>
  <section anchor="libp2p_comm" numbered="true" toc="default">
    <name>libp2p communicator</name>
    <t>
      The libp2p communicator uses libp2p as a means of communication.
      libp2p is "a modular networking framework bundled together as a full stack
      of protocols for peer-to-peer systems" and thus shares the general
      approach and a similar vision.
      The first goal would have been to integrate libp2p directly below core as
      an alternative/addition to the transport service as a first step of trying
      to get two different p2p networks and their implementations closer to each
      other. The long term goal would be to make the two networks compatible
      with each other and on the way learn from the respectively other network
      and apply the learnings to the respective on network.
      But it became soon clear that this was too ambitious for the short term
      and the short term goal was simplified to make libp2p a communicator for
      transport without loosing the perspective of integrating the two networks
      further in the future.
      Interesting insights include performance (in terms of throughput, memory
      consumption, cpu usage, ...), capabilities (NAT traversal, peer discovery,
      ...), different approaches to abstract similar underlying concepts, data
      structures employed and the usage of different schemes itself.
      If both networks would start to implement compatibilities to each other,
      both could profit from elements only the other has implemented.
    </t>
    <t>
      In order to address another peer and open a connecting, the libp2p
      multiaddress of the other peer or peer discovery is required. A libp2p
      multiaddress follows a very similar idea to a gnunet HELLO. Integrating
      the one with the other or finding a common abstraction would make a lot of
      sense in the mid to long term. For a libp2p communicator the easiest is to
      integrate a libp2p multiaddress just as one of the underlying
      transport/communicator addresses.
      The documentation of the libp2p multiaddress can be found here:
      https://docs.rs/libp2p/latest/libp2p/struct.Multiaddr.html
    </t>
    <t>
      One of the first consideration, when connecting the two networks, is the
      language. libp2p has implementations in many languages which all have
      different capabilities. (An overview is provided at
      https://libp2p.io/implementations.)
      In order to decide on the implementation mainly two factors have to be
      considered: Which features are needed and how difficult is the technical
      connection of the implementation? Depending on the implementation
      different wrappers and converters have to be implemented before being able
      to use them.
    </t>
    <t>
      Gnunet HELLO and libp2p multiaddress: The basic element to connect two
      gnunet peers via their libp2p communicators would be to exchange their
      libp2p multiaddress as part of a gnunet HELLO. Both represent a collection
      of different, underlying protocols, the respective implementations
      communicate over. Due to the similarity in representation, an adaption is
      needed to either (a) properly embed the one in the other without parsing
      issues, or (b) being able to directly parse both.
      <!-- seems not to be parsed and displayed on the web representation:
      For a better understanding, here is an exemplary libp2p multiaddress:
      <artwork anchor="libp2p multiaddress" name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
/ip4/198.51.100/tcp/1234/p2p/QmYyQSo1c1Ym7orWxLYvCrM2EmxFTANf8wXmmE7DWjhx5N
      ]]></artwork>
      ... and an exemplary printable (shortened and obfuscated) representaiton
      of a gnunet HELLO:
      <artwork anchor="gnunet HELLO" name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        gnunet://hello/HFXP<...>Y0/WDV0<...>WE20/1754<...>40?udp=%5Bfe80%3A%3Ad284%3A<...>3A2086&udp=%5B2003%3Acb%3A<...>%5D%3A2086<...>&tcp=%5Bfe80%3A%3A<...>%5D%3A2086&tcp=192.168.2.135%3A2086
      ]]></artwork>
      -->
      For the specification of libp2p multiaddresses see https://github.com/libp2p/specs/tree/master/addressing
      For just connecting two gnunet nodes via libp2p communicators, the main
      adaption needed is the compatibility between addressing schemes, as gnunet
      internally processes (signs with its peer id) the underlying addresses in
      order to exchange them via its bootstap system.
    </t>
    <t>
      Peer IDs: While gnunet only uses a single cryptographic primitive (EdDSA
      curve Ed25519) keys, libp2p has the option of using different keys. While
      not necessary if the connection is only as a communicator below transport,
      there might be the possibility of a direct compatibility at this level.
      (Probably a conversion in encoding/representation has still to be done.)
      The difference being that libp2p peer ids are stable, gnunet peer ids can
      change.
      For more see the libp2p spec on peer-ids:
      https://github.com/libp2p/specs/blob/master/peer-ids/peer-ids.md
    </t>
    <t>
      DHT: The Distributed Hash Tables of both networks are a bit different and
      as such not directly compatible. libp2p implements Kademlia
      (https://github.com/libp2p/specs/tree/master/kad-dht), whereas
      gnunet implements R5N
      (https://docs.gnunet.org/latest/users/subsystems.html#dht-distributed-hash-table).
    </t>
  </section>
   <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
   <name>Security and Privacy Considerations</name>
     <section anchor="security_kem" numbered="true" toc="default">
     <name>Ed25519 KEM</name>
       <t>
        Communicators use a modified version of the standard X25519 key exchange described in
        section 6.1 of <xref target="RFC7748"/>.
        It deviates in that we use the Ed25519 key pair "x","X = x*G" of the peer identity as X25519 scalars
        and curve points, respectively.
        The safety of this use of a KEM has been investigated by <xref target="T21"/>.
        </t>
     </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="work_in_progress" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>Work in Progress</name>
       <t>
       TRANSPORT API: GNUNET_TRANSPORT_MessageCompletedCallback, GNUNET_TRANSPORT_communicator_receive, and 
       GNUNET_TRANSPORT_MessageCompletedCallback should follow a generic API for all communicator types. 
       </t>
       <t>
       UDP Communicator: RTT (Round-Trip Time) measurement is missing. Values such as the number of shared secrets could be adapted based on the RTT.
       </t>
       <t>
       TCP Communicator: Currently, the only sanity check for a valid TCP handshake message is the verification of the signature. Additional checks, such as 
       verifying the sender's peer identity, are needed. 
       The use of the mac-then-encrypt approach within the TCP BOX messages should be analyzed further, specifically regarding padding-oracle attacks.
       </t>
    </section>
   <!--  <section anchor="gana" numbered="true" toc="default">
       <name>GANA Considerations</name>
    </section>-->
     <!-- gana -->
    <!--<section>
       <name>IANA Considerations</name>
 </section>-->
       <!-- <section>
       <name>Implementation and Deployment Status</name>
       <t>
         FIXME
       </t>
     </section>
     <section>
        <name>Acknowledgements</name>
        <t>
          FIXME
        </t>
        </section>-->
   </middle>
   <back>
     <references>
       <name>Normative References</name>
         &RFC2119;
         &RFC5869;
         &RFC6234;
         &RFC7748;
         &RFC8032;
         &RFC8174;
         &RFC9114;
         &RFC9180;

     </references>
     <references>
       <name>Informative References</name>
       <reference anchor="T21" target="https://eprint.iacr.org/2021/509.pdf">
       <front>
         <title>On using the same key pair for Ed25519 and an X25519 based KEM</title>
         <author initials="E." surname="Thormaker"
                 fullname="Erik Thormarker">
         </author>
         <date month="April" year="2021" />
     </front>
  </reference>
  <reference anchor="LSD0011" target="https://lsd.gnunet.org/lsd0011">
       <front>
         <title>The GNUnet communicators</title>
         <author initials="M" surname="Schanzenbach"
                 fullname="Martin Schanzenbach">
         </author>
         <author initials="P." surname="Fardzadeh"
                 fullname="Pedram Fardzadeh">
         </author>
         <date month="July" year="2024" />
     </front>
  </reference>
  <reference anchor="GANA" target="https://gana.gnunet.org">
       <front>
         <title>The GNUnet communicators</title>
         <author fullname="GNUnet e.V.">
         </author>
         <date month="July" year="2024" />
     </front>
  </reference>     </references>
   
 
 </back>
</rfc>
