<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3986 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5234 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- SEE ALSO: https://docs.taler.net/core/taler-uri.html -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-grothoff-taler-01"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="The 'taler' URI scheme">
      The 'taler' URI scheme for GNU Taler Wallet interactions
    </title>

    <author fullname="Christian Grothoff" initials="C.G." surname="Grothoff">
      <organization>BFH</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>H&ouml;heweg 80</street>
          <street></street>
          <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
	      <code>CH-2501</code>
          <country>CH</country>
        </postal>
        <email>christian.grothoff@bfh.ch</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Florian Dold" initials="F.D." surname="Dold">
      <organization>Taler Systems SA</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>7, rue de Mondorf</street>
          <city>Erpeldange</city>
          <code>L-5421</code>
          <country>LU</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dold@taler.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="07" month="January" year="2024" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>Independent Stream</workgroup>
    <keyword>payments</keyword>

    <abstract>

      <t>
        This document defines the 'taler' Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) scheme
        for triggering interactions with a GNU Taler wallet.
      </t>

      <t>
        This URI scheme allows applications to trigger interactions with the GNU Taler wallet,
        such as withdrawing money, making payments, receiving refunds and restoring a wallet
        from a backup.  Applications may receive such URIs in many ways (including via NFC,
        QR codes, Web links or messaging applications), or might generate them internally to
        interact with a wallet.  By having a Taler wallet handle the respective URIs,
        applications can integrate Taler payments without having to support the Taler protocol
        directly. Furthermore, by passing control to a Taler wallet process, the wallet's
        database with its financial data might be better protected from application failures.
      </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>
  This document defines the 'taler' Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) <xref target="RFC3986" /> scheme
  for triggering interactions with GNU Taler wallets.
</t>

<section title="Objective">
<t>
  A 'taler' URI always instructs a GNU Taler wallet to perform a particular operation.
  A 'taler' URI consists of an action and optional parameters.
</t>
<t>
  The interpretation of the optional parameters depends on the action.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Requirements Language">
<t>
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
   "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14
   <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when,
   they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section anchor="syntax"
  title="Syntax of a 'taler' URI">
  <t>
  This document uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) of <xref target="RFC5234"/>.
  </t>
  <figure>
  <artwork type="abnf"><![CDATA[
  taler-URI = ("taler://" / "TALER://" / "taler+http://" / "TALER+HTTP://" )
              action path-abempty [ "?" query ]
  action = ALPHA *( ALPHA / DIGIT / "-" / "." )
]]>
  </artwork>
  </figure>
  <t>
    'path-abempty' is defined in <xref target="RFC3986" /> in Section 3.3.
    'query' is defined in <xref target="RFC3986" />, in Section 3.4.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="semantics" title="Semantics">
<t>
  The action of a Taler URI identifies the operation requested from the Taler
  wallet.  Actions are not case-sensitive.  The actions are defined in the "Taler
  URI Actions" sub-registry, see <xref target="taler-registry" />.

  The path component of the URI typically provides a network address needed to
  locate additional information or services relevant to the requested operation.
  Paths are case-sensitive, but may contain case-insensitive portions, such
  as domain names.

  The query component of the URI provides immediate additional parameters or
  options for the operation.  The query is case-sensitive.

  The default operation of applications that invoke a URI with the taler
  scheme MUST be to launch a Taler wallet (if available).  If no taler URI
  handler is available, an application SHOULD show a QR code with the contents
  of the URI.  If multiple Taler wallets are registered, the user SHOULD be
  able to choose which application to launch.  This allows users with multiple
  wallets (each possibly with its own money) to choose which wallet to perform
  the operation with.

  An application SHOULD allow dereferencing a "taler://" URI even
  if the action of that URI is not registered in the "Taler URI Actions" sub-registry.

  Wallets seeing a "taler://" URI MUST use HTTP over TLS when talking
  to the respective network service.
  Wallets seeing a "taler+http://" URI MUST use HTTP without TLS when talking
  to the respective network service.  Wallets SHOULD support
  "taler+http://"-URIs only when run in developer or debug mode.

</t>
</section>

<section anchor="examples" title="Examples">
<figure>
  <artwork><![CDATA[
  taler://pay/example.com/2022.268-03G33PTAY2C6T/\
    00f68430-363a-46b7-8e33-241a0e49c430?c=KKBWMSTF4AZSP8XS0FFNE9KM5M
  taler://pay-push/bank.example.com/\
    3BBW6N8PVDYBRT0DERT8YYARQGFYHVQFG3WVAN1D58FRP5JG3M4G
  TALER://PAY-PULL/BANK.EXAMPLE.COM/\
    WB361HXN7BZ9ND1B9YP1Y20NB4H5WS0RNM4K8AFZ5Q2VRW577BPG
]]>
  </artwork>
</figure>

</section>

<section anchor="tracking" title="Tracking Taler URI Actions">
  <t>
    A registry of Taler URI Actions is described in <xref target="taler-registry" />.

    The registration policy for this registry is "Expert Review",
    as described in <xref target="RFC8126" />.
When requesting new entries, careful consideration of the following criteria is strongly advised:
<list style="numbers">
  <t>The description clearly defines the semantics of the action and optional parameters if applicable.</t>
  <t>The name states the unique name for the action that must be part of the URI.</t>
  <t>The syntax defines the format of the action-specific part of the URI.</t>
  <t>Relevant references are provided if they are available.</t>
  <t>The chosen name is appropriate for the operation, and avoids potential to confuse users.</t>
  <t>A libre software reference implementation is available.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Documents that support requests for new registry entries should
 provide the following information for each entry:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Description: A description of the action, including
   the semantics of the path in the URI if applicable.</t>
<t>Name: The name of the Taler URI action (case insensitive ASCII string, restricted to alphanumeric characters,
dots and dashes)</t>
<t>Syntax: summary of the syntax of the URI as a one-liner.</t>
<t>Example: At least one example URI to illustrate the action.</t>
<t>Contact: The contact information of a person to contact for further information</t>
<t>References: Optionally, references describing the action (such as an RFC) and target-specific options.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
This document populates the registry with $COUNT entries as follows (see
also <xref target="taler-registry" />).
</t>

<section anchor="registry-entry-withdraw" title="Action: withdraw">
<t>
  The action "withdraw" is used to trigger a bank-integrated withdrawal operation.
  This means that the user has been interacting with some online banking App and
  wants to instruct the bank to transfer money from the user's bank account into
  a the GNU Taler wallet.  The wallet now needs to allow the user to select the
  GNU Taler exchange, and then ultimately provide the bank with its
  reserve public key and await the completion of the wire transfer.
</t>
<t>
  The specific arguments of a "withdraw" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>bank_host: hostname of the bank (optionally including a port number)</t>
    <t>bank_prefix_path: list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the bank integration API base URL</t>
    <t>withdrawal_uid: the unique ID of the withdrawal operation</t>
    <t>ext (optional): when set to "1", the wallet does not show a confirmation link to the user.
    Useful when the withdrawal is initiated from an account that is not controlled by the same
    user as the user of the wallet.</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: withdraw</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://withdraw/{bank_host}{/bank_prefix_path*}/{withdrawal_uid}{?external-confirmation=ext}</t>
<t>Example: taler://withdraw/bank.example.com/wid</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="registry-entry-pay" title="Action: pay">
<t>
  Payments are requested with the "pay" action.
  The parameters are a hierarchical identifier for the requested payment,
  and must include a hostname, order ID and session ID (which may be
  an empty string). Additionally, a claim token and a prefix path to be used
  as part of the HTTP REST API request to the hostname may be specified.
</t>
<t>
  The specific arguments of a "pay" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
   <t>merchant_host: hostname of the GNU Taler REST service of merchant (may optionally include a port number)</t>
   <t>merchant_prefix_path: list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the merchant base URL</t>
   <t>order_id: the order ID that the customer is asked to pay for</t>
   <t>session_id:  the session ID under which the payment takes place</t>
   <t>ct: a high-entropy order "ClaimToken"</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: pay</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://pay/{merchant_host}{/merchant_prefix_path*}/{order_id}/{session_id}{?c=ct}</t>
<t>Example: taler://pay/merchant.example.com/42/</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="registry-entry-refund" title="Action: refund">
  <t>
    A "refund" action instructs the wallet to download information about
    an available refund. Wallet SHOULD consult the user about the refund and
    then obtain the refund for an already paid order.
  </t>
  <t>
  The specific arguments of a "refund" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>merchant_host: hostname of the merchant (possibly including a port number)</t>
    <t>merchant_prefix_path: list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the merchant base URL</t>
    <t>order_id: the order ID to check for refunds</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: refund</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://refund/{merchant_host}{/merchant_prefix_path*}/{order_id}/</t>
<t>Example: taler://refund/shop.example.com/42/</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="registry-entry-pay-push" title="Action: pay-push">
  <t>
    A pay-push URI instructs the wallet to ask the user about accepting a P2P
    payment. The wallet should download, decrypt and display the underlying
    contract and accept the offered money if the user agrees to the contract.
  </t>
  <t>
  The specific arguments of a "pay-push" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>exchange_host: the hostname of the exchange (possibly including a port number)</t>
    <t>exchange_prefix_path: list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the exchange base URL</t>
    <t>merge_priv: private key that grants the capability to take the money in the purse</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: pay-push</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://pay-push/{exchange_host}{/exchange_prefix_path*}/{merge_priv}</t>
<t>Example: taler://pay-push/exchange.example.com/KAMRGDM8FNQ82HSBVDEH8MCAF13Q0B51P4R35RFG2CBVHKGT321G</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="registry-entry-pay-pull" title="Action: pay-pull">
  <t>
    A pay-pull URI instructs the wallet about a request made to the user to
    pay an invoice (or to simply send money to another wallet).  The wallet
    should download, decrypt and display the underlying contract and ask the
    user if they agree to pay the invoice.
  </t>
<t>
  The specific arguments of a "pay-pull" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>exchange_host: the hostname of the exchange (possibly including a port number)</t>
    <t>exchange_prefix_path: list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the exchange base URL</t>
    <t>contract_priv: the private key of the peer push payment contract stored at the exchange</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: pay-pull</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://pay-pull/{exchange_host}{/exchange_prefix_path*}/{contract_priv}</t>
<t>Example: taler://pay-pull/exchange.example.com/PN3W8SN6N8V1V5MTEZRPJJ2ANY8GGZMB1MBXC7NMSRXJN6MZ5SWG</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>


<section anchor="registry-entry-pay-template" title="Action: pay-template">
 <t>
   A "pay-template" action instructs the wallet to ask its user to
   manually complete an order template and submit the information
   to the merchant to obtain a "pay" request.  Wallets MUST fetch
   meta data about the template from the merchant to determine which
   information to request from the user.
 </t>
 <t>
   Wallets MAY support users entering all possible fields of a
   contract if allowed by the template.  Fields that MUST be supported
   at this time are the "amount" and the "summary".  The wallet
   MUST validate that the amount entered by the user is well-formed.
   For the amount, it is possible that the template restricts
   the currency in which case the wallet MUST only allow the user to
   enter an amount in that currency.  If the amount entered by the
   user exceeds the wallet balance, the wallet SHOULD NOT allow the
   user to submit the action.
 </t>
 <t>
   The specific arguments of a "pay-template" action is:
   <list style="symbols">
     <t>merchant_host: hostname of the merchant</t>
     <t>merchant_prefix_path: list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the merchant base URL</t>
     <t>template_id: identifier that uniquely identifies the template</t>
   </list>
 </t>
<t>
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>Name: pay-template</t>
    <t>Syntax: taler://pay-template/{merchant_host}{/merchant_prefix_path*}/{template_id}</t>
    <t>Example: taler://pay-template/merchant.example.com/lunch</t>
    <t>Contact: N/A</t>
    <t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
  </list>
</t>
</section>


<section anchor="registry-entry-restore" title="Action: restore">
<t>
  A "restore" action instructs the wallet to restore a wallet backup
  and merge it into its current state.
</t>
<t>
  The specific arguments of a "restore" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>sync_rootkey: Root sync key of the wallet, used to derive the symmetric key to encrypt the backup with individual providers.</t>
    <t>sync_provider_list: Comma-separated list of provider http or https URLs.  If no scheme part is specified, https is assumed. Each URL is URI-encoded for all characters except "A-Z a-z 0-9 - _ . ! ~ * ' ( )" (matching the HTML5 encodeURIComponent).</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: restore</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://restore/{sync_rootkey}/{sync_provider_list}</t>
<t>Example: taler://restore/backup.example.com/GJKG23V4ZBHEH45YRK7TWQE8ZTY7JWTY5094TQJSRZN5DSDBX8E0/prov1.example.com,prov2.example.com</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="registry-entry-dev-experiment" title="Action: dev-experiment">
<t>
  An "dev-experiment" action instructs the wallet to simulate a particular
  error scenario.  This action can be used to test the user interface.
  Wallets that are not in developer mode should not run
  the specified action and instead inform the user that "dev-experiment"
  actions are only supported in developer mode.
</t>
<t>
  The specific arguments of a "dev-experiment" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>name: specifies the specific type of dev experiment</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: dev-experiment</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://dev-experiment/{name}</t>
<t>Example: taler://dev-experiment/xxx</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="registry-entry-add-exchange" title="Action: add-exchange">
 <t>
   An "add-exchange" action instructs the wallet to add an exchange to its list of
   exchanges, download its meta data ("/config"), check that it is compatible with
   the wallet, and if it is a new exchange, ask the user to agree to the
   terms of service of the exchange.  If the user agrees to the terms,
   the currency of the exchange should be added to the list of currencies.
 </t>
 <t>
  The specific arguments of an "add-exchange" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>exchange_host: hostname of the exchange (possibly including a port number)</t>
    <t>exchange_prefix_path (optional): list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the exchange base URL</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: add-exchange</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://add-exchange/{exchange_host}{/exchange_prefix_path*}/</t>
<t>Example: taler://add-exchange/exchange.example.com/</t>
<t>Example: taler://add-exchange/exchanges.example.com/api/</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>


<section anchor="registry-entry-withdraw-exchange" title="Action: withdraw-exchange">
 <t>
  A "withdraw-exchange" action instructs the wallet to display a prompt to the user, asking
  the user to confirm/decline withdrawing from the exchange. The amount to be withdraw MAY be
  specified in the URI with the "amount" parameter and this SHOULD be used as suggested input
  for the withdraw. The user MUST accept the ToS and select the correct amount before starting
  the withdrawal.
 </t>
<t>
  The specific arguments of a "withdraw-exchange" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>exchange_host: hostname of the exchange (possibly including a port number)</t>
    <t>exchange_prefix_path (optional): list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the exchange base URL</t>
    <t>amount_value (optional): default value to use for the withdrawal amount, currency included</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: withdraw-exchange</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://withdraw-exchange/{exchange_host}{/exchange_prefix_path*}/{?a=amount_value]}</t>
<t>Example: taler://withdraw-exchange/exchange.example.com/?a=KUDOS:10</t>
<t>Example: taler://withdraw-exchange/exchanges.example.com/exchange1/</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="registry-entry-add-contact" title="Action: add-contact">
 <t>
   An "add-contact" action instructs the wallet to add a contact to its list of
   contacts.
 </t>
 <t>
  The specific arguments of an "add-contact" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>alias_type: the type of alias of this contact</t>
    <t>alias: the alias of a contact</t>
    <t>mailbox_host: hostname of the mailbox of the contact (possibly including a port number)</t>
    <t>mailbox_prefix_path (optional): list of path components that identifies the path prefix of the mailbox base URL</t>
    <t>mailbox_address: the contacts mailbox address.</t>
    <t>source_base_url (optional): the source of this contact information (taler directory service base URL). Optional.</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: add-contact</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://add-contact/{alias_type}/{alias}/{mailbox_host}{/mailbox_prefix_path*}/{mailbox_address}{?sourceBaseUrl=source_base_url}</t>
<t>Example: taler://add-contact/email/taler@example.com/mailbox.example.com/SOMEADDRESS/?sourceBaseUrl=https://taldir.example.com</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>


<section anchor="registry-entry-withdrawal-transfer-result" title="Action: withdrawal-transfer-result">
 <t>
   A "withdrawal-transfer-result" action instructs the wallet to display the status of a withdrawal
   to the user.  Typically used to transfer control between a banking app/website and a Taler wallet.
   Optionally, the URI can also specify an update to the status of the transfer
   to the exchange for the withdrawal as a hint for the wallet.  The wallet must only use this
   value to show further hints to the user.
 </t>
<t>
  The specific arguments of a "withdraw-exchange" action are:
  <list style="symbols">
    <t>ref_value: A reference for the transaction that must contain the reserve public key. Used to identify the
    withdrawal transaction in the wallet.</t>
    <t>status_value (optional): The status of the transfer, must be one of: "success", "aborted".</t>
  </list>
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name: withdraw-transfer-result</t>
<t>Syntax: taler://withdrawal-transfer-result{?ref=ref_value}{?status=status_value}</t>
<t>Contact: N/A</t>
<t>References: [this.I-D]</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>


</section><!-- tracking -->

<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
  Interactive applications handling the taler URI scheme MUST NOT initiate any
  unsafe payment operations prior review and confirmation from the user,
  and MUST take measures to prevent clickjacking <xref target="HMW12"/>.
</t>
<t>
  The authentication/authorization mechanisms and transport security services
  used to process a payment encoded in a taler URI
  are handled by the application and are not in scope of this document.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>
IANA maintains a registry called the "Uniform Resource Identifier
(URI) Schemes" registry.
</t>

<section anchor="taler-uri" title="URI Scheme Registration">
<t>
  IANA maintains the "Uniform Resource Identifier (URI) Schemes"
  registry that contains an entry for the 'taler' URI scheme.  IANA is
  requested to update that entry to reference this document when
  published as an RFC.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="taler-registry" title="Taler URI Actions">
<t>
   This document specifies a list of Taler URI Actions.  It is
   possible that future work will need to specify additional
   actions.  The GNUnet Assigned Numbers Authority (GANA) <xref target="GANA" />
   operates the "taler-uri-actions" registry to track
   the following information for each payment target type:
<list style="symbols">
<t>Name:  The name of the action (case insensitive ASCII string, restricted to alphanumeric characters,
dots and dashes)</t>
<t>Contact: The contact information of a person to contact for further information</t>
<t>References: Optionally, references describing the payment target type (such as an RFC) and target-specific options,
  or references describing the payment system underlying the payment target type.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
  The entries that have been made for the "taler-uri-actions"
  defined in this document are as follows:
</t>
<figure>
  <artwork>
    Name                       | Contact                 | Reference
    ----------------------------+-------------------------+----------
    pay                        | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    withdraw                   | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    refund                     | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    pay-pull                   | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    pay-push                   | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    pay-template               | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    restore                    | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    dev-experiment             | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    add-exchange               | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    add-contact                | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    withdraw-exchange          | N/A                     | [This.I-D]
    withdrawal-transfer-result | N/A                     | [This-I.D]
  </artwork>
</figure>

</section><!-- taler-registry -->

</middle>

<back>

  <references title="Normative References">

    &RFC2119;

    &RFC3986;

    &RFC5234;

    &RFC8126;

    &RFC8174;


  </references>

  <references title="Informational References">

   <reference anchor="HMW12" target="https://www.usenix.org/system/files/conference/usenixsecurity12/sec12-final39.pdf">
     <front>
         <title>Clickjacking: Attacks and Defenses</title>
         <author initials="L.S." surname="Huang"
                 fullname="Lin-Shung Huang">
         </author>
         <author initials="A." surname="Moshchuk"
                 fullname="Alexander, Moshchuk">
         </author>
         <author initials="H.J." surname="Wang"
                 fullname="Helen J. Wang">
         </author>
         <author initials="S." surname="Schecter"
                 fullname="Stuart Schecter">
         </author>
         <author initials="C." surname="Jackson"
                 fullname="Collin Jackson">
         </author>

         <date month="January" year="2012" />
     </front>
  </reference>

 <reference anchor="GANA" target="https://gana.gnunet.org/">
   <front>
       <title>GNUnet Assigned Numbers Authority (GANA)</title>
      <author><organization>GNUnet e.V.</organization>
      </author>
       <date month="April" year="2020" />
   </front>
 </reference>

  </references>

<!-- Change Log
v00 2022-11-11  CG   Initial version
  -->
</back>
</rfc>
