<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj "&#8288;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="info"
  docName="draft-nadler-sbox-1"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates=""
  sortRefs="false"
  submissionType="independent"
  symRefs="true"
  tocDepth="3"
  tocInclude="true"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.26.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="The GNS SBOX Record Type">The GNS SBOX Record Type</title>
    <seriesInfo name="LSD" value="0008" />
    <author fullname="Sebastian Nadler" initials="S." surname="Nadler">
      <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
      <address>
        <email>sebastian.nadler@tum.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Martin Schanzenbach" initials="M." surname="Schanzenbach">
      <organization>Fraunhofer AISEC</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Lichtenbergstrasse 11</street>
          <city>Garching</city>
          <code>85748</code>
          <country>Germany</country>
        </postal>
        <email>martin.schanzenbach@aisec.fraunhofer.de</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <workgroup>GNUnet</workgroup>
    <keyword>name systems</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t> This document provides an extension to the GNU Name System (GNS) technical specification <xref
          target="RFC9498" />. GNS is a decentralized and censorship-resistant domain name
        resolution protocol that provides a privacy-enhancing alternative to the Domain Name System
        (DNS) protocols. </t>
      <t>
        This document defines the normative wire format of an additional resource record
        and a modified resolution processes for use by implementers.
      </t>
      <t>
        This specification was developed outside the IETF and does not have
        IETF consensus. It is published here to inform readers about the
        function of GNS, guide future GNS implementations, and ensure
        interoperability among implementations (for example, pre-existing
        GNUnet implementations).
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t> This specification describes additions to the GNU Name System (GNS) <xref target="RFC9498" />,
        a censorship-resistant, privacy-preserving, and decentralized domain name resolution
        protocol. GNS cryptographically secures the binding of names to arbitrary tokens, enabling
        it to double in some respects as an alternative to some of today's public key
        infrastructures. </t>
      <t>
        This LSD document is an extension to the GNS technical specification <xref target="RFC9498" />.
        It is intended to be read in conjunction with the GNS technical specification. 
      </t>
      <t>
        A new record type is defined to extend the GNS to support a wider range of underscore labels.
        The new record type is called SBOX and is intended to handle all variations of underscore labels the BOX record type is not able to.
      </t>
      <t>
        This document defines the normative wire format of the SBOX resource
        record and resolution processes for use by implementers.
      </t>
      <section>
        <name>Requirements Notation</name>
        <t>The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>",
          "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD
          NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>",
          and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as described in
          BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119" /> <xref target="RFC8174" /> when, and only when, they
          appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>Terminology</name>
      <t>The terminology defined in <xref target="RFC9498" /> also applies to this document.</t>
      <t>This document includes the following additional terms:</t>
      <dl>
      <dt>Underscore label:</dt>
      <dd>
        A label is considered an underscore label only if it begins with an underscore. (e.g., "_name")
      </dd>
      <dt>Underscore prefix:</dt>
        <dd>
          The underscore prefix contains the rightmost underscore label and all subsequent labels to its left.
          For example, the underscore prefix of "_service._proto.example.gns.alt" is "_service._proto" and 
          the underscore prefix of "c93f1e400.abcd._info.example.gns.alt" is "c93f1e400.abcd._info".
       </dd>
      </dl>
    </section>
    <section anchor="rrecords">
      <name>Resource Records</name>
      <section anchor="gnsrecords_other">
        <name>Auxiliary Records</name>
        <t> This section defines an additional auxiliary GNS record type. Any implementation <bcp14>
          SHOULD</bcp14> be able to process the specified record types according to <xref
            target="record_processing" />. </t>
        <section anchor="gnsrecords_sbox">
          <name>SBOX</name>
          <t>
            GNS lookups are expected to return all of the required useful
            information in one record set. This avoids unnecessary additional
            lookups and cryptographically ties together information that belongs
            together, making it impossible for an adversarial storage entity to provide
            partial answers that might omit information critical for security.
          </t>
          <t>
            This general strategy is incompatible with the
            special labels used by DNS for SRV and TLSA records. Thus, GNS
            defines the BOX record format to box up SRV and TLSA records and
            include them in the record set of the label they are associated
            with.</t>
          <t>This way of handling and storing restricts the allowed and processable underscore
            prefixes to the format of "_SERVICE._PROTOCOL" as well as only services registered in
            the corresponding IANA registry. A new SBOX record is proposed to enable the use of labels
            such as "c93f1e400f26708f98cb19d936620da35eec8f72e57f9eec01c1afd6._smimecert" and other variations of 
            underscore prefixes for SMIMEA/URI/SRV, and other records. The SBOX
            record is supposed to handle all variations of underscore prefixes. The idea
            is to store the string representation of the underscore prefix instead of the service and protocol numbers. 
            A SBOX record boxes the record's type and data as well as the underscore prefix, and adds them to the record set
            of the associated label. For example, a URI record for "_scheme._trust.example.gns.alt"
            will be stored as an SBOX record in the record set of "example.gns.alt" with the underscore prefix
            "_schema._trust" and record type URI and the URI records data.</t>
          <t>For reference, see also <xref target="RFC8552" />.</t>
          <t>A SBOX DATA entry is illustrated in <xref
              target="figure_boxrecord" />.</t>
          <figure anchor="figure_boxrecord">
            <name>The SBOX DATA Wire Format</name>
            <artwork name="" type="" alt="">
0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
|          TYPE         |         PREFIX        /
+-----------+-----------+                       /
/                                               /
/                                               /
+-----------------------------------------------+
/                 RECORD DATA                   /
/                                               /
+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
            </artwork>
          </figure>
          <dl newline="false">
            <dt>TYPE:</dt>
            <dd>
              The 32-bit record type of the boxed record in network byte order.
            </dd>
            <dt>PREFIX:</dt>
            <dd> A variable-length field containing the first GNS name prefix consisting of multiple
              labels. The rightmost label <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> begin with an underscore.
              PREFIX <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a zero terminated string.
            </dd>
            <dt>RECORD DATA:</dt>
            <dd> A variable-length field containing the "DATA" format of TYPE as defined for the
              respective TYPE. Thus, for TYPE values below 2<sup>16</sup>, the format is the same as
              the respective record type's binary format in DNS. </dd>
          </dl>
          <section anchor="gnsrecords_sbox_box">
            <name>Overlap of BOX and SBOX records</name>
            <t>
              Records saved as BOX records can also be saved as SBOX records. 
              Thus, upon encountering underscore labels processable by BOX records, 
              the resolver must store the labels as their protocol and service numbers, 
              as well as the underscore prefix. This way, the resolver should be able to 
              return all boxed records later, whether they are SBOX or BOX records. 
              More on this in <xref target="resolution" />.
              BOX records are more efficient for boxing resource records due to their smaller wire format.
              Therefore, SBOX records are not a replacement for BOX records.
            </t>
          </section>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="resolution">
      <name>Name Resolution</name>
      <section anchor="record_processing">
        <name>Record Processing</name>
        <t> The first step in processing the records remains the same as described in <xref
            target="RFC9498" /> Section 7. </t>
        <t> The next step depends on the context of the name being resolved. Case 3, as defined in <xref
            target="RFC9498" /> Section 7.3, is modified here. All other cases and further processing steps remain the same.</t>
        <dl newline="false">
          <dt>Case 3:</dt>
          <dd>If the record set contains SBOX records and the name to be resolved is an underscore prefix, 
            the records in the matching SBOX records are part of the final result.
            The recursion is processed as described in <xref
              target="sbox_processing" />.
            Additionally, it <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be checked whether the record set contains BOX records and the underscore prefix is in the format "_SERVICE._PROTO".
            If this is the case the matching BOX records are added to the final result.  The recursion is processed as described in <xref
            target="box_processing" />.
            The final result is the combination of the unboxed record sets of the matched SBOX and BOX records.
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <section anchor="box_processing">
          <name>BOX</name>
          <t>
            When a BOX record is received, a GNS resolver must unbox it if the
            name to be resolved continues with "_SERVICE._PROTO".
            Otherwise, the BOX record is to be left untouched. This way, TLSA
            (and SRV) records do not require a separate network request, and
            TLSA records become inseparable from the corresponding address
            records.
          </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="sbox_processing">
          <name>SBOX</name>
          <t>
            When a SBOX record is received, a GNS resolver must unbox it if the
            name to be resolved continues with an underscore prefix.
            Otherwise, the SBOX record is to be left untouched.
          </t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="gana">
      <name>GANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="gana_gnsrr">
        <name>GNS Record Types Registry</name>
        <t> GANA <xref target="GANA" /> manages the "GNS Record Types" registry. </t>
        <t> GANA has assigned a number for the record type SBOX defined in this specification in the
          "GNS Record Types" registry as listed in <xref target="tab_rrtypenums" />. </t>

        <table anchor="tab_rrtypenums">
          <name>The GANA GNS Record Types Registry</name>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Number</th>
              <th>Name</th>
              <th>Contact</th>
              <th>References</th>
              <th>Comment</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td>65547</td>
              <td>SBOX</td>
              <td>(*)</td>
              <td>LSD 0008</td>
              <td>SBOX records</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
          <tfoot>
            <tr>
              <td align="left" colspan="5">(*): gns-registry@gnunet.org</td>
            </tr>
          </tfoot>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>

        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml" />
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml" />

        <reference anchor="GANA" target="https://gana.gnunet.org/">
          <front>
            <title>GNUnet Assigned Numbers Authority (GANA)</title>
            <author>
              <organization>GNUnet e.V.</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2023" />
          </front>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8552.xml" />
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9498.xml" />

      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
