<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent" [
        <!ENTITY RFC1034 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC1035 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC2782 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2782.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC3686 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3686.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC5869 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5869.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC3385 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3385.xml">
        <!ENTITY RFC1951 PUBLIC '' "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1951.xml">
        ]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="info" docName="draft-summermatter-set-union-01" ipr="trust200902"
     obsoletes="" updates="" submissionType="IETF" xml:lang="en" version="3">
    <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.26.0 -->
    <front>
        <title abbrev="Set Union">
            Byzantine Fault Tolerant Set Reconciliation
        </title>
        <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-summermatter-set-union-01"/>
        <author fullname="Elias Summermatter" initials="E." surname="Summermatter">
            <organization>Seccom GmbH</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Brunnmattstrasse 44</street>
                    <city>Bern</city>
                    <code>3007</code>
                    <country>CH</country>
                </postal>
                <email>elias.summermatter@seccom.ch</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Christian Grothoff" initials="C." surname="Grothoff">
            <organization>Berner Fachhochschule</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Hoeheweg 80</street>
                    <city>Biel/Bienne</city>
                    <code>2501</code>
                    <country>CH</country>
                </postal>
                <email>grothoff@gnunet.org</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->
        <area>General</area>
        <workgroup>Independent Stream</workgroup>
        <keyword>name systems</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t>This document contains a protocol specification for Byzantine fault-tolerant
                Set Reconciliation.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section anchor="introduction" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Introduction</name>
            <t>
              This document describes a byzantine fault tolerant set reconciliation protocol used to efficient and securely
              compute the union of two sets across a network.
            </t>
            <t>
              This byzantine fault tolerant set reconciliation
              protocol can be used in a variety of applications.

              Our primary envisioned application domain is the
              distribution of revocation messages in the GNU Name
              System (GNS) <xref target="GNS" format="default" />. In GNS,
              key revocation messages are usually flooded across the
              peer-to-peer overlay network to all connected peers
              whenever a key is revoked. However, as peers may be
              offline or the network might have been partitioned,
              there is a need to reconcile revocation lists whenever
              network partitions are healed or peers go online.  The
              GNU Name System uses the protocol described in this
              specification to efficiently distribute revocation
              messages whenever network partitions are healed.

              Another application domain for the protocol described
              in this specification are Byzantine fault-tolerant
              bulletin boards, like those required in some secure
              multiparty computations.  A well-known example for
              secure multiparty computations are various E-voting
              protocols <xref target="CryptographicallySecureVoting" format="default"/> which
              use a bulletin board to share the votes and intermediate
              computational results. We note that for such systems,
              the set reconciliation protocol is merely a component of
              a multiparty consensus protocol, such as the one
              described in Dold's "Byzantine set-union consensus using
              efficient set reconciliation" <xref target="ByzantineSetUnionConsensusUsingEfficientSetReconciliation" format="default"/>.
            </t>
            <t>
              The protocol described in this report is generic and
              suitable for a wide range of applications. As a result,
              the internal structure of the elements in the sets MUST
              be defined and verified by the application using the
              protocol.  This document thus does not cover the element
              structure, except for imposing a limit on the maximum
              size of an element.
            </t>
            <t>
              The protocol faces an inherent trade-off between minimizing
              the number of network round-trips and the number of bytes
              sent over the network.  Thus, for the protocol to choose
              the right parameters for a given situation, applications
              using an implementation of the protocol SHOULD provide a
              parameter that specifies
              the cost-ratio of round-trips vs. bandwidth usage.  Given
              this trade-off factor, an implementation CAN then choose parameters
              that minimize total execution cost.  In particular, there
              is one major choice to be made, namely between sending the
              complete set of elements, or computing the set differences and
              transmitting only the elements in the set differences.
              In the latter case, our design is basically a concrete
              implementation of a proposal by Eppstein.<xref target="Eppstein" format="default" />
            </t>

            <t>
              We say that our set reconciliation protocol is Byzantine
              fault-tolerant because it provides cryptographic and
              probabilistic methods to discover if the other peer
              is dishonest or misbehaving.
              Here, the security objective is to limit resources wasted on
              malicious actors. Malicious actors could send malformed
              messages, including malformed set elements, claim to
              have much larger numbers of valid set elements than they
              actually hold, or request the retransmission of elements
              that they have already received in previous
              interactions.  Bounding resources consumed by malicous
              actors is important to ensure that higher-level protocols
              can use set reconciliation and still meet their resource
              targets.  This can be particularly critical in multi-round
              synchronous consensus protocols where peers that cannot
              answer in a timely fashion would have to be treated as
              failed or malicious.
            </t>
            <t>
              To defend against some of these attacks, applications
              SHOULD remember the number of elements previously
              shared with a peer, and SHOULD provide a way to check that
              elements are well-formed. Applications MAY also
              provide an upper bound on the total number of valid
              elements that exist. For example, in E-voting, the
              number of eligible voters MAY be used to provide such
              an upper bound.
            </t>
            <t>
              A first draft of this RFC is part of Elias Summermatter's
              bachelor thesis. Many of the algorithms and parameters
              documented in this RFC are derived from experiments
              detailed in this thesis.
              <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/>
            </t>

            <t>
              This document defines the normative wire format of resource records, resolution processes,
              cryptographic routines and security considerations for use by implementors.
              SETU requires a bidirectional secure communication channel between the two parties.
              Specification of the communication channel is out of scope of this document.
            </t>
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
                NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
                "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described
                in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="background" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Background</name>
            <section anchor="bf" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Bloom Filter</name>
                <t>
                  A Bloom filter (BF) is a space-efficient probabilistic
                  datastructure to test if an element is part of a set of elements.
                  Elements are identified by an element ID.
                  Since a BF is a probabilistic datastructure, it is possible to have false-positives: when asked
                  if an element is in the set, the answer from a BF is either "no" or "maybe".
                </t>
                <t>
                    A BF consists of L buckets. Every bucket is a binary value that can be either 0 or 1. All buckets are initialized
                    to 0.  A mapping function M is used to map each ID of each element from the set to a subset of k buckets.  In the original proposal by Bloom, M is non-injective
                    and can thus map the same element multiple times to the same bucket.
                    The type of the mapping function can thus be described by the following mathematical notation:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="bf_mapping_function_math">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            ------------------------------------
            # M: E->B^k
            ------------------------------------
            # L = Number of buckets
            # B = 0,1,2,3,4,...L-1 (the buckets)
            # k = Number of buckets per element
            # E = Set of elements
            ------------------------------------
            Example: L=256, k=3
            M('element-data') = {4,6,255}

                     ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    A typical mapping function is constructed by hashing the element, for example
                    using the well-known <relref  section="2" target="RFC5869" displayFormat="of">HKDF construction</relref>.
                </t>
                <t>
                    To add an element to the BF, the corresponding buckets under the map M are set to 1.
                    To check if an element may be in the set, one tests if all buckets under the map M are set to 1.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In the BF the buckets are set to 1 if the corresponding bit in the bitstream is 1.
                    If there is a collision and a bucket is already set to 1, the bucket stays at 1.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In the following example the element e0 with M(e0) = {1,3} has been added:
                </t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_bf_insert_0">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
            +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
            |      0      |      1      |      0      |      1      |
            +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                     ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                <t>
                  It is easy to see that an element e1 with M(e1) = {0,3}
                  could have been added to the BF below, while an element e2
                  with M(e2) = {0,2} cannot be in the set represented by the
                  BF below:
                </t>

                <figure anchor="figure_bf_contains">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
            +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
            |      1      |      0      |      0      |      1      |
            +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                     ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                  The parameters L and k depend on the set size and MUST be
                  chosen carefully to ensure that the BF does not return too
                  many false-positives.
                </t>
                <t>
                    It is not possible to remove an element from the BF because buckets can only be set to 1 or 0. Hence it is impossible to
                    differentiate between buckets containing one or more elements. To remove elements from the BF a <xref target="cbf" format="title" />
                    is required.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="cbf" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Counting Bloom Filter</name>
                <t>
                  A Counting Bloom Filter (CBF) is a variation on the idea
                  of a <xref target="bf" format="title" />. With a CBF, buckets are
                  unsigned numbers instead of binary values.
                  This allows the removal of an element from the CBF.
                </t>
                <t>
                  Adding an element to the CBF is similar to the adding operation of the BF.
                  However, instead of setting the buckets to 1 the
                  numeric value stored in the bucket is increased by 1.
                  For example, if two colliding elements M(e1) = {1,3} and
                  M(e2) = {0,3} are added to the CBF, bucket 0 and 1 are set
                  to 1 and bucket 3 (the colliding bucket) is set to 2:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="figure_cbf_insert_0">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
            +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
            |      1      |      1      |      0      |      2      |
            +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                     ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                  The counter stored in the bucket is also called the order of the bucket.
                </t>
                <t>
                  To remove an element form the CBF the counters of all buckets
                  the element is mapped to are decreased by 1.
                </t>
                <t>
                  For example, removing M(e2) = {1,3} from the CBF above
                  results in:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="figure_cbf_remove_0">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
            +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
            |      1      |      0      |      0      |      1      |
            +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                     ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                  In practice, the number of bits available for the counters
                  is often finite. For example, given a 4-bit
                  counter, a CBF bucket would overflow 16 elements are mapped
                  to the same bucket. To handle this case, the maximum value
                  (15 in our example) is considered to represent "infinity". Once the
                  order of a bucket reaches "infinity", it is no longer incremented or decremented.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The parameters L and k and the number of bits allocated to the counters
                  SHOULD depend on the set size.
                  A CBF will degenerate when subjected to insert and remove iterations of
                  different elements, and eventually all buckets will reach "infinity".
                  The speed of the degradation will depend on the choice of L and k in
                  relation to the number of elements stored in the IBF.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="ibf" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Invertible Bloom Filter</name>
            <t>
                An Invertible Bloom Filter (IBF) is a further extension of the <xref target="cbf" format="title" />.
                An IBF extends the <xref target="cbf" format="title" /> with two more operations:
                decode and set difference. This two extra operations are key to efficiently obtain
                small differences between large sets.
            </t>
            <section anchor="ibf_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Structure</name>
                <t>
                  An IBF consists of an injective mapping function M mapping
                  elements to k out of L buckets. Each of the L buckets stores
                  a signed COUNTER, an IDSUM and an XHASH.
                  An IDSUM is the XOR of various element IDs.
                  An XHASH is the XOR of various hash values.
                  As before, the values used for k, L and the number of bits used
                  for the signed counter and the XHASH depend
                  on the set size and various other trade-offs.
                </t>
                <t>
                  If the IBF size is too small or the mapping
                  function does not spread out the elements
                  uniformly, the signed counter can overflow or
                  underflow. As with the CBF, the "maximum" value is
                  thus used to represent "infinite".  As there is no
                  need to distinguish between overflow and
                  underflow, the most canonical representation of
                  "infinite" would be the minimum value of the
                  counter in the canonical 2-complement
                  interpretation.  For example, given a 4-bit
                  counter a value of -8 would be used to represent
                  "infinity".
                </t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_structure">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+-------
  count |   COUNTER   |   COUNTER   |   COUNTER   |   COUNTER   |  C...
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+------
  idSum |    IDSUM    |    IDSUM    |    IDSUM    |     IDSUM   |  I...
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+------
hashSum |   HASHSUM   |   HASHSUM   |   HASHSUM   |    HASHSUM  |  H..
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+-------
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>

            </section>

            <section anchor="ibf_format_id_generation" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Salted Element ID Calculation</name>
              <t>
                IBFs are a probabilistic data structure, hence it can be necessary to
                recompute the IBF in case operations fail, and then try again. The
                recomputed IBF would ideally be statistically independent of the
                failed IBF. This is achieved by introducing an IBF-salt. Given that with
                benign peers failures should be rare, and that we need to be able to
                "invert" the application of the IBF-salt to the element IDs, we use an
                unsigned 32 bit non-random IBF-salt value of which the lowest 6 bits will
                be used to rotate bits in the element ID computation.
              </t>
              <t>
                64-bit element IDs are generated from a
                <relref  section="2" target="RFC5869" displayFormat="of">HKDF construction</relref>
                with HMAC-SHA512 as XTR and HMAC-SHA256 as PRF with a 16-bit KDF-salt set to a
                unsigned 16-bit representation of zero.
                The output of the KDF is then truncated to 64-bit.
                Finally, salting is done by calculating the IBF-salt modulo 64
                (effectively using only the lowest 6-bits of the IBF-salt)
                and doing a bitwise right rotation of the output of KDF.  We
                note that this operation was chosen as it is easily inverted,
                allowing applications to easily derive element IDs with one
                IBF-salt value from element IDs generated with a different
                IBF-salt value.
              </t>
              <t>
                In case the IBF does not decode, the IBF-salt can be changed to
                compute different element IDs, which will (likely) be mapped
                to different buckets, likely allowing the IBF to decode in a
                subsequent iteration.
              </t>
              <figure anchor="ibf_format_id_generation_pseudo_code">
                <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
# INPUTS:
# key: Pre calculated and truncated key from id_calculation function
# ibf_salt: Salt of the IBF
# OUTPUT:
# value: salted key
FUNCTION salt_key(key,ibf_salt):
  s = (ibf_salt * 7) modulo 64;
  /* rotate key */
  return (key >> s) | (key << (64 - s))
END FUNCTION


# INPUTS:
# element: element for which we are to calculate the element ID
# ibf_salt: Salt of the IBF
# OUTPUT:
# value: the ID of the element
FUNCTION id_calculation (element,ibf_salt):
    kdf_salt = 0 // 16 bits
    XTR=HMAC-SHA256
    PRF=HMAC-SHA256
    key = HKDF(XTR, PRF, kdf_salt, element) modulo 2^64
    return salt_key(key, ibf_salt)
END FUNCTION
                 ]]></artwork>
              </figure>
            </section>

            <section anchor="ibf_format_HASH_calculation" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>HASH calculation</name>
              <t>
                The HASH of an element ID is computed by calculating the
                CRC32 checksum of the 64-bit ID value,
                which returns a 32-bit value.CRC32 is well-known and described in <relref  section="4.1" target="RFC3385" displayFormat="of">the RFC</relref>.
              </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="ibf_m" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Mapping Function</name>
              <t>
                The mapping function M decides which buckets a given ID is mapped to.
                For an IBF, it is beneficial to use an injective mapping function M.
              </t>
              <t>
                The first index is simply the CRC32 of the ID modulo the IBF size. The second
                index is calculated by creating a new 64-bit value by shifting the previous 32-bit
                value left and setting the lower 32 bits to the number of indices already processed.
                From the resulting 64-bit value, another CRC32 checksum is computed.
                The subsequent index is the modulo of this CRC32 output.
                The process is repeated until the desired number of indices is generated.
                In the case the process computes the same index twice,
                which would mean this bucket could not get pure again,
                the second hit is just skipped and the next iteration is used instead,
                creating an injective mapping function.
              </t>
              <figure anchor="ibf_format_bucket_identification_pseudo_code">
                <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
# INPUTS:
# key: the ID of the element calculated
# k: numbers of buckets per element
# L: total number of buckets in the IBF
# OUTPUT:
# dst: Array with k bucket IDs
FUNCTION get_bucket_id (key, k, L)
  bucket = CRC32(key)
  i = 0 // unsigned 32-bit index
  filled = 0
  WHILE filled < k DO

    element_already_in_bucket = false
    j = 0
    WHILE j < filled DO
      IF dst[j] == bucket modulo L THEN
        element_already_in_bucket = true
      END IF
      j++
    END WHILE

    IF !element_already_in_bucket THEN
        dst[filled] = bucket modulo L
        filled = filled + 1
    END IF

    x = (bucket << 32) | i // 64 bit result
    bucket = CRC32(x)
    i = i + 1
  END WHILE
  return dst
END FUNCTION
  ]]></artwork>
              </figure>
            </section>

            <section anchor="ibf_operations" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Operations</name>
              <t>
                When an IBF is created, all counters and IDSUM and HASHSUM values of
                all buckets are initialized to zero.
              </t>
                <section anchor="ibv_operations_insert" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Insert Element</name>
                    <t>
                      To add an element to an IBF, the element is mapped to a subset of k buckets using
                      the injective mapping function M as described in section <xref target="ibf_m" format="title" />. For the buckets selected by the mapping function, the counter is increased by one and the
                      IDSUM field is set to the XOR of the element ID
                      computed as described in section <xref target="ibf_format_id_generation" format="title" />
                      and the previously stored IDSUM. Furthermore,
                      the HASHSUM is set to the XOR of the previously stored HASHSUM
                      and the hash of the element ID computed as described
                      in section <xref target="ibf_format_HASH_calculation" format="title" />.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      In the following example, the insert operation is illustrated using an element with the
                      ID 0x0102 mapped to {1,3} with a hash of 0x4242, and a second element with the
                      ID 0x0304 mapped to {0,1} and a hash of 0x0101.
                    </t>
                    <t>Empty IBF:</t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_insert_0">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      0      |      0      |      0      |      0      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>Insert first element with ID 0x0102 and hash 0x4242 into {1,3}:</t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_insert_1">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      0      |      1      |      0      |      1      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>Insert second element with ID 0x0304 and hash 0101 into {0,1}:</t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_insert_2">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      1      |      2      |      0      |      1      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0304   |   0x0206    |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0101   |   0x4343    |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section anchor="ibf_operations_remove" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Remove Element</name>
                    <t>
                        To remove an element from the IBF the element is again mapped to a subset of the buckets using M.
                        Then all the counters of the buckets selected by M are reduced by one, the IDSUM is
                        replaced by the XOR of the old IDSUM and the ID of the element being removed, and the
                        HASHSUM is similarly replaced with the XOR of the old HASHSUM and the hash of the ID.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        In the following example the remove operation is illustrated.
                    </t>
                <t>IBF with two encoded elements:</t>
                <figure anchor="figure_ibf_remove_0">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      1      |      2      |      0      |      1      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0304   |   0x0206    |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |   0x0101    |   0x4343    |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                    <t>After removal of element with ID 0x0304 and hash 0x0101 mapped to {0,1} from the IBF:</t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_remove_1">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      0      |      1      |      0      |      1      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                      Note that it is possible to "remove" elements from an IBF that were never present
                      in the IBF in the first place. A negative counter value is thus indicative of
                      elements that were removed without having been added.  Note that an IBF bucket
                      counter of zero no longer guarantees that an element mapped to that bucket is not
                      present in the set: a bucket with a counter of zero can be the result of one
                      element being added and a different element (mapped to the same bucket) being removed.
                      To check that an element is not present requires a counter of zero and an
                      IDSUM and HASHSUM of zero --- and some certainty that there was no collision due
                      to the limited number of bits in IDSUM and HASHSUM.  Thus,
                      IBFs are not suitable to replace BFs or IBFs.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      Buckets in an IBF with a counter of 1 or -1 are crucial for decoding an IBF, as
                      they MIGHT represent only a single element, with the IDSUM being the ID of that element.
                      Following Eppstein <xref target="Eppstein" format="default" />, we will call buckets that only represent a single
                      element <em>pure buckets</em>.
                      Note that due to the possibility of multiple insertion and removal operations
                      affecting the same bucket, not all buckets with a counter of 1 or -1 are
                      actually pure buckets.  Sometimes a counter can be 1 or -1 because N elements
                      mapped to that bucket were added while N-1 or N+1 different elements also
                      mapped to that bucket were removed.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <section anchor="ibf_operations_decode" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Extracting elements</name>
                    <t>
                      Extracting elements from an IBF yields IDs of elements from the IBF.
                      Elements are extracted from an IBF by repeatedly performing a
                      decode operation on the IBF.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      A decode operation requires a pure bucket, that is a bucket to which M
                      only mapped a single element, to succeed.  Thus, if there is no bucket with
                      a counter of 1 or -1, decoding fails. However, as a counter of 1 or -1 is
                      not a guarantee that the bucket is pure, there is also a chance that the
                      decoder returns an IDSUM value that is actually the XOR of several IDSUMs.
                      This is primarily detected by checking that the HASHSUM is the hash of the IDSUM.
                      Only if the HASHSUM also matches, the bucket could be pure.  Additionally,
                      one MUST check that the IDSUM value actually would be mapped by M to
                      the respective bucket. If not, there was a hash collision and the bucket
                      is also not pure.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      The very rare case that after all these checks a bucket is still
                      falsely identified as pure MUST be detected (say by determining that
                      extracted element IDs do not match any actual elements), and addressed
                      at a higher level in the protocol. As these failures are probabilistic
                      and depend on element IDs and the IBF construction, they can typically
                      be avoided by retrying with different parameters, such as a different
                      way to assign element IDs to elements (by varying the IBF-salt),
                      using a larger value for L, or a different mapping function M.
                      A more common scenario (especially if L was too small) is that
                      IBF decoding fails because there is no pure bucket. In this case, the
                      higher-level protocol generally MUST also retry using different
                      parameters (except if an attack is detected).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      Suppose the IBF contains a pure bucket. In this case, the IDSUM in the
                      bucket is the ID of an element.  Furthermore, it is then possible
                      to remove that element from the IBF (by inserting it if the counter
                      was negative, and by removing it if the counter was positive). This
                      is likely to cause other buckets to become pure, allowing further
                      elements to be decoded.  Eventually, decoding ought to finish with
                      all counters and IDSUM and HASHSUM values reach zero. However, it is also
                      possible that an IBF only partly decodes and then decoding fails due
                      to the lack of pure buckets after extracting some element IDs.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      In the following example the successful decoding of an IBF containing
                      the two elements previously added in our running example.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                       We begin with an IBF with two elements added:
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_decode_0">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      1      |      2      |      0      |      1      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |   0x0304    |   0x0206    |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |   0x0101    |   0x4343    |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                      In the IBF are two pure buckets to decode (buckets 0 and 3) we choose to start with
                      decoding bucket 0. This yields the element with the hash ID 0x0304 and
                      hash 1010. This element ID is mapped to buckets
                      {0,1}.
                      Subtracting this element results in bucket 1 becoming pure:
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_decode_1">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      0      |      1      |      0      |      1      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>
                        We can now decoding bucket 2 and extract the element
                        with the ID 0x0102 and hash 0x4242. Now the IBF is
                        empty. Extraction completes with the status that
                        the IBF has been successfully decoded.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_decode_2">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      0      |      0      |      0      |      0      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |    0x0000   |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>

                <section anchor="ibv_operations_setdiff" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Set Difference</name>
                    <t>
                        Given addition and removal as defined above, it is possible to define an operation on IBFs
                        that computes an IBF representing the set difference.  Suppose IBF1 represents set A, and
                        IBF2 represents set B.  Then this set difference operation will compute IBF3 which
                        represents the set A - B. Note that this computation can be done only on the IBFs,
                        and does not require access to the elements from set A or B.

                        To calculate the IBF representing this set difference, both IBFs MUST have the same
                        length L, the same number of buckets per element k and use the same map M.
                        Naturally, all IDs must have been computed using the same IBF-salt.  Given this,
                        one can compute the IBF representing the set difference by taking the XOR of the IDSUM and HASHSUM values
                        of the respective buckets and subtracting the respective counters.  Care MUST be taken
                        to handle overflows and underflows by setting the counter to "infinity" as necessary.
                        The result is a new IBF with the same number of buckets representing the set difference.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This new IBF can be decoded as described in section <xref target="ibf_operations_decode" format="counter" />.
                        The new IBF can have two types of pure buckets with counter set to 1 or -1. If the counter is set to 1
                        the element is missing in the secondary set, and if the counter is set to -1 the element is missing in
                        the primary set.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        To demonstrate the set difference operation we compare IBF-A with IBF-B and generate as described
                        IBF-AB
                    </t>
                    <t>IBF-A contains the elements with ID 0x0304 and hash 0x0101 mapped to {0,1},
                       and ID 0x0102 and hash 0x4242 mapped to {1,3}:</t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_setdiff_A">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      1      |      2      |      0      |      1      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0304   |   0x0206    |    0x0000   |   0x0102    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0101   |   0x4343    |    0x0000   |   0x4242    |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>IBF-B also contains the element with ID 0x0102 and
                     and another element with ID 0x1345 and hash 0x5050
                     mapped to {1,2}.</t>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_setdiff_B">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      0      |      1      |      1      |      1      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0000   |    0x1447   |    0x1345   |    0x0102   |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0000   |    0x9292   |    0x5050   |    0x4242   |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                <t>IBF-A minus IBF-B is then:</t>
                <figure anchor="figure_ibf_setdiff_AB">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
            bucket-0     bucket-1       bucket-2      bucket-3
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  count |      1      |      0      |      -1     |      0      |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
  idSum |    0x0304   |    0x1049   |    0x1345   |    0x0000   |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
hashSum |    0x0101   |    0x5151   |    0x5050   |    0x0000   |
        +-------------+-------------+-------------+-------------+
                 ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>After calculating and decoding the IBF-AB shows clear that in IBF-A the element with the hash 0x5050
                    is missing (-1 in bucket 2) while in IBF-B the element with the hash 0101 is missing
                    (1 in bucket 0). The element with hash 0x4242 is present in IBF-A and IBF-B and is
                    removed by the set difference operation.  Bucket 2 is not empty.
                </t>
            </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="ibf_format" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Wire format</name>
                <t>
                    For the counter field, we use a variable-size encoding to ensure
                    that even for very large sets the counter should never reach
                    "infinity", while also ensuring that the encoding is compact for
                    small sets.
                    Hence, the counter size transmitted over the wire
                    varies between 1 and 64 bits, depending on the
                    maximum counter in the IBF. A range of 1 to 64 bits
                    should cover most areas of application and can be
                    efficiently implemented on most contemporary CPU
                    architectures and programming languages.
                    The bit length for the transmitted IBF
                    will be communicated in the header of the
                    <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em> message
                    in the "IMCS" field as unsigned 8-bit integer.
                    For implementation details see section <xref target="performance_counter_variable_size" format="title" />.
                </t>
                <t>
                    For the "IDSUM", we always use a 64-bit representation.
                    The IDSUM value MUST have sufficient entropy for the
                    mapping function M to yield reasonably random buckets
                    even for very large values of L. With a 32 bit
                    value the chance that multiple elements may be mapped
                    to the same ID would be quite high, even for moderately
                    large sets.  Using more than 64 bits would at best make
                    sense for very large sets, but then it is likely always
                    better to simply afford additional round trips to handle
                    the occasional collision. 64 bits are also a reasonable
                    size for many CPU architectures.
                </t>
                <t>
                    For the "HASHSUM", we always use a 32-bit
                    representation.  Here, it is most important to
                    avoid collisions, where different elements are
                    mapped to the same hash, possibly resulting in
                    a bucket being falsely classified as pure.
                    While with 32 bits there remains a non-negligible chance of
                    accidental collisions, our protocol is designed
                    to handle occasional collisions. Hence, at 32 bit the chance is
                    believed to be sufficiently small enough
                    for the protocol to handle those cases efficiently.  Smaller hash
                    values would safe bandwidth, but also substantially
                    increase the chance of collisions. 32 bits are
                    also again a reasonable size for many CPU
                    architectures.
                </t>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="se" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Strata Estimator</name>
                <t>
                    Strata Estimators help estimate the size of the set difference between two sets of elements.
                    This is necessary to efficiently determinate the tuning parameters for an IBF, in particular
                    a good value for L.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Basically a Strata Estimator (SE) is a series of IBFs (with a rather small value of L=79)
                    in which increasingly large subsets of the full set
                    of elements are added to each IBF.  For the n-th IBF, the function selecting the
                    subset of elements MUST sample to select (probabilistically) 1/(2^n) of all
                    elements.  This can be done by counting the number of trailing bits set to "1"
                    in an element ID, and then inserting the element into the IBF identified by that
                    counter.  As a result, all elements will be mapped to one IBF, with the n-th
                    IBF being statistically expected to contain 1/(2^n) elements.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Given two SEs, the set size difference can be estimated by attempting to decode all of the
                    IBFs.  Given that L is set to a fixed and rather small value, IBFs containing large strata
                    will likely fail to decode.  For IBFs that failed to decode, one simply
                    extrapolates the number of elements by scaling the numbers obtained from the
                    other IBFs that did decode.  If none of the IBFs of the SE decoded (which given
                    a reasonable number of IBFs in the SE should be highly unlikely), one can theoretically
                    retry using a different IBF-salt.
                </t>
                <t>
                    When decoding the IBFs in the strata estimator, it is possible to determine
                    on which side which part of the difference is. For this purpose, the pure buckets with
                    counter 1 and -1 must be distinguished and assigned to the respective side when decoding
                    the IBFs.
                </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="modeofoperation" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Mode of Operation</name>
            <t>
              Depending on the state of the two sets the set union
              protocol uses different modes of operation to efficiently
              determinate missing elements between the two sets.
            </t>
            <t>
              The simplest mode is the <em>full synchronisation mode</em>.
              If the difference between the sets of the two
              peers exceeds a certain threshold, the overhead to determine
              which elements are different would outweigh the overhead of
              simply sending the complete set. Hence, the protocol may
              determine that the most efficient method is to exchange the full sets.
            </t>
            <t>
              The second possibility is that the difference between the sets
              is relatively small compared to the set size.
              In this case, the <em>differential synchronisation mode</em> is more efficient.
              Given these two possibilities, the first steps of the protocol are used to
              determine which mode MUST be used.
            </t>
            <t>
              Thus, the set union protocol always begins with the following operation mode independent steps:
            </t>

            <t>
              The initiating peer begins in the <strong>Initiating Connection</strong> state and the receiving peer in the <strong>Expecting Connection</strong>
              state. The first step for the initiating peer in the protocol is to send an <em><xref target="messages_operation_request" format="title" /></em> to the receiving peer and
              transition into the <strong>Expect SE</strong> state. After receiving the <em><xref target="messages_operation_request" format="title" /></em> the receiving peer
              transitions to the <strong>Expecting IBF</strong> state and answers with the
              <em><xref target="messages_se" format="title" /></em> message. When the initiating peer receives the <em><xref target="messages_se" format="title" /></em> message,
              it decides with some heuristics which operation mode is likely more suitable for the estimated set difference and the application-provided latency-bandwidth tradeoff.
              The detailed algorithm used to choose between the <xref target="modeofoperation_full-sync" format="title" /> and the <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" />
              is explained in the section <xref target="modeofoperation_combined-mode" format="title" /> below.
            </t>
            <section anchor="modeofoperation_full-sync" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Full Synchronisation Mode</name>
              <t>
                When the initiating peer decides to use the full synchronisation mode and it is better that the other peer sends his set first, the initiating
                peer sends a <em><xref target="messages_request_full" format="title" /></em> message, and transitions from <strong>Expecting SE</strong> to the <strong>Full Receiving</strong> state.
                If it has been determined that it is better that the initiating peer sends his set first, the initiating peer sends a <em><xref target="messages_send_full" format="title" /></em> message followed by all
                set elements in <em><xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" /></em> messages to the other peer, followed by the <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message, and transitions into the <strong>Full Sending</strong> state.
              </t>
              <t>
                A state diagram illustrating the state machine used during full synchronization
                is provided
                <eref target="https://git.gnunet.org/lsd0003.git/plain/statemachine/state_machine_full.png">here</eref>.
              </t>
              <t><strong>The behavior of the participants the different state is described below:</strong></t>
              <dl>
                <dt><strong>Expecting IBF:</strong></dt>
                <dd>
                  If a peer in the <strong>Expecting IBF</strong> state receives a <em><xref target="messages_request_full" format="title" /></em> message from the other peer, the
                  peer sends all the elements of his set followed by a <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message to the other peer, and transitions to the
                  <strong>Full Sending</strong> state. If the peer receives an <em><xref target="messages_send_full" format="title" /></em> message followed by
                  <em><xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" /></em> messages, the peer processes the element and transitions to the <strong>Full Receiving</strong> state.
                </dd>
                <dt><strong>Full Sending:</strong></dt>
                <dd>
                  While a peer is in <strong>Full Sending</strong> state the peer expects to continuously receive elements from the other
                  peer. As soon as a the <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message is received, the peer transitions into
                  the <strong>Finished</strong> state.
                </dd>
                <dt><strong>Full Receiving: </strong></dt>
                <dd>
                  While a peer is in the <strong>Full Receiving</strong> state, it expects to continuously receive elements from the other
                  peer. As soon as a the <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message is received, it sends
                  the remaining elements (those it did not receive) from his set to the other
                  peer, followed by a <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em>.
                  After sending the last message, the peer transitions into the <strong>Finished</strong> state.
                </dd>
              </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="modeofoperation_individual-elements" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Differential Synchronisation Mode</name>
              <t>
                The message format used by the protocol limits the maximum message size to
                64 kb. Given that L can be large, an IBF will not always fit within that
                size limit. To deal with this, larger IBFs are split into multiple messages.
              </t>
              <t>
                When the initiating peer in the <strong>Expected SE</strong> state decides to use the differential synchronisation mode, it
                sends an IBF, which may
                consist of several <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em> messages,
                to the receiving peer and transitions into the <strong>Passive Decoding</strong> state.
              </t>
              <t>
                The receiving peer in the <strong>Expecting IBF</strong> state receives the
                first <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em> message from
                the initiating peer, and transitions into the <strong>Expecting IBF Last</strong> state
                if the IBF was split into multiple <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em>
                messages. If there is just a single <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em>
                message, the receiving peer
                transitions directly to the <strong>Active Decoding</strong> state.
              </t>
              <t>
                The peer that is in the <strong>Active Decoding</strong>, <strong>Finish Closing</strong> or in the <strong>Expecting IBF Last</strong>
                state is called the active peer, and the peer that is in either the <strong>Passive Decoding</strong> or the <strong>Finish Waiting</strong> state
                is called the passive peer.
              </t>
              <t>
                A state diagram illustrating the state machine used during differential synchronization
                is provided
                <eref target="https://git.gnunet.org/lsd0003.git/plain/statemachine/differential_state_machine.png">here</eref>.
              </t>
              <t><strong>The behavior of the participants the different states is described below:</strong></t>
              <dl>
                <dt><strong>Passive Decoding:</strong></dt>
                <dd>
                  <t>
                    In the <strong>Passive Decoding</strong> state the passive peer reacts to requests from the active peer.
                    The action the passive peer executes depends on the message the passive peer receives in the <strong>Passive Decoding</strong> state from the active peer
                    and is described below on a per message basis.
                  </t>

                  <dl>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      The <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> message
                      is received if the active peer requests the SHA-512 hash of one or more elements (by sending the 64 bit element ID)
                      that are missing from the active peer's set.
                      In this case the passive peer answers with <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> messages
                      which contain the SHA-512 hash of the requested element.  If the passive peer does not have an element with
                      a matching element ID, it MUST ignore the inquiry (in this case, a bucket was falsely classified as pure, decoding the IBF will eventually fail, and roles will be swapped).
                      It should be verified that after an falsely classified pure bucket a role change is made.
                      If multiple elements match the 64 bit element ID, the passive
                      peer MUST send offers for all of the matching elements.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      The <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message
                      is received if the active peer requests a complete element that is missing in the active peers set in response to an offer. If the requested element is known and has not yet been transmitted
                      the passive peer answers with an <em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message which contains the full,
                      application-dependent data of the requested element.  If the passive peer receives a demand for a SHA-512 hash for which
                      it has no corresponding element, a protocol violation is detected and the protocol MUST be aborted.
                      Implementations MUST also abort when facing demands without previous matching offers or for which the passive peer previously transmitted the element to the active peer.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      The <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message
                      is received if the active peer has decoded an element that is present in the active peers set and is likely be missing in the
                      set of the passive peer. If the SHA-512 hash of the offer is indeed not a hash of any of the elements from the set of
                      the passive peer, the passive peer MUST answer with a <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message
                      for that SHA-512 hash and remember that it issued this demand. The demand thus needs to be added to a list with unsatisfied demands.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      When a new <em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message has been received the peer checks if a corresponding
                      <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> for the element has been sent
                      and the demand is still unsatisfied.
                      If the element has been demanded the peer checks the element for validity, removes it from the list
                      of pending demands and then saves the element to the set. Otherwise the peer
                      ignores the element.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      If an <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em> message is received, this
                      indicates that decoding of the IBF on the active site has failed and roles will be swapped.
                      The receiving passive peer transitions into the <strong>Expecting IBF Last</strong> state,
                      and waits for more <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em> messages.
                      There, once the final <em><xref target="messages_ibf_last" format="title" /></em> message has been received, it transitions to <strong>Active Decoding</strong>.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_ibf_last" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      If an <em><xref target="messages_ibf_last" format="title" /></em> message is received this
                      indicates that there is just one IBF slice left and a direct state and role transition from
                      <strong>Passive Decoding</strong> to <strong>Active Decoding</strong> is initiated.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      Receiving the <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message signals
                      the passive peer that all demands of the active peer have been satisfied. Alas, the
                      active peer will continue to process demands from the passive peer.
                      Upon receiving this message, the passive peer transitions into the
                      <strong>Finish Waiting</strong> state.
                    </dd>
                  </dl>
                </dd>
                <dt><strong>Active Decoding:</strong></dt>
                <dd>
                  <t>
                    In the <strong>Active Decoding</strong> state the active peer decodes the IBFs and evaluates the set difference
                    between the active and passive peer. Whenever an element ID is obtained by decoding the IBF, the active peer
                    sends either an offer or an inquiry to the passive peer, depending on which site the decoded element is missing.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    If the IBF decodes a positive (1) pure bucket, the element is missing on the passive peers site.
                    Thus, the active peer sends an <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> to the passive peer.
                    A negative (-1) pure bucket indicates that an element is missing in the active peers set, so the active peer
                    sends a <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> to the passive peer.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    In case the IBF does not successfully decode anymore, the active peer sends a new IBF computed with a different IBF-salt to the passive peer
                    and changes into <strong>Passive Decoding</strong> state. This initiates a role swap.
                    To reduce overhead and prevent double transmission of offers and elements, the new IBF is created
                    on the local set after updating it with the all of the elements that have been successfully demanded.  Note that the active peer MUST NOT wait for all active demands to be satisfied, as demands can fail if a bucket was falsely classified as pure.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    As soon as the active peer successfully finished decoding the IBF, the active peer sends a
                    <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message to the passive peer.
                  </t>
                  <t>
                    All other actions taken by the active peer depend on the message the active peer receives from
                    the passive peer. The actions are described below on a per message basis:
                  </t>
                  <dl>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      The <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message indicates that the
                      passive peer received a <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> message from
                      the active peer. If a inquiry has been sent and
                      the offered element is missing in the active peers set,
                      the active peer sends a <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message to the
                      passive peer. The demand needs to be added to a list of unsatisfied demands.
                      In case the received offer is for an element that is already in the set of the peer, the offer MUST BE ignored.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      The <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message indicates that the
                      passive peer received a <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> from
                      the active peer. The active peer satisfies the demand of the passive peer by sending an
                      <em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message if a offer request
                      for the element was sent earlier. Otherwise, the protocol MUST be aborted, as peers must never send demands for hashes that they have never been offered.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      If element is received that was not demanded or for which
                      the application-specific validation logic fails, the protocol
                      MUST be aborted.  Otherwise, the corresponding demand is marked
                      as satisfied.  Note that this applies only to the differential
                      synchronization mode. In full synchronization, it is perfectly
                      normal to receive
                      <xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" />
                      messages for elements that were not demanded and that might
                      even already be known locally.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message:</dt>
                    <dd>
                      Receiving the message <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> indicates
                      that all demands of the passive peer have been satisfied. The active peer then changes into the
                      <strong>Finish Closing</strong> state.
                      If the IBF has not finished decoding and the <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em>
                      is received, the other peer is not in compliance with the protocol and the protocol MUST be aborted.
                    </dd>
                  </dl>
                </dd>
                <dt><strong>Expecing IBF Last</strong></dt>
                <dd>
                  <t>
                    In this state the active peer continuously receives <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em>
                    messages from the passive peer. When the last <em><xref target="messages_ibf_last" format="title" /></em> message is received,
                    the peer changes into the <strong>Active Decoding</strong> state.
                  </t>
                </dd>
                <dt><strong>Finish Closing</strong> / <strong>Finish Waiting</strong></dt>
                <dd>
                  <t>
                    In this states the peers are waiting for all demands to be satisfied and for the synchronisation
                    to be completed. When all demands are satisfied the peer changes into <strong>Finished</strong> state.
                  </t>
                </dd>
              </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="modeofoperation_combined-mode" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Combined Mode</name>
              <t>
                In the <em>combined mode</em> the protocol decides between
                <xref target="modeofoperation_full-sync" format="title" /> and
                the <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" />
                to minimize resource consumption.  Typically, the protocol always runs
                in combined mode, but implementations MAY allow applications to force
                the use of one of the modes for testing.  In this case, applications MUST
                ensure that the respective options to force a particular mode are used by
                both participants.
              </t>
              <t>
                The <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" /> is only efficient on small set
                differences or if the byte-size of the elements is large. If the set difference is estimated to be large
                the <xref target="modeofoperation_full-sync" format="title" /> is
                more efficient. The exact heuristics and parameters on which the protocol decides which mode
                MUST be used are described in the <xref target="performance" format="title" /> section of this document.
              </t>
              <t>
                There are two main cases when a <xref target="modeofoperation_full-sync" format="title" />
                is always used.
                The first case is when one of the peers announces having an empty set. This is announced by setting
                the SETSIZE field in the <em><xref target="messages_se" format="title" /></em> to 0.
                <!-- FIXME: why not also do this if sending the elements is about as
                     expensive as sending the SE? Should be a simple calculation. (thesis summermatter: future work) @Christian:
                      As discussed 14.06 we let this comment in here as it is described in the thesis-->
                The second case is if the application requests full synchronisation explicitly.
                This is useful for testing and MUST NOT be used in production.
              </t>
              <t>
                The state diagram illustrating the combined mode can be found
                <eref target="https://git.gnunet.org/lsd0003.git/plain/statemachine/full_state_machine.png">here</eref>.
              </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="messages" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Messages</name>
            <t>
              This section describes the various message formats used by the protocol.
            </t>
            <section anchor="messages_operation_request" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Operation Request</name>

                <section anchor="messages_operation_request_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        This message is the first message of the protocol and it is sent to signal to the receiving peer
                        that the initiating peer wants to initialize a new connection.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This message is sent in the transition between the <strong>Initiating Connection</strong> state and the <strong>Expect SE</strong> state.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      If a peer receives this message and is willing to run the protocol, it answers by sending back a <em><xref target="messages_se" format="title" /></em> message.
                      Otherwise it simply closes the connection.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_operation_request_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>

                    <figure anchor="figure_operation_request">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |    ELEMENT COUNT      |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                      APX
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /  APPLICATION DATA                             /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                          is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                          is the type of SETU_P2P_OPERATION_REQUEST as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" />, in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>ELEMENT COUNT</dt>
                        <dd>
                          is the number of the elements the requesting party has in its set, as a 32-bit unsigned integer in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>APX</dt>
                        <dd>
                          is a SHA-512 hash that identifies the application.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>APPLICATION DATA</dt>
                        <dd>
                          is optional, variable-size application specific data that can be used
                          by the application to decide if it would like to answer the request.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_ibf" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>IBF</name>

                <section anchor="messages_ibf_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /> message contains a slice of the IBF.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The <em>IBF</em> message is sent at the start of the protocol from the initiating peer in the transaction
                        between <strong>Expect SE</strong> -> <strong>Expecting IBF Last</strong> or when the IBF does not
                        decode and there is a role change in the transition between <strong>Active Decoding</strong> -> <strong>Expecting IBF Last</strong>.
                        This message is only sent if there is more than one IBF slice to be sent. If there is just
                        one slice, then only the <xref target="messages_ibf_last" format="title" /> message is sent.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_ibf_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |       IBF SIZE        |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |         OFFSET        |    SALT   |   IMCS    |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                   IBF-SLICE
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte orderwhichdescribes the message size in bytes with the header included.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            the type of SETU_P2P_REQUEST_IBF as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>

                        <dt>IBF SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 32-bit unsigned integer which signals the total number of buckets in the IBF.  The minimal number of buckets is 37.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>OFFSET</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 32-bit unsigned integer which signals the offset of the following IBF slices in the original.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>SALT</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer that contains the IBF-salt which was used to create the
                            IBF.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>IMCS</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer, which describes the number of bits that
                            are required to store a single counter. This is used for the unpacking function as described
                            in the <xref target="performance_counter_variable_size" format="title" /> section.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>IBF-SLICE</dt>
                        <dd>
                          <t>
                            are variable numbers of slices in an array. A single slice contains multiple 64-bit IDSUMS,
                            32-bit HASHSUMS and (1-64)-bit COUNTERS of variable size. All values are in the network byte order. The array of IDSUMS is serialized first, followed
                            by an array of HASHSUMS. Last comes an array of unsigned COUNTERS (details of the COUNTERS encoding are described in section
                            <xref target="performance_counter_variable_size" format="default"/>). The length of the array is
                            defined by MIN( SIZE - OFFSET, MAX_BUCKETS_PER_MESSAGE). MAX_BUCKETS_PER_MESSAGE is defined as
                            32768 divided by the BUCKET_SIZE which ranges between 97-bits when counter uses bit 1 (IMCS=1) and 160-bit when counter size uses 64 bit (IMCS=64).
                          </t>
                          <t>
                            To get the IDSUM field, all IDs (computed with the IBF-salt) hitting a bucket under the map M are added up with a binary XOR operation.
                            See <xref target="ibf_format_id_generation" format="title" /> details about ID generation.
                          </t>
                          <t>
                            The calculation of the HASHSUM field is done accordingly to the calculation of the IDSUM field:
                            all HASHes are added up with a binary XOR operation.
                            The HASH value is calculated as described in detail in section <xref target="ibf_format_HASH_calculation" format="title" />.
                          </t>
                          <t>
                            The algorithm to find the correct bucket in which the ID and the HASH have to be added
                            is described in detail in section <xref target="ibf_m" format="title" />.
                          </t>
                          <t>
                            Test vectors for an implementation can be found in the <xref target="test_vectors" format="title" /> section
                          </t>
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                    <figure anchor="figure_ibf_slice">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                             IBF-SLICE
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                    IDSUMS                     |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                    IDSUMS                     |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |        HASHSUMS       |        HASHSUMS       |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |        COUNTERS*      |        COUNTERS*      |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
* Counter size is variable. In this example the IMCS is 32 (4 bytes).
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_ibf_last" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>IBF Last</name>

              <section anchor="messages_ibf_last_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Description</name>
                <t>
                  This message indicates to the remote peer that this is the last slice
                  of the Bloom filter. The receiving peer MUST check that the sizes and
                  offsets of all received IBF slices add up to the total IBF SIZE that was
                  given.
                </t>
                <t>
                  Receiving this message initiates the state transmissions
                  <strong>Expecting IBF Last</strong> -> <strong>Active Decoding</strong>,
                  <strong>Expecting IBF</strong> -> <strong>Active Decoding</strong> and
                  <strong>Passive Decoding</strong> -> <strong>Active Decoding</strong>. This message
                  can initiate a peer the roll change from <strong>Active Decoding</strong> to
                  <strong>Passive Decoding</strong>.
                </t>
              </section>
              <section anchor="messages_ibf_last_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Structure</name>
                <t>
                  The binary structure is exactly the same as the <xref target="messages_ibf_structure" format="title" /> of
                  the message <xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /> with a different "MSG TYPE"
                  which is defined in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> "SETU_P2P_IBF_LAST".
                </t>
              </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_elements" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Element</name>

                <section anchor="messages_elements_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message contains an element that is synchronized in the <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" />
                        and transmits a full element between the peers.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This message is sent in the state <strong>Active Decoding</strong> and <strong>Passive Decoding</strong>
                        as answer to a <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message from the remote peer.
                        The <em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message can also be received in the <strong>Finish Closing</strong> or <strong>Finish Waiting</strong>
                        state after receiving a <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message from the remote peer. In this
                        case the peer changes to the <strong>Finished</strong> state as soon as all demands for elements have been satisfied.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This message is exclusively used in the <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" />.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_elements_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_elements">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |   E TYPE  |  PADDING  |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |   E SIZE  |              DATA
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is SETU_P2P_ELEMENTS as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>E TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer which defines the element type for
                            the application.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>PADDING</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is 16-bit always set to zero.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>E SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer that signals the size of the elements data part.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>DATA</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a field with variable length that contains the data of the element.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_offer" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Offer</name>

                <section anchor="messages_offer_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message is an answer to an <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> message
                        and transmits the full hash of an element that has been requested by the other peer.
                        This full hash enables the other peer to check if the element is really missing in his set and
                        eventually sends a <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message for that element.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The offer is sent and received only in the <strong>Active Decoding</strong> and in the <strong>Passive Decoding</strong>
                        state.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This message is exclusively sent in the <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" />.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_offer_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_offer">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |         HASH 1
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
       ...                                             ...
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
                 HASH 1         |         HASH 2
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
       ...                                             ...
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
                 HASH 2         |         HASH n
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes header included.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is SETU_P2P_OFFER as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>HASH n</dt>
                        <dd>
                            contains n (one or more) successive SHA 512-bit hashes of the elements that are being requested with <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> messages.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>


            <section anchor="messages_inquiry" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Inquiry</name>

                <section anchor="messages_inquiry_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> message is exclusively sent by the active peer in <strong>Active Decoding</strong> state
                        to request the full hash of an element that is missing in the active peers set. This is normally answered
                        by the passive peer with <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This message is exclusively sent in the <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" />.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_inquiry_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_inquiry">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |          SALT         |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                   IBF KEY 1                   |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                   IBF KEY 2                   |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        ...                                            ...
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                   IBF KEY n                   |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is SETU_P2P_INQUIRY as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>IBF KEY</dt>
                        <dd>
                            contains n (one or more) successive ibf keys (64-bit unsigned integer) for which the inquiry is sent.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_demand" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Demand</name>

                <section anchor="messages_demand_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message is sent in the <strong>Active Decoding</strong> and in the <strong>Passive Decoding</strong>
                        state. It is an answer to a received <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message
                        and is sent if the element described in the <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message
                        is missing in the peers set. In the normal workflow the answer to the <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message is an
                        <em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This message is exclusively sent in the <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" />.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_demand_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_demand">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |         HASH 1
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
       ...                                             ...
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
                 HASH 1         |         HASH 2
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
       ...                                             ...
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
                 HASH 2         |         HASH n
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes and the header is included.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            the type of SETU_P2P_DEMAND as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>HASH n</dt>
                        <dd>
                            contains n (one or more) successive SHA 512-bit hashes of the elements that are being demanded.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_done" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Done</name>

                <section anchor="messages_done_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message is sent when all <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> messages
                        have been successfully satisfied and from the perspective of the sender the set is completely synchronized.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This message is exclusively sent in the <xref target="modeofoperation_individual-elements" format="title" />.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_done_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_done">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |    FINAL CHECKSUM
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /

                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included. The value is always 4 for this message type.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is SETU_P2P_DONE as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>FINAL CHECKSUM</dt>
                        <dd>
                            a SHA-512 hash XOR sum of the full set after synchronization. This should ensure that the sets are identical in the end!
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_full_done" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Full Done</name>

                <section anchor="messages_full_done_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message is sent in the <xref target="modeofoperation_full-sync" format="title" />
                        to signal that all remaining elements of the set have been sent. The message is received and sent in the
                        <strong>Full Sending</strong> and in the <strong>Full Receiving</strong> state. When the <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message is received
                        in <strong>Full Sending</strong> state the peer changes directly into <strong>Finished</strong> state. In
                        <strong>Full Receiving</strong> state receiving a <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message initiates the sending of
                        the remaining elements that are missing in the set of the other peer.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_full_done_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_full_done">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |     FINAL CHECKSUM
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included. The value is always 4 for this message type.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            the type of SETU_P2P_FULL_DONE as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt> FINAL CHECKSUM</dt>
                        <dd>
                            a SHA-512 hash XOR sum of the full set after synchronization. This should ensure that the sets are identical in the end!
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_request_full" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Request Full</name>

                <section anchor="messages_request_full_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_request_full" format="title" /></em> message is sent by the initiating peer in <strong>Expect SE</strong> state to the receiving peer, if
                        the operation mode "<xref target="modeofoperation_full-sync" format="title" />" is
                        determined to be the superior <xref target="modeofoperation" format="title" /> and that it is the better choice that
                       the other peer sends his elements first. The initiating peer changes after sending the <em><xref target="messages_request_full" format="title" /></em> message into
                        <strong>Full Receiving</strong> state.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The receiving peer receives the <em><xref target="messages_request_full" format="title" /></em> message in the <strong>Expecting IBF</strong>, afterwards the receiving peer
                        starts sending his complete set in <xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" /> messages to the initiating peer.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_request_full_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_request_full">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |    REMOTE SET DIFF    |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |   REMOTE SET SIZE     |    LOCAL SET DIFF     |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included. The value is always 16 for this message type.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is SETU_P2P_REQUEST_FULL as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>REMOTE SET DIFF</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 32-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which represents the remote (from the perspective of the
                            sending peer) set difference calculated with strata estimator.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>REMOTE SET SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 32-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which represents the total remote
                            (from the perspective of the sending peer) set size.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>LOCAL SET DIFF</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 32-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which represents the local
                            (from the perspective of the sending peer) set difference calculated with strata estimator.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>


            <section anchor="messages_send_full" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Send Full</name>

                <section anchor="messages_send_full_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_send_full" format="title" /></em> message is sent by the initiating peer in <strong>Expect SE</strong> state to the receiving peer if
                        the operation mode "<xref target="modeofoperation_full-sync" format="title" />" is
                        determined as superior <xref target="modeofoperation" format="title" /> and that it is the better choice that the
                        peer sends his elements first. The initiating peer changes after sending the <em><xref target="messages_request_full" format="title" /></em> message into
                        <strong>Full Sending</strong> state.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The receiving peer receives the <em><xref target="messages_send_full" format="title" /></em> message in the <strong>Expecting IBF</strong> state, afterwards the receiving peer
                        changes into <strong>Full Receiving</strong> state and expects to receive the set of the remote peer.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_send_full_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_send_full">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |    REMOTE SET DIFF    |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |   REMOTE SET SIZE     |    LOCAL SET DIFF     |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included.  The value is always 16 for this message type.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is SETU_P2P_REQUEST_FULL as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>REMOTE SET DIFF</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 32-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which represents the remote (from the perspective of the sending peer)
                            set difference calculated with strata estimator.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>REMOTE SET SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 32-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which represents the total remote (from the perspective
                            of the sending peer) set size.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>LOCAL SET DIFF</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 32-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which represents the local (from the perspective of the sending peer)
                            set difference calculated with strata estimator.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>


            <section anchor="messages_se" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Strata Estimator</name>

                <section anchor="messages_se_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The strata estimator is sent by the receiving peer at the start of the protocol, right after the
                        <xref target="messages_operation_request" format="title" /> message has been received.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The strata estimator is used to estimate the difference between the two sets as described in section <xref target="se" format="title" />.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        When the initiating peer receives the strata estimator, the peer decides which <xref target="modeofoperation" format="title" /> to use
                        for the synchronisation. Depending on the size of the set difference and the <xref target="modeofoperation" format="title" /> the initiating peer
                        changes into <strong>Full Sending</strong>, <strong>Full Receiving</strong> or <strong>Passive Decoding</strong> state.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_se" format="title" /></em> message can contain one, two, four or eight strata estimators with different salts, depending on the initial size of the sets.
                        More details can be found in section <xref target="performance_multi_se" format="title" />.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The IBFs in a strata estimator always have 79 buckets. The reason why can be found in <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/> in section 3.4.2.
                    </t>
                    <!-- Give a more precise reference into the thesis for this, do not cite the whole thesis! -->
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_se_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Structure</name>
                    <figure anchor="figure_se">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE | SEC |     SETSIZE
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
              SETSIZE                 |     SE-SLICES
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is SETU_P2P_SE as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>SEC</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 8-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which indicates how many strata estimators
                            with different salts are attached to the message. Valid values are 1,2,4 or 8, more details can be found
                            in the section <xref target="performance_multi_se" format="title" />.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>SETSIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 64-bit unsigned integer that is defined by the size of the set the SE is
                        </dd>
                        <dt>SE-SLICES</dt>
                        <dd>
                            <t>
                                are variable numbers of slices in an array. A slice can contain one or more Strata Estimators which
                                contain multiple IBFs as described in IBF-SLICES in <xref target="messages_ibf_structure" format="default"/>.
                                A SE slice can contain one to eight Strata Estimators which contain 32 (Defined as Constant SE_STRATA_COUNT) IBFs. Every IBF in
                                a SE contains 79 Buckets.
                            </t>
                            <t>
                                The different SEs are built as in detail described in <xref target="performance_multi_se" format="default"/>.
                                Simply put, the IBFs in each SE are serialized as described in <xref target="messages_ibf_structure" format="default"/> starting with the highest stratum.
                                Then the created SEs are appended one after the other starting with the SE that was created with a salt of zero.

                            </t>
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                    <figure anchor="figure_se_slice">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
                             SE-SLICE
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                  SE_1 -> IBF_1
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
       ...                                             ...
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                  SE_1 -> IBF_30
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |                  SE_2 -> IBF_1
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
       ...                                             ...
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_sec" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Strata Estimator Compressed</name>

              <section anchor="messages_sec_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Description</name>
                <t>
                  The Strata Estimator can be compressed with gzip as
                  described in <xref target="RFC1951"/> to improve performance. This can be recognized
                  by the different message type number from <xref target="gana" format="title" />.
                </t>
                <section anchor="messages_sec_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                      <name>Structure</name>
                        <t>
                            The key difference between the compressed and the uncompressed Strata Estimator is that the
                            SE slices are compressed with gzip (<xref target="RFC1951"/>) in the compressed SE.
                            But the header remains uncompressed with both.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Since the content of the message is the same as the uncompressed Strata Estimator, the details
                            are not repeated here. For details see section <xref target="messages_se" format="counter" />.
                        </t>
                </section>
              </section>
            </section>

            <section anchor="messages_full_element" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Full Element</name>

                <section anchor="messages_full_element_description" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Description</name>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" /></em> message is the equivalent of the <xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /> message in
                        the <xref target="modeofoperation_full-sync" format="title" />. It contains a complete element that is missing
                        in the set of the peer that receives this message.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The <em><xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" /></em> message is exclusively sent in the transitions <strong>Expecting IBF</strong> -> <strong>Full Receiving</strong> and
                        <strong>Full Receiving</strong> -> <strong>Finished</strong>. The message is only received in the <strong> Full Sending</strong> and
                        <strong>Full Receiving</strong> state.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        After the last <em><xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" /></em> message has been sent, the <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message
                        is sent to conclude the full synchronisation of the element sending peer.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="messages_full_element_structure" numbered="true" toc="default">
                  <name>Structure</name>
                  <!-- MAYBE just refer to the "ELEMENT" section on structure and only
                       note the different MSG TYPE here? -->
                    <figure anchor="figure_full_element">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
        0     8     16    24    32    40    48    56
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |  MSG SIZE |  MSG TYPE |   E TYPE  |  PADDING  |
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        |    SIZE   |   AE TYPE |          DATA
        +-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+-----+
        /                                               /
        /                                               /
                 ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    <t>where:</t>
                    <dl>
                        <dt>MSG SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer in network byte order, which describes the message size in bytes with the header included.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>MSG TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is SETU_P2P_REQUEST_FULL_ELEMENT as registered in <xref target="gana" format="title" /> in network byte order.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>E TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer which defines the element type for
                            the application.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>PADDING</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is 16-bit always set to zero
                        </dd>
                        <dt>E SIZE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer that signals the size of the elements data part.
                        </dd>
                        <dt>AE TYPE</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a 16-bit unsigned integer that is needed to identify
                            the type of element that is in the data field
                        </dd>
                        <dt>DATA</dt>
                        <dd>
                            is a field with variable length that contains the data of the element.
                        </dd>
                    </dl>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="performance" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Performance Considerations</name>
            <section anchor="performance_formulas" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Formulas</name>
                <section anchor="performance_formulas_operationmode" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Operation Mode</name>
                    <t>
                        The decision which <xref target="modeofoperation" format="title"/> is used is described by the following code.
                        More detailed explanations motivating the design can be found in the accompanying thesis in section 4.5.3.<xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The function takes as input the average element size, the local set size, the remote set size, the set differences as estimated from the strata estimator for both the local and remote sets,
                        and the bandwidth/roundtrip tradeoff.
                        The function returns the exact <xref target="modeofoperation" format="title"/> that is predicted to be best as output: FULL_SYNC_REMOTE_SENDING_FIRST
                        if it is likely cheapest that the other peer transmits his elements first, FULL_SYNC_LOCAL_SENDING_FIRST
                        if it is likely cheapest that the elements are transmitted to the other peer directly, and
                        DIFFERENTIAL_SYNC if the differential synchronisation is likely cheapest.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                      The constant IBF_BUCKET_NUMBER_FACTOR is always 2 and IBF_MIN_SIZE is 37.
                      The method for deriving
                        this can be found in the IBF parameter study in <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/> in section 4.5.2.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="performance_formulas_operationmode_code">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
# CONSTANTS:
# IBF_BUCKET_NUMBER_FACTOR = 2: The amount the IBF gets increased if
#                               decoding fails
# RTT_MIN_FULL = 2: Minimal round trips used for full Synchronisation
# IBF_MIN_SIZE = 37: The minimal size of an IBF
# MAX_BUCKETS_PER_MESSAGE: Custom value depending on the underlying
#                          protocol
# INPUTS:
# avg_es: The average element size
# lss: The initial local set size
# rss: The remote set size
# lsd: the estimated local set difference calculated by the SE
# rsd: the estimated remote set difference calculated by the SE
# rtt: the tradeoff between round trips and bandwidth
# OUTPUT:
# FULL_SYNC_REMOTE_SENDING_FIRST, FULL_SYNC_LOCAL_SENDING_FIRST or
# DIFFERENTIAL_SYNC

FUNCTION decide_operation_mode(avg_es,
                               lss,
                               rss,
                               lsd
                               rsd,
                               rtt)

    # If a set size is zero always do full sync
    IF 0 == rss THEN
        RETURN FULL_SYNC_LOCAL_SENDING_FIRST
    END IF
    IF 0 == lss THEN
        RETURN FULL_SYNC_REMOTE_SENDING_FIRST
    END IF

    # Estimate required transferred bytes when doing a full
    # synchronisation and transmitting local set first.
    semh = sizeof(ELEMENT_MSG_HEADER)
    estimated_total_diff = rsd + lsd
    total_elements_local_send = rsd + lss
    cost_local_full_sync = avg_es * total_elements_local_send
                           + total_elements_local_send * semh
                           + sizeof(FULL_DONE_MSG_HEADER) * 2
                           + RTT_MIN_FULL * rtt

    # Estimate required transferred bytes when doing a full
    # synchronisation and transmitting remote set first.
    total_elements_remote_send = lsd + rss
    cost_remote_full_sync = avg_es * total_elements_remote_send
                            + total_elements_remote_send * semh
                            + sizeof(FULL_DONE_MSG_HEADER) * 2
                            + (RTT_MIN_FULL + 0.5) * rtt
                            + sizeof(REQUEST_FULL_MSG)

    # Estimate required transferred bytes when doing a differential
    #  synchronisation

    # Estimate messages required to transfer IBF
    ibf_bucket_count = estimated_total_diff * IBF_BUCKET_NUMBER_FACTOR
    IF ibf_bucket_count <= IBF_MIN_SIZE THEN
        ibf_bucket_count = IBF_MIN_SIZE
    END IF
    ibf_message_count = ceil (ibf_bucket_count / MAX_BUCKETS_PER_MESSAGE)

    # Estimate average counter length with variable counter
    estimated_counter_bits = MIN (2 * LOG2(lss / ibf_bucket_count),
                                  LOG2(lss))
    estimated_counter_bytes = estimated_counter_bits / 8

    # Sum up all messages required to do differential synchronisation
    ibf_bytes = sizeof(IBF_MESSAGE) * ibf_message_count
              + ibf_bucket_count * sizeof(IBF_KEY)
              + ibf_bucket_count * sizeof(IBF_KEYHASH)
              + ibf_bucket_count * estimated_counter_bytes
    # Add 20% overhead to cover IBF retries due to decoding failures
    total_ibf_bytes = ibf_bytes * 1.2

    # Estimate other message sizes to be transfered in diff sync
    # Note that we simplify by adding the header each time;
    # if the implementation combines multiple INQUIRY/DEMAND/OFFER
    # requests in one message, the bandwidth would be lower.
    done_size = sizeof(DONE_HEADER)
    element_size = (avg_es + sizeof(ELEMENT_MSG_HEADER))
                 * estimated_total_diff
    inquery_size = (sizeof(IBF_KEY) + sizeof(INQUERY_MSG_HEADER))
                 * estimated_total_diff
    demand_size  = (sizeof(HASHCODE) + sizeof(DEMAND_MSG_HEADER))
                 * estimated_total_diff
    offer_size   = (sizeof(HASHCODE) + sizeof(OFFER_MSG_HEADER))
                 * estimated_total_diff

    # Estimate total cost
    diff_cost = element_size + done_size + inquery_size
              + demand_size + offer_size + total_ibf_bytes
              + DIFFERENTIAL_RTT_MEAN * rtt

    # Decide for a optimal mode of operation
    full_cost_min = MIN (cost_local_full_sync,
                         cost_remote_full_sync)
    IF full_cost_min < diff_cost THEN
        IF cost_remote_full_sync > cost_local_full_sync THEN
            RETURN FULL_SYNC_LOCAL_SENDING_FIRST
        ELSE
            RETURN FULL_SYNC_REMOTE_SENDING_FIRST
        END IF
    ELSE
        RETURN DIFFERENTIAL_SYNC
    END IF
END FUNCTION
    ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section anchor="performance_formula_ibf_parameters" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>IBF Size</name>
                    <t>
                        The functions, described in this section, calculate a good initial size (initial_ibf_size)
                        and in case of decoding failure, a good next IBF size (get_next_ibf_size).
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        These algorithms are described and justified in more details in
                        <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/> in the parameter study in
                        section 3.5.2, the max IBF counter in section 3.10 and the Improved IBF size in section 3.11.
                    </t>
                    <figure anchor="performance_formula_ibf_parameters_code">
                        <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
# CONSTANTS:
# IBF_BUCKET_NUMBER_FACTOR = 2: The amount the IBF gets increased
                                if decoding fails
# Inputs:
# sd: Estimated set difference
# Output:
# next_size: Size of the initial IBF

FUNCTION initial_ibf_size(sd)
    # We do not go below 37, as 37 buckets should
    # basically always be below one MTU, so there is
    # little to be gained, while a smaller IBF would
    # increase the chance of a decoding failure.
    RETURN MAX(37, IBF_BUCKET_NUMBER_FACTOR * sd);
END FUNCTION

# CONSTANTS:
# IBF_BUCKET_NUMBER_FACTOR = 2: The amount the IBF gets increased if
#                               decoding fails
# Inputs:
# de: Number of elements that have been successfully decoded
# lis: The number of buckets of the last IBF
# Output:
# number of buckets for the next IBF

FUNCTION get_next_ibf_size(de, lis)
    next_size = IBF_BUCKET_NUMBER_FACTOR * (lis - de)
    # The MAX operation here also ensures that the
    # result is positive.
    RETURN MAX(37, next_size);
END FUNCTION
                        ]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                </section>
                <section anchor="performance_num_buck_hash" numbered="true" toc="default">
                    <name>Number of Buckets an Element is Hashed into</name>
                    <t>
                        The number of buckets an element is hashed to is hardcoded to 3. Reasoning and
                        justification can be found in
                        <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/> in the
                        IBF parameter performance study in section 4.5.2.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section anchor="performance_counter_variable_size" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Variable Counter Size</name>
                <t>
                  The number of bits required to represent the counters of an IBF varies
                  due to different parameters as described in section 3.2 of
                  <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/>.
                  Therefore, a packing algorithm has been implemented.
                  This algorithm encodes the IBF counters in their optimal bit-width
                  and thus minimizes the bandwidth needed to transmit the IBF.
                </t>
                <t>
                  A simple algorithm is used for the packing.
                  In a first step it is determined, which is the largest counter.
                  The the base 2 logarithm then determines how many bits are needed to store it.
                  In a second step for every counter of every bucket, the counter
                  is stored using this many bits. The resulting bit sequence is then simply concatenated.
                </t>
                <t>
                  Three individual functions are used for this purpose.
                  The first one is a function that iterates over each bucket of
                  the IBF to get the maximum counter in the IBF. The second function
                  packs the counters of the IBF, and the third function that unpacks the counters.
                </t>
                <t>
                    As a plausibly check to prevent the byzantine upper bound
                    checks in <xref target="security_generic_functions_check_byzantine_boundaries" format="default"/>
                    to fail, implementations must ensure that the
                    estimates of the set size difference added together
                    never exceed the set byzantine upper bound. This
                    could for example happen in case the strata estimator
                    overestimates the set difference.
                </t>
                <figure anchor="performance_counter_variable_size_code">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[

# INPUTS:
# ibf: The IBF
# OUTPUTS:
# returns: Minimal amount of bits required to store the counter

FUNCTION ibf_get_max_counter(ibf)
    max_counter=1 # convince static analysis that we never take log2(0)
    FOR bucket IN ibf DO
        IF bucket.counter > max_counter THEN
            max_counter = bucket.counter
        END IF
    END FOR
    # next bigger discrete number of the binary logarithm of the
    # max counter
    RETURN CEILING( LOG2( max_counter ) )
END FUNCTION

# INPUTS:
# ibf: The IBF
# offset: The offset which defines the starting point from which bucket
#         the pack operation starts
# count: The number of buckets in the array that will be packed
# OUTPUTS:
# returns: A byte array of packed counters to send over the network

# INPUTS:
# ibf: The IBF
# offset: The offset which defines the starting point from which bucket
#         the pack operation starts
# count: The number of buckets in the array that will be packed
# OUTPUTS:
# returns: A byte array of packed counters to send over the network

FUNCTION pack_counter(ibf, offset, count)
    counter_bytes = ibf_get_max_counter(ibf)
    store_bits = 0
    store = 0
    byte_ctr = 0
    buf=[]

    FOR bucket IN ibf[offset] TO ibf[count] DO
        counter = bucket.counter
        byte_len = counter_bytes

        WHILE byte_len + store_bits < 8 DO
            bit_to_shift = 0

            IF store_bits > 0 OR byte_len > 8 THEN
                bit_free = 8 - store_bits
                bit_to_shift = byte_len - bit_free
                store = store << bit_free
            END IF
            buf[byte_ctr] = (( counter >> bit_to_shift) | store) & 0xFF
            byte_ctr = byte_ctr + 1
            byte_len -= 8 - store_bits
            counter = counter & ((1 << byte_len) - 1)
            store = 0
            store_bits = 0
        END WHILE
        store = (store << byte_len) | counter
        store_bits = store_bits + byte_len
        byte_len = 0
    END FOR

    # Write the last partial packed byte to the buffer
    IF store_bits > 0 THEN
        buf[byte_ctr] = store << (8 - store_bits)
        byte_ctr = byte_ctr + 1
    END IF

    RETURN buf
FUNCTION END

# INPUTS:
# ibf: The IBF
# offset: The offset which defines the starting point from which bucket
          the packed operation starts
# count: The number of buckets in the array that will be packed
# cbl: The bit length of the counter can be found in the
       ibf message in the ibf_counter_bit_length field
# pd: A byte array which contains the data packed with the pack_counter
      function
# OUTPUTS:
# returns: Nothing because the unpacked counter is saved directly
           into the IBF

FUNCTION unpack_counter(ibf, offset, count, cbl, pd)
    ibf_bucket_ctr = 0
    store = 0
    store_bits = 0
    byte_ctr = 0

    WHILE TRUE
        byte_read = pd[byte_ctr]
        bit_to_pack_left = 8
        byte_ctr++

        WHILE bit_to_pack_left >= 0 DO

            # Prevent packet from reading more than required
            IF ibf_bucket_ctr > (count - 1) THEN
                RETURN
            END IF

            IF store_bits + bit_to_pack_left >= cbl THEN
                bit_use = cbl - store_bits

                IF store_bits > 0 THEN
                    store = store << bit_use
                END IF
                bytes_to_shift = bit_to_pack_left - bit_use
                counter_partial = byte_read >> bytes_to_shift
                store = store | counter_partial
                ibf.counter[ibf_bucket_ctr + offset] = store
                byte_read = byte_read & (( 1 << bytes_to_shift ) - 1)

                bit_to_pack_left -= bit_use
                ibf_bucket_ctr++
                store = 0
                store_bits = 0
            ELSE
                store_bits = store_bits + bit_to_pack_left

                IF 0 == store_bits THEN
                    store = byte_read
                ELSE
                    store = store << bit_to_pack_left
                    store = store | byte_read
                END IF
                BREAK
            END IF
        END WHILE
    END WHILE
END FUNCTION
                                    ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section anchor="performance_multi_se" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Multi Strata Estimators</name>
                <t>
                    In order to improve the precision of the estimates not only one strata estimator
                    is transmitted for larger sets. One, two, four or eight strata estimators can be
                    transferred. Transmitting multiple strata estimators has the disadvantage that
                    additional bandwidth will be used, so despite the higher precision, it is not
                    always optimal to transmit eight strata estimators. Therefore, the following
                    rules are used, which are based on the average element size multiplied by the number
                    of elements in the set. This value is denoted as "b" in the table:
                </t>
                <dl>
                    <dt>SEs</dt>
                    <dd>Rule</dd>
                    <dt>1</dt>
                    <dd>b &lt; 68kb</dd>
                    <dt>2</dt>
                    <dd>b &gt; 68kb</dd>
                    <dt>4</dt>
                    <dd>b &gt; 269kb</dd>
                    <dt>8</dt>
                    <dd>b &gt; 1'077kb</dd>
                </dl>
                <t>
                    When creating multiple strata estimators, it is important to salt the keys for the IBFs in the strata
                    estimators differently, using the following bit rotation based salting method:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="performance_multi_se_salting_code">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[

# Inputs:
# value: Input value to salt (needs to be 64 bit unsigned)
# salt: Salt to salt value with; Should always be ascending and start
#       at zero
    i.e. SE1 = Salt 0; SE2 = Salt 1 etc.
# Output:
# Returns: Salted value

FUNCTION se_key_salting(value, salt)
    s = (salt * 7) modulo 64
    RETURN (value >> s) | (value << (64 - s))
END FUNCTION

                                    ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    Performance study and details about the reasoning for the used methods can be found in <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/> in section
                    3.4.1 under the title "Added Support for Multiple Strata Estimators".
                    <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>


    <section anchor="security" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Security Considerations</name>
        <t>
            The security considerations in this document focus mainly on the security
            goal of availability. The primary goal of the protocol is to prevent an attacker from
            wasting computing and network resources of the attacked peer.
        </t>
        <t>
            To prevent denial of service attacks, it is vital to check that peers can only
            reconcile a set once in a predefined time span. This is a predefined value and needs
            to be adapted per use basis. To enhance reliability and to allow
            for legitimate failures, say due to network connectivity issues,
            applications SHOULD define a threshold for
            the maximum number of failed reconciliation attempts in a given time period.
        </t>
        <t>
            It is important to close and purge connections after a given timeout
            to prevent draining attacks.
        </t>
        <section anchor="security_generic_functions" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>General Security Checks</name>
            <t>
               In this section general checks are described which should be applied to multiple states.
            </t>

            <section anchor="security_generic_input_validation" numbered="true" toc="default">
              <name>Input validation</name>
              <t>
                The format of all received messages needs to be properly validated. This is important to prevent many
                attacks on the code. The application data MUST be validated by the application using
                the protocol not by the implementation of the protocol.
                In case the format validation fails the set operation MUST be terminated.
              </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="security_generic_functions_check_byzantine_boundaries" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Byzantine Boundaries</name>
                <t>
                    To restrict an attacker there should be an upper and lower bound defined and checked
                    at the beginning of the protocol, based
                    on prior knowledge, for the number of elements.
                    The lower byzantine bound can be, for example, the number of elements the
                    other peer had in his set at the last contact.
                    The upper byzantine bound can be a practical maximum e.g. the number
                    of e-voting votes, in Switzerland.
                </t>
                <figure anchor="security_generic_functions_missing_message_code">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
# Input:
# rec: Number of elements in remote set
# rsd: Number of elements differ in remote set
# lec: Number of elements in local set
# lsd: Number of elements differ in local set
# UPPER_BOUND: Given byzantine upper bound
# LOWER_BOUND: Given byzantine lower bound
# Output:
# returns TRUE if parameters in byzantine bounds otherwise returns FALSE
FUNCTION check_byzantine_bounds (rec,rsd,lec,lsd)
    IF rec + rsd > UPPER_BOUND THEN
        RETURN FALSE
    END IF
    IF lec + lsd > UPPER_BOUND THEN
        RETURN FALSE
    END IF
    IF rec < LOWER_BOUND THEN
        RETURN FALSE
    END IF
    RETURN TRUE
END FUNCTION
                    ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>

            <section anchor="security_generic_functions_check_valid_state" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Valid State</name>
                <t>
                    To harden the protocol against attacks, controls were introduced in the improved
                    implementation that check for each message whether the message was received
                    in the correct state. This is central so that an attacker finds as little attack
                    surface as possible and makes it more difficult for the attacker to send the
                    protocol into an endless loop, for example.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="security_generic_functions_mfc" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Message Flow Control</name>
                <t>
                    For most messages received and sent there needs to be a check in place that checks
                    that a message is not received multiple times. This is solved with a global store (message)
                    and the following code
                </t>
                <t>
                    The sequence in which messages are received and sent is arranged in a chain.
                    The messages are dependent on each other. There are dependencies that are
                    mandatory, e.g. for a sent "Demand" message, an "Element" message must
                    always be received. But there are also messages for which a response is
                    not mandatory, e.g. the <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> message is only followed by an
                    "Offer" message, if the corresponding element is in the set. Due to this
                    fact, checks can be installed to verify compliance with the following chain.
                </t>
                <figure anchor="security_generic_functions_mfc_chain">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[


Chain for
elements    +---------+    +---------+    +---------+    +---------+
NOT in IBF  | INQUIRY |--->|  OFFER  |===>|  DEMAND |===>| ELEMENT |
decoding    +---------+    +---------+    +---------+    +---------+
peers set

Chain for
elements    +---------+    +---------+    +---------+
in IBF      |  OFFER  |--->| DEMAND  |===>| ELEMENT |
decoding    +---------+    +---------+    +---------+
peers set

            --->: Answer not mandatory
            ===>: Always answer needed.
                    ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    In the message control flow its important to ensure that no duplicated messages are received
                    (Except inquiries where collisions are possible) and only messages are received which are compliant
                    with the flow in <xref target="security_generic_functions_mfc_chain" format="default" />.
                    To link messages the SHA-512 element hashes, that are part of all messages, except in the
                    <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> messages, can be used.
                    To link an <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> message to an
                    <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message
                    the SHA-512 hash from the offer has to be salted and converted to the IBF-Key (as described in
                    <xref target="ibf_format_id_generation_pseudo_code" format="default" />). The IBF-Key can
                    be matched with the received <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> message.
                </t>
                <t>
                    At the end of the set reconciliation operation after receiving and sending the
                    <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message, it should be checked
                    that all demands have been satisfied and all elements have been received.
                </t>
                <t>
                    This is based on <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/>, section 5.3 (Message Control Flow).
                </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="security_generic_functions_active_passive_switches" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Limit Active/Passive Decoding changes</name>
                <t>
                  To prevent an attacker from sending a peer into an endless loop between active and passive decoding, a
                  limitation for active/passive roll switches is required.
                  Otherwise, an attacker could
                  force the victim to waste unlimited amount of resources by just transmitting
                  IBFs that do not decode.
                  This can be implemented by
                  a simple counter which terminates the operation after a predefined number of switches.
                  The maximum number of switches needs to be defined in such a way that it is
                  very improbable that more switches are required in a legitimate interaction,
                  and hence the malicious behavior of the other peer is assured.
                </t>
                <t>
                  The question after how many active/passive switches it can be assumed that the other peer is not honest,
                  depends on the various tuning parameters of the algorithm.
                  Section 5.4 of <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/>
                  demonstrates that the probability of decoding failure is less than
                  15% for each round. The probability that there will be n legitimate
                  active/passive changes is thus less than 0.15^{round number}.
                  Which means that after about 30 active/passive switches it can be said with a certainty of 2^80 that one of the peers
                  is not following the protocol.
                  Hence, participants MUST impose a maximum of 30 active/passive changes.
                </t>
            </section>

            <section anchor="security_generic_functions_full_plausibility_check" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Full Synchronisation Plausibility Check</name>
                <t>
                    An attacker can try to use up a peer's bandwidth by pretending that the peer
                    needs full synchronisation, even if the set difference is very small and the attacker
                    only has a few (or even zero) elements that are not already synchronised.
                    In such a case, it would be ideal if the plausibility could already be checked
                    during full synchronisation as to whether the other peer was honest or not with
                    regard to the estimation of the set size difference and thus the choice of mode
                    of operation.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In order to calculate this plausibility, section 5.5 of <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/> describes a formula, which depicts the probability with which one
                    can calculate the corresponding plausibility based on the number of
                    new and repeated elements after each received element.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Besides this approach from probability theory, there is an additional check
                    that can be made. After the entire set has been transferred to the other peer,
                    no known elements may be returned by the second peer, since the second peer
                    should only return the elements that are missing from the initial peer's set.
                </t>
                <t>
                    This two approaches are implemented in the following pseudocode:
                </t>

                <figure anchor="security_generic_functions_full_plausibility_check_code">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
# Input:
# SECURITY_LEVEL: The security level used e.g. 2^80
# state: The statemachine state
# rs: Estimated remote set difference
# lis: Number of elements in set
# rd: Number of duplicated elements received
# rf: Number of fresh elements received
# Output:
# Returns TRUE if full synchronisation is plausible and FALSE otherwise

FUNCTION full_sync_plausibility_check (state,rs,lis,rd,rf)
    security_level_lb = -1 * SECURITY_LEVEL

    # Make sure that no element is received double when
    # all elements already are transmitted to the oder side.
    IF FULL_SENDING == state AND rd > 0 THEN
        RETURN FALSE
    END IF

    # Probabilistic algorithm to check for plausible
    # element distribution
    IF FULL_RECEIVING == state THEN

        # Prevent division by 0
        IF  0 <= rs THEN
            rs = 1
        END IF

        # Formula to verify plausibility
        base = 1 - (rs / (lis + rs))
        exponent = rd - rf * lis / rs
        value = exponent * (LOG2(base)/LOG2(2))
        IF value < security_level_lb OR value > SECURITY_LEVEL THEN
            RETURN FALSE
        END IF
    END IF
    RETURN TRUE
END FUNCTION
                    ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>
    </section>

        <section anchor="security_states" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>States</name>

            <t>
                In this section the security considerations for each valid message
                in all states is described, if any other message
                is received the peer MUST terminate the operation.
            </t>

            <section anchor="security_states_expecting_ibf" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Expecting IBF</name>
                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_request_full" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                        It needs to be checked that the full synchronisation mode with receiving peer
                        sending first is plausible according to the algorithm deciding which operation mode
                        is applicable as described in <xref target="performance_formulas_operationmode" format="default"/>.
                        </t>

                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            It needs to be checked that the differential synchronisation mode is plausible according
                            to the algorithm deciding which operation mode
                            is applicable as described in <xref target="performance_formulas_operationmode" format="default"/>.
                        </t>

                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_send_full" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            It needs to be checked that the full synchronisation mode with initiating peer
                            sending first is plausible according to the algorithm deciding which operation mode
                            is applicable as described in <xref target="performance_formulas_operationmode" format="default"/>.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>

            <section anchor="security_states_full_sending" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Full Sending</name>
                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                      <t>
                        When receiving full elements there needs to be checked, that every
                        element is a valid element, that no element has been received more than once, and
                        that not more elements have been received than the other peer has committed
                        to at the beginning of the operation. The plausibility should also be checked
                        with an algorithm as described in <xref target="security_generic_functions_full_plausibility_check" format="default"/>.
                      </t>
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                      <t>
                        When receiving the <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em>
                        message, it is important to check that
                        not fewer elements have been received than the other peer has committed to
                        send at the beginning of the operation.
                        If the sets differ (the FINAL CHECKSUM field in the <xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" />
                        message does not match to the SHA-512 hash XOR sum of the local set), the operation has failed and the
                        reconciliation MUST be aborted. It is a strong indicator
                        that something went wrong (eg. some hardware bug). This should never occur!
                      </t>
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>

            <section anchor="security_states_expecting_ibf_last" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Expecting IBF Last</name>
                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                          The application should check that the overall size of the IBF
                          that is being transmitted is within its resource bounds, and
                          abort the protocol if its resource limits are likely to be
                          exceeded, or if the size is implausible for the given operation.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                          It needs to be checked that the offset (message field "OFFSET")
                          for every received <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em> message
                          is strictly monotonic increasing and is a multiple of the MAX_BUCKETS_PER_MESSAGE
                          defined in the <xref target="constants" format="title" /> section, otherwise the
                          connection MUST be aborted.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                          Another sanity check is to ensure that the "OFFSET" message field never
                          is higher than the "IBF SIZE" field in the <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em>
                          message.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_ibf_last" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            When all <em><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></em> messages have
                            been received an <em><xref target="messages_ibf_last" format="title" /></em> message
                            should conclude the transmission of the IBF and a change to the <strong>Active Decoding</strong>
                            phase should be ensured.
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            To verify that all IBFs have been received, a simple validation can be made.
                            The number of buckets in the <em><xref target="messages_ibf_last" format="title" /></em> message
                            added to the value in the message OFFSET field should always be equal to the "IBF SIZE".
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            Further plausibility checks can be made. One is to ensure that after each active/passive
                            switch the IBF can never be more than double in size. Another plausibility check is
                            that an IBF probably never will be larger than the byzantine upperbound multiplied by two.
                            The third plausibility check is to take successfully decoded IBF keys (received offers and demands)
                            into account and to validate the size of the received IBF with the in <xref target="performance_formula_ibf_parameters_code" format="default" />
                            described function get_next_ibf_size(). If any of these three checks fail the operation
                            must be aborted.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>

            <section anchor="security_states_active_decoding" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Active Decoding</name>
                <t>
                    In the <strong>Active Decoding</strong> state it is important to prevent an attacker from
                    generating and transmitting an unlimited number of IBFs that all do not decode, or
                    to generate an IBF constructed to send the peers in an endless loop.
                    To prevent an endless loop in decoding, loop detection MUST be implemented.
                    A solution to prevent endless loop is to limit the number of elements decoded from an IBF.
                    This limit is defined by the number of buckets in the IBF. It is not possible that more elements are decoded
                    from an IBF than an IBF has buckets. If more elements than buckets are in an IBF it is not possible to
                    get pure buckets.
                    An additional check that should be implemented, is to store all element IDs
                    that were prior decoded. When a new element ID is decoded from the IBF it should
                    always be checked that no element ID is repeated.
                    If the same element ID is decoded more than once, this is a strong indication
                    for an invalid IBF and the operation MUST be aborted. Notice that the decoded
                    element IDs are salted as described in <xref target="ibf_format_id_generation_pseudo_code" format="default" />
                    so the described bit rotation needs to be reverted before the decoded element ID
                    is stored and compared to the previous decoded element IDs.
                </t>
                <t>
                    If the IBF decodes more elements than are plausible, the
                    operation MUST be terminated. Furthermore, if the IBF
                    decoding successfully terminates and fewer elements were
                    decoded than plausible, the operation MUST also be terminated.
                    The upper thresholds for decoded elements from the IBF is the
                    remote set size the other peer has committed too (Case if the complete remote set is
                    new). The lower threshold for decoding element is the absolute value of the difference
                    between the local and remote set size (Case the set difference is only in the set of
                    a single peer). The other peer's committed set sizes
                    is transmitted in the the <strong>Expecting IBF</strong> state.
                </t>

                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            If an offer for an element, that never has been requested by
                            an inquiry or if an offer is received twice, the operation MUST be terminated.
                            This requirement can be fulfilled by saving lists that keep track of the state of
                            all sent inquiries and offers. When answering offers these lists MUST be checked.
                            The sending and receiving of <xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /> messages should
                            always be protected with an <xref target="security_generic_functions_mfc" format="title" />
                            to secure the protocol against missing, duplicated, out-of-order or unexpected messages.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            If an element that never has been requested by
                            a demand or is received twice, the operation MUST be terminated.
                            The sending and receiving of <xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /> messages should
                            always be protected with an <xref target="security_generic_functions_mfc" format="title" />
                            to secure the protocol against missing, duplicated, out-of-order or unexpected messages.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                        For every received demand an offer has to be sent in advance. If a demand
                        for an element is received, that never has been offered or the offer already has
                        been answered with a demand, the operation MUST be terminated. It is required to implement
                        a list which keeps track of the state of all sent offers and received demands.
                        The sending and receiving of <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> messages should
                        always be protected with an <xref target="security_generic_functions_mfc" format="title" />
                        to secure the protocol against missing, duplicated, out-of-order or unexpected messages.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            The <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message is only received if the IBF has finished
                            decoding and all offers have been sent. If the <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message is received before
                            the decoding of the IBF is finished or all open demands
                            have been answered, the operation MUST be terminated.
                            If the sets differ (the FINAL CHECKSUM field in the <xref target="messages_done" format="title" />
                            message does not match to the SHA-512 hash XOR sum of the local set), the operation has failed and the
                            reconciliation MUST be aborted. It is a strong indicator
                            that something went wrong (eg. some hardware bug). This should never occur!
                        </t>
                        <t>
                            When a <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message is received the
                            "check_if_synchronisation_is_complete()" function from the <xref target="security_generic_functions_mfc" format="title" />
                            is required to ensure that all demands have been satisfied successfully.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="security_states_finish_closing" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Finish Closing</name>
                <t>
                    In the  <strong>Finish Closing</strong> state the protocol waits for
                    all sent demands to be fulfilled.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In case not all sent demands have been answered in time,
                    the operation has failed and MUST be terminated.
                </t>
                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        When receiving <xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /> messages it is important
                        to always check the <xref target="security_generic_functions_mfc" format="title" />
                        to secure the protocol against missing, duplicated, out-of-order or unexpected messages.
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="security_states_finished" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Finished</name>
                <t>
                    In this state the connection is terminated, so no security considerations are needed.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="security_states_expect_se" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Expect SE</name>
                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_se" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            In case the strata estimator does not decode, the
                            operation MUST be terminated to prevent to get to an unresolvable state.
                            The set difference calculated from the strata estimator needs to be plausible,
                            which means within the byzantine boundaries described in section <xref target="security_generic_functions_check_byzantine_boundaries" format="title" />.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="security_states_full_receiving" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Full Receiving</name>
                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_full_element" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            When receiving full elements there needs to be checked, that every
                            element is a valid element, no element has been received more than once and
                            not more elements are received than the other peer committed
                            to sending at the beginning of the operation. The plausibility should also be checked
                            with an algorithm as described in <xref target="security_generic_functions_full_plausibility_check" format="default"/>.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            When the <em><xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" /></em> message is received from the remote peer, it should be checked that the number of
                            elements received matches the number that the remote peer
                            originally committed to transmitting,
                            otherwise the operation MUST be terminated.
                            If the sets differ (the FINAL CHECKSUM field in the <xref target="messages_full_done" format="title" />
                            message does not match to the SHA-512 hash XOR sum of the local set), the operation has failed and the
                            reconciliation MUST be aborted. It is a strong indicator
                            that something went wrong (eg. some hardware bug). This should never occur!
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="security_states_passive_decoding" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Passive Decoding</name>
                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                            In case an <xref target="messages_ibf" format="title" /> message is received by the peer a active/passive role switch
                            is initiated by the active decoding remote peer.
                            A switch into active decoding mode MUST only be permitted for
                            a predefined number of times as described in <xref target="security_generic_functions_active_passive_switches" format="default"/>
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        <t>
                        A check needs to be in place that prevents receiving an inquiry
                        for an element multiple times or more inquiries than are plausible.
                        The upper thresholds for sent/received inquiries is the
                        remote set size the other peer has committed too (Case if the complete remote set is
                        new). The lower threshold for for sent/received inquiries is the absolute value of the
                        set difference between the local and remote set size
                        (Case the set difference is only in the set of a single peer).
                        The other peer's committed set sizes is transmitted in the the <strong>Expecting IBF</strong> state.
                        Beware that it is possible to get key collisions and an inquiry for the same key
                        can be transmitted multiple times, so the threshold should take this into account.
                        The sending and receiving of <em><xref target="messages_inquiry" format="title" /></em> messages should
                        always be protected with an <xref target="security_generic_functions_mfc" format="title" />
                        to secure the protocol against missing, duplicated, out-of-order or unexpected messages.
                        </t>
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        Same action as described for <em><xref target="messages_demand" format="title" /></em> message in section
                        <xref target="security_states_active_decoding" format="title"/>.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        Same action as described for <em><xref target="messages_offer" format="title" /></em> message in section
                        <xref target="security_states_active_decoding" format="title"/>.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        Same action as described for <em><xref target="messages_done" format="title" /></em> message in section
                        <xref target="security_states_active_decoding" format="title"/>.
                    </dd>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        Same action as described for <em><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></em> message in section
                        <xref target="security_states_active_decoding" format="title"/>.
                    </dd>

                </dl>
            </section>
            <section anchor="security_states_finish_waiting" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Finish Waiting</name>
                <t>
                    In the  <strong>Finish Waiting</strong> state the protocol waits for
                    all transmitted demands to be fulfilled.
                </t>
                <t>
                    In case not all transmitted demands have been answered at this time, the operation
                    has failed and the protocol MUST be terminated with an error.
                </t>
                <t>Security considerations for received messages:</t>
                <dl>
                    <dt><xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /></dt>
                    <dd>
                        When receiving <xref target="messages_elements" format="title" /> messages it is important
                        to always check the <xref target="security_generic_functions_mfc" format="title" />
                        to secure the protocol against missing, duplicated, out-of-order or unexpected messages.
                    </dd>
                </dl>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="constants" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Constants</name>
        <t>
            The following table contains constants used by the protocol. The constants marked with a * are
            validated through experiments in <xref target="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" format="default"/>.
        </t>
        <figure anchor="figure_constants">
            <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Name                        | Value      | Description
----------------------------+------------+-------------------------------
SE_STRATA_COUNT             | 32         | Number of IBFs in a strata
                                           estimator.
IBF_HASH_NUM*               | 3          | Number of times an element is
                                           hashed to an IBF.
                                           (from section 4.5.2)
IBF_FACTOR*                 | 2          | The factor by which the size
                                           of the IBF is increased in
                                           case of decoding failure or
                                           initially from the set
                                           difference.
                                           (from section 4.5.2)
MAX_BUCKETS_PER_MESSAGE     | 1120       | Maximum bucket of an IBF
                                           that are transmitted in
                                           single message.
IBF_MIN_SIZE*               | 37         | Minimal number of buckets
                                           in an IBF. (from section 3.8)
DIFFERENTIAL_RTT_MEAN*      | 3.65145    | The average RTT that is
                                           needed for a differential
                                           synchronisation.
SECURITY_LEVEL*             | 2^80       | Security level for
                                           probabilistic security
                                           algorithms. (from section 5.8)
PROBABILITY_FOR_NEW_ROUND*  | 0.15       | The probability for a IBF
                                           decoding failure in the
                                           differential synchronisation
                                           mode. (from section 5.4)
DIFFERENTIAL_RTT_MEAN*      | 3.65145    | The average RTT that is needed
                                           for a differential
                                           synchronisation.
                                           (from section 4.5.3)
MAX_IBF_SIZE                | 1048576    | Maximal number of buckets in
                                           an IBF.
AVG_BYTE_SIZE_SE*           | 4221       | Average byte size of a single
                                           strata estimator.
                                           (from section 3.4.3)
VALID_NUMBER_SE*            | [1,2,4,8]  | Valid number of SE's
                                           (from section 3.4)
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>

     </section>
        <section anchor="gana" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>GANA Considerations</name>
            <t>
                GANA is requested to amend the "GNUnet Message Type" <xref target="GANA" format="default"/> registry
                as follows:
            </t>
            <figure anchor="figure_purposenums">
                <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
Type    | Name                       | References | Description
--------+----------------------------+------------+----------------------
 559    | SETU_P2P_REQUEST_FULL      | [This.I-D] | Request the full set
                                                    of the other peer.
 710    | SETU_P2P_SEND_FULL         | [This.I-D] | Signals to send the
                                                    full set to the other
                                                    peer.
 560    | SETU_P2P_DEMAND            | [This.I-D] | Demand the whole
                                                    element from the
                                                    otherpeer, given
                                                    only the hash code.
 561    | SETU_P2P_INQUIRY           | [This.I-D] | Tell the other peer
                                                    to send a list of
                                                    hashes that match
                                                    an IBF key.
 562    | SETU_P2P_OFFER             | [This.I-D] | Tell the other peer
                                                    which hashes match
                                                    a given IBF key.
 563    | SETU_P2P_OPERATION_REQUEST | [This.I-D] | Request a set union
                                                    operation from a
                                                    remote peer.
 564    | SETU_P2P_SE                | [This.I-D] | Strata Estimator
                                                    uncompressed.
 565    | SETU_P2P_IBF               | [This.I-D] | Invertible Bloom
                                                    Filter slices.
 566    | SETU_P2P_ELEMENTS          | [This.I-D] | Actual set elements.
 567    | SETU_P2P_IBF_LAST          | [This.I-D] | Invertible Bloom
                                                    Filter Last Slices.
 568    | SETU_P2P_DONE              | [This.I-D] | Set operation is
                                                    done.
 569    | SETU_P2P_SEC               | [This.I-D] | Strata Estimator
                                                    compressed.
 570    | SETU_P2P_FULL_DONE         | [This.I-D] | All elements in
                                                    full synchronisation
                                                    mode have been sent
                                                    is done.
 571    | SETU_P2P_FULL_ELEMENT      | [This.I-D] | Send an actual
                                                    element in full
                                                    synchronisation mode.

           ]]></artwork>
            </figure>
        </section>
        <!-- gana -->
        <section anchor="contributors" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Contributors</name>
            <t>
	        The GNUnet implementation of the byzantine fault tolerant set reconciliation
	        protocol was originally implemented by Florian Dold.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references>
            <name>Normative References</name>
            &RFC5869;
            &RFC2119;
            &RFC3385;
            &RFC1951;

            <reference anchor="byzantine_fault_tolerant_set_reconciliation" target="https://summermatter.net/byzantine-fault-tolerant-set-reconciliation-summermatter.pdf">
                <front>
                    <title>Byzantine Fault Tolerant Set Reconciliation</title>
                    <author initials="E." surname="Summermatter" fullname="Elias Summermatter">
                        <organization>University of Applied Sciences Bern</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date year="2021"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="GANA" target="https://gana.gnunet.org/">
                <front>
                    <title>GNUnet Assigned Numbers Authority (GANA)</title>
                    <author>
                        <organization>GNUnet e.V.</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date month="April" year="2020"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="CryptographicallySecureVoting" target="https://git.gnunet.org/bibliography.git/plain/docs/ba_dold_voting_24aug2014.pdf">
                <front>
                    <title>Cryptographically Secure, Distributed Electronic Voting</title>
                    <author initials="F." surname="Dold" fullname="Florian Dold">
                        <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
                    </author>
                </front>
            </reference>


            <reference anchor="ByzantineSetUnionConsensusUsingEfficientSetReconciliation" target="https://doi.org/10.1186/s13635-017-0066-3">
                <front>
                    <title>Byzantine set-union consensus using efficient set reconciliation</title>
                    <author initials="F." surname="Dold" fullname="Florian Dold">
                        <organization>Technische Universität München</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="C." surname="Grothoff" fullname="Christian Grothoff">
                        <organization>Inria, Domaine de Voluceau Rocquencourt</organization>
                    </author>
                </front>
            </reference>
            <reference anchor="Eppstein" target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2018436.2018462">
                <front>
                    <title>What’s the Difference? Efficient Set Reconciliation without Prior Context</title>
                    <author initials="D." surname="Eppstein" fullname="David Eppstein">
                        <organization>U.C. Irvine</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="M." surname="Goodrich" fullname="Michael T. Goodrich">
                        <organization>U.C. Irvine</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="F." surname="Uyeda" fullname="Frank Uyeda">
                        <organization>U.C. San Diego</organization>
                    </author>
                    <author initials="G." surname="Varghese" fullname="George Varghese">
                        <organization>U.C. San Diego</organization>
                    </author>
                </front>
            </reference>

            <reference anchor="GNS" target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-12280-9_9">
                <front>
                    <title>A Censorship-Resistant, Privacy-Enhancing and Fully Decentralized Name System</title>
                    <author initials="M." surname="Wachs" fullname="Matthias Wachs">
                        <organization>Technische Universitaet Muenchen</organization>
                    </author>

                    <author initials="M." surname="Schanzenbach" fullname="Martin Schanzenbach">
                        <organization>Technische Universitaet Muenchen</organization>
                    </author>

                    <author initials="C." surname="Grothoff"
                            fullname="Christian Grothoff">
                        <organization>Technische Universitaet Muenchen</organization>
                    </author>
                    <date year="2014"/>
                </front>
            </reference>

        </references>
        <section anchor="test_vectors" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>Test Vectors</name>
            <section anchor="test_vectors_map_function" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Map Function</name>
                <t>
                    INPUTS:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="test_vectors_map_function_inputs">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
k: 3
ibf_size: 300

key1: 0xFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF (64-bit)
key2: 0x0000000000000000 (64-bit)
key3: 0x00000000FFFFFFFF (64-bit)
key4: 0xC662B6298512A22D (64-bit)
key5: 0xF20fA7C0AA0585BE (64-bit)
           ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    OUTPUT:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="test_vectors_map_function_outputs">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
key1: ["122","157","192"]
key2: ["85","243","126"]
key3: ["208","101","222"]
key4: ["239","269","56"]
key5: ["150","104","33"]
           ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section anchor="test_vectors_id_function" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>ID Calculation Function</name>
                <t>
                    INPUTS:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="test_vectors_id_function_inputs">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
element 1: 0xFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF (64-bit)
element 2: 0x0000000000000000 (64-bit)
element 3: 0x00000000FFFFFFFF (64-bit)
element 4: 0xC662B6298512A22D (64-bit)
element 5: 0xF20fA7C0AA0585BE (64-bit)
           ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    OUTPUT:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="test_vectors_id_function_outputs">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
element 1: 0x5AFB177B
element 2: 0x64AB557C
element 3: 0xCB5DB740
element 4: 0x8C6A2BB2
element 5: 0x7EC42981
           ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>
            <section anchor="test_counter_compression_function" numbered="true" toc="default">
                <name>Counter Compression Function</name>
                <t>
                    INPUTS:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="test_counter_compression_function_inputs">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
counter serie 1: [1,8,10,6,2] (min bytes 4)
counter serie 2: [26,17,19,15,2,8] (min bytes 5)
counter serie 3: [4,2,0,1,3] (min bytes 3)
           ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
                <t>
                    OUTPUT:
                </t>
                <figure anchor="test_counter_compression_function_outputs">
                    <artwork name="" type="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
counter serie 1: 0x18A62
counter serie 2: 0x3519BC48
counter serie 3: 0x440B
           ]]></artwork>
                </figure>
            </section>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
